<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Medicina instaurata, or, A brief account of the true grounds and principles of the art of physick with the insufficiency of the vulgar way of preparing medicines, and the excellency of such as are made by chymical operation : whereto is added a short but plain discourse as a light to the true preparation of animal and vegetable arcana's : together with a discovery of the true subject of the philosophick mineral mercury ... as also some small light to the preparation of and use of the said mercury ... / by Edward Bolnest ... ; also an epistolary discourse upon the whole by the author of Medela medicinæ.</title>
            <author>Bolnest, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 224 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33237</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13110095</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13110095</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97616</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28604)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97616)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1544:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Medicina instaurata, or, A brief account of the true grounds and principles of the art of physick with the insufficiency of the vulgar way of preparing medicines, and the excellency of such as are made by chymical operation : whereto is added a short but plain discourse as a light to the true preparation of animal and vegetable arcana's : together with a discovery of the true subject of the philosophick mineral mercury ... as also some small light to the preparation of and use of the said mercury ... / by Edward Bolnest ... ; also an epistolary discourse upon the whole by the author of Medela medicinæ.</title>
                  <author>Bolnest, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36], 151 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Starkey ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MEDICINA INSTA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATA,</hi> OR; A Brief Account of the true GROUNDS And PRINCIPLES of the Art of PHYSICK.</p>
            <p>With the Inſufficiency of the Vulgar way of Preparing <hi>Medicines,</hi> and the Excellency of ſuch as are made by <hi>Chymical</hi> Operation.</p>
            <p>Whereto is added, a ſhort, but plain Diſcourſe, as a Light to the true Preparation of <hi>Animal</hi> and <hi>Vegetable Arcana's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with a Diſcovery of the true Subject of the <hi>Philoſophick Mineral Mercury,</hi> and that from the Authorities of the moſt Famous of Philoſophers.</p>
            <p>As alſo ſome ſmall Light to the Preparation and Uſe of the ſaid <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the diſſolution of <hi>Minerals</hi> and <hi>Metals,</hi> for a Phyſical Uſe.</p>
            <p>By EDVVARD BOLNEST. Med. <hi>Lond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo an Epiſtolary Diſcourſe upon the whole, by the Author of <hi>Medela Medicinae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Starkey</hi> at the <hi>Mitre</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Temple-Barr.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS GRACE <hi>GEORGE,</hi> DUKE, Marqueſs, and Earl of <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CKINGHAM,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> PRESENT not this ſmall Piece unto Your Grace, with ſo large a Confidence and good Opinion, either of my own, or its worth, as to think it a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:97616:3"/>that Merits your Patronage and Protection; it is only out of Gratitude, and a Compliance with that good and juſt Adage, <hi>Qui aquam hauris puteum corona.</hi> Your Grace, being the greateſt and moſt conſtant Incourager, and Fautor, (that this Age hath produced) not only to Ingenuity in general, but alſo to my particular Self, (though the meaneſt of Nature's (now) Numerous Diſciples.) Give me leave to make it my Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to return an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for that ſignal Honour of Your Princely Countenance, and other Favours You have been pleaſed to confer on me; I offer it not (My Lord) for your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, You are One whom Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath already admitted, and
<pb facs="tcp:97616:3"/>her Self taught You in her own Schole, the Tract of her moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Operations; and being, as You are, (even to Admiration) above others, of a moſt ſubtile and quick Apprehenſion; and one, who by Your own moſt Noble and Acute Genius, Conceptions, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, and conſtant Manual Operations, have not only diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the Vanity of the Galenick way, but rendred Your Self moſt Perfect, as well in the Practick, as Theory of Experimental Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and conſequently are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly Stored, and Enriched with thoſe two worthy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable Attributes of the Learned, Judgment and Candor. I cannot appeal to ſuch another Judge, and Patron: Be pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:97616:4"/>therefore to accept of this my Mite, and from an improvement of my Talent, You may juſtly expect and challenge, and ſhall accordingly receive, a more large and ample Offering. In the mean time, I beg pardon for this trouble and preſumption, who, in all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Graces moſt humble, and moſt devoted Servant, <hi>Edward Bolneſt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_his_friend">
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:4"/>
            <head>To Doctor <hi>Edward Bolnest,</hi> at his Houſe in <hi>Jewen-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Cripplegate.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My honor'd Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you have vouchafed me the Sight of thoſe Papers which you intend for the Preſs, tis an Argument of extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Friendſhip; and a ſubmitting to my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſhews, that your Humility is as great as your Knowledge in the noblest part of Medicine. There are many other perſons of our <hi>Society,</hi> you might have pitch't on (to whom I pay a reverence and ſubmiſſion in point of <hi>Chymical Philoſophy</hi>) whoſe long labours in the Fire have qualified them to a degree of Eminency far above me, and on whoſe Judgment you might have more ſurely rested; but ſince it is ſo, that you have ſingled out me, the meaneſt of our
<pb facs="tcp:97616:5"/>Collegues, I will be free with you, and you and all the World ſhall have my Opinion, whether it be worth any thing or no.</p>
            <p>One thing in the Front pleaſeth me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly; and that is the name of that Excellent Perſon, my Lord Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi> one that knows you well, and how to value you; a Prince by Merit as well as Title: for whether you take him in the <hi>Chymical,</hi> or in his Politick capacity, he appears no leſs in either; and yet he can be greater, if he pleaſe, becauſe with ſo rare a Wit and other Abilities of mind, ſeated in a comely Body, I know not what he may not effect in Philoſophy and Politie, by plying his <hi>Laboratory</hi> at Home, and another at Court. Therefore 'tis fit he ſhould be your Patron, becauſe he is able to be your Judge.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe Noble Preparations, of whoſe vertues you give ſome Account to the World, whatever others may think, I can by Experience ſay, that in ſeveral Caſes I have found them the best that ever I met with. This is to do you Right, not to flatter you, becauſe you are above it; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> cauſe it is, that I have been In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental
<pb facs="tcp:97616:5"/>to pull you out of your privacy, and by perſwaſions brought you upon the publick Theatre, that men may know how learnedly and judiciouſly you can write, as well as operate; and that being thus openly ingaged in the Cauſe of <hi>Chymiſtry,</hi> the Adverſe party of Calumniators may be aſhamed, while they go about and tattle among the Women, and weaker ſort of Men, that we are a Company of <hi>Illiterate Profeſſors;</hi> and this, becauſe we have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome Perſons to aſſociate who have not been hooded in an Univerſity, though 'tis known they every day mend the work of their <hi>VVorſhips,</hi> and cure what they leave off as incurable by <hi>Galenick Remedies</hi> (of which 'tis like the World may ſhortly have ſufficient Information;) and if men may be justified by their Works, it will appear (how mean ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their Book-learning be) that the leaſt of them hath skill enough in Medicine, to furniſh a ſcore of the ordinary <hi>Maſter</hi> Drs. In the mean time, 'tis well we are not wanting of others who have a Reputation for Letters, and that we have you <hi>(Sir)</hi> for a Champion, you that can Inſtruct a Colledge, if need be. Therefore <hi>Macte tuâ virtute,</hi> go on as
<pb facs="tcp:97616:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:7"/>you have begun, that the Profeſſion of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick may be redeemed from that obloquie which the uſual unprofitable Learning, and idle pride of the Profeſſors, hath brought upon it among the People; and that from your Pen men may know, there is a way to true Phyſical Learning, which lies quite out of the Common <hi>Scholaſtick Road;</hi> and that we muſt paſs through the fire to it, while the fine Fellows are afraid to follow for fear of ſingeing their <hi>Scarlet.</hi> And yet 'tis pretty to obſerve, how ſome of them, now at last, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving moſt of the great Lords, and other Noble Gentlemen of Learning do prefer our way before the <hi>Galenick,</hi> are not aſhamed to cry out, that themſelves alſo are <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> and ſo no need of erecting a new Society upon the account of <hi>Chymiſtry;</hi> but alas, what hope is there of a due Reformation of Phyſick by Chymical Principles and Operations, in the hands of ſuch as make pretence of owning them, meerly to put by others that are faſt friends to the work? had not we, and our fellow-labourers, beſtirr'd our ſelves, to erect a <hi>New Colledge</hi> to give credit to the State of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, by putting People into a readier way of eaſe and Security, for their lives and
<pb facs="tcp:97616:7"/>Purſes, there had never been found a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the mouths of thoſe men, as if they all on a ſuddain were become the only Cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and the moſt Excellent Chymists, and that there needed no more toward the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good in this way of Medicine, than what they know; which, how little it is, God knows, and you <hi>(Sir)</hi> of all men, are most able to make appear.</p>
            <p>And give me leave to ſay, whoever reads and underſtands what you have written, will be of the ſame opinion: If not, 'tis becauſe they are peeviſh, and are of the number of thoſe that have been drawn in to pay <hi>five and twenty Pounds</hi> as a Teſt of their being the lawful Sons of thoſe two great Dreamers, <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen.</hi> You and I <hi>(Sir)</hi> have both been Univerſity men, and may (no doubt) pay our Fees when we pleaſe, and bring our formalities to <hi>London;</hi> but truly I would not willingly have you, nor my ſelf, loſe one Afternoons operation in your Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, for all the Honours Academical, and the Veniſon that helps to make them; and becauſe we have a mind all the days of our lives to be Learners, therefore we are not at leiſure to croſs the Sea, and return <hi>Doctors</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:8"/>as wiſe as we went. Not that we deſpiſe thoſe Academick Honours, but must needs ſigh to ſee what a matter of courſe it is grown, to ſee all manner of men proceed, ſome of which it were a Diſeaſe to converſe with, while they bring home little elſe beſides the vices, and the Atheiſm, or the Scholastick Pedantrie of other Nations; which Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in conferring thoſe Academick Titles ſo eaſily, do as good as tell us, it is not the formal Accoutrement of a <hi>Doctor</hi> that makes Him one indeed, but it only inables him with a fair ſhew to think well of himſelf, and gull the Vulgar, who not being able to penetrate into the ſubſtance, are apt to court the ſhadow, and admire an empty Title, and to expect ſomewhat from <hi>Maſter Doctor,</hi> becauſe by the ſound he ſeems to be Some-body: But I have heard it ſaid, that the <hi>Rectors</hi> of divers forein Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, when they have created ſuch a Doctor, have oftentimes laught in their Sleeves, and given him this Farewell, behind his back,
<pb facs="tcp:97616:8"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Accepimus Aurum,</l>
                  <l>Dimittimus Aſinum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But with what Opinion ſoever they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs Him, it is plain enough here what we find Him, and he uſually ſo far forgets his own Country, that when he comes home again, he falls to practice upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bodies with Exotick Principles, Methods, and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
            <p>As to our own Univerſities, I believe they are the most refined in <hi>Europe,</hi> and deſerve all the honour we can give them, becauſe they appear more wary in distribution of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; but 'tis a ſhame to ſee, that the great Body of Practicers ſhould be made up of ſuch Titular things as have been foisted up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Foreiners, or elſe by Alliance at home, the favour and recommendation of ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Uncle, or Couſin-Doctor, that hath had a Name, though perhaps little more of true Knowledge in Medicine than the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that he prefers; or elſe they come in Play, by liſting themſelves in the number of ſome numerous party, or by colloguing with Midwives, Nurſes, and old Woman and
<pb facs="tcp:97616:9"/>courting or humouring the Younger, in order to the getting of a Name. And thus they proceed Doctors again, after they come from the Univerſities.</p>
            <p>Really, (Sir) to ſee, and talk of theſe things, as You and I have done, would make any Man almoſt forſwear the Study, if not the Practice of Phyſick, whoſe own Internal worth will not permit him to deſcend ſo low, as to uſe theſe little Arts, for the gaining of a Trade, and yet ſhall find very ſmall Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Fellows which uſe them, to riſe equal to himſelf, and ſometimes above him, in the noiſe of the World. And thus it will always be, while Phyſick hath no other Advance in the World than what the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> can give it: For, to ſay truth, our Art must needs be at a ſtand, while old Notions and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines are in faſhion, and while old Authors are ſet up as the only Standard, whereby to try Doctrines and Experiments both Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical and Medicinal; and there is no way to redeem our Profeſſion out of the hands of old Women, and others, but by ſetting the whole frame of Phyſick upon a new foot of Operative and Experimental Philoſophy, becauſe the common Methods and Remedies
<pb facs="tcp:97616:9"/>are every where to be had in Print, and, in a Twelvemonths time, any Perſon of good Parts and Induſtry, may as amply be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, as most of the Maſter-Doctors that walk with their Patients in the wonted Road to another World. And hence it is, that the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> are ſo eager for a power to hedge in the Common, for fear it may be over-ſtock'd, and to ſuppreſs, or deterr, all others from entring into what they would fain make their own Propriety, ſeeing it is an eaſie matter for ingenious Men, that have a mind to quit other Employments, to betake themſelves to this, and in a ſhort time to be as Wiſe as any that would be thought the only Learned, upon the account of having read the <hi>Galenick Inſtitutions,</hi> Commentators, and Practicers; whereas on the other ſide, we, who profeſs Chymical Principles and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, are never better pleaſed, than when we hear of numbers of Profeſſors and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators coming in to us, becauſe we know <hi>the Harveſt is great, and the true Labourers few;</hi> there are in the field of Nature, yet undiſcover'd, Secrets enough for Ages to fetch forth, and to find work for all the World, ſo that it were happy for us, if all the great
<pb facs="tcp:97616:10"/>Lords, and Gentlemen of <hi>England,</hi> would (as the King himſelf, and divers of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, have given an excellent example) erect Laboratories of their own, and ſpend time in the invention of Remedies more ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and of a Philoſophy more conducible, to cure the Diſeaſes of this Age; for, then thoſe noble Perſonages finding by experience, how much more of worth and uſe is attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, beyond what is contained in the <hi>Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> Books, or is in Vogue among ſuch idle Book-men, would ſoon ſpue them out of their Houſes, and in their ſtead entertain the true Sons and Labourers of Art and Nature, who are in Truth, if not in Title, the only Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, becauſe they are able to teach the other what Phyſick is indeed.</p>
            <p>And this you <hi>(my noble Friend)</hi> have ſufficiently ſhewn in your Learned Papers: They, whether Learned or no in their Own way, are obſtinately ignorant of Ours, and ſo, not competent Judges of Us or Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty; We, for our parts, dare profeſs as much of Scholaſtick Learning in their way as most of themſelves, and ſo take our ſelves to be the more competent Judges of the ſtate of Medicine, becauſe, beſides what we know
<pb facs="tcp:97616:10"/>of our own way, we are alſo Masters of theirs; and we ought the rather to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, if, after having had a through acquaintance with theirs, we have caſhired it, and pitch'd upon the <hi>Chymical,</hi> as the most ſafe, ſatisfactory, and beneficial for Mankind. Therefore, before I return the Papers, give me leave to kiſs ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of yours; as when you profeſs you have not taken up this way of Phyſick, but after a ſtrict (though fruitleſs) ſearch for ſatisfaction in the other;</p>
            <p>That, having found the vulgar Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines ſo compoſed, that the nobler part in them, being clogg'd with foeculential Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities, is made ineffectual, there appears a neceſſity of freeing Materials Medicinal from them, and of exalting thoſe to a more Active and Spirituous nature;</p>
            <p>That, after a due conſideration of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables</hi> and <hi>Animals,</hi> you found greater Virtues are contained in the later; yet after theſe, conſidering the <hi>Mineral</hi> and <hi>Metalline</hi> Subjects, you found by experience, as well as reaſon, that they are indued with far greater Virtues, and that, if rightly prepared, they are of all Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines
<pb facs="tcp:97616:11"/>the moſt ſafe and efficacious; And that, after long inquiry and diligence, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way or method how to purifie and exalt the reſtaurative Powers of all the three ſorts of Subjects, having attained it, then at length you fully reſolved to leave the old <hi>Galenical Road,</hi> and betake your ſelf (for the main) in your practice, to the uſe of <hi>Chymical Remedies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This judicious proceeding of yours is moſt highly to be commended; and he, who hath tried, or ſhall try the Excellency of your Medicines, ſhall find you have ſaid the Truth. Alas, theſe few that you intend to publiſh, are but a ſmall part of thoſe noble Preparations which I know you to be Master of, and of which the World is not worthy; and how great a Master of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as well as a Work-man, you are, may be ſeen by your Philoſophiſing upon the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Vomits,</hi> and the cauſes of <hi>Agues,</hi> and <hi>Fevers,</hi> as alſo by your profound Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe touching the grand <hi>Mercurial Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor,</hi> or <hi>Eſſence,</hi> a <hi>Menſtruum</hi> that will diſſolve and radically reduce all Metals to their first moist and unctuous form, by which, wonders may be effected in Phyſick,
<pb facs="tcp:97616:11"/>and otherwiſe; and, if ever our Nation come to ſee thoſe great Things, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but cloudily talk of, I that have ſeen you in your Way, and daily Labours, have cauſe to tell Men, that, I believe, you are the Man we muſt be beholden to for the diſcovery.</p>
            <p>Thus much to you <hi>(my dear Friend)</hi> without Flattery, for, you know, I abhor it, and have in my Nature (like you) too much of a <hi>Satyr</hi> to be a Flatterer; I ſhall now only add a few words concerning ſome Intimations that you have given me. The first is, of a Book in Anſwer to my <hi>Mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Medicinae,</hi> which the Author, very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known (unleſs it be at ſome certain Coffee-Houſes) is pleaſed to entitle <hi>Medela Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantiae,</hi> and in his Title-page he thinks fit to tell the World I am <hi>Illiterate;</hi> but who or what he is, ſcarce any body can tell, and ſo 'tis imagined he hath taken this courſe to provoke me to make him known; therefore I ſuppoſe the only way to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on him is, to ſpoile his deſign by not vouchſafing to name him: And in Letters at length he ſtiles himſelf <hi>Doctor of Phyſick,</hi> as perhaps he may be; for,
<pb facs="tcp:97616:12"/>there are too many ſlight fellows about this Town, that bring no credit to Univerſities, yet have the confidence to wear the Title, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of the Gang being meer Inſects and Imperfect Animals in the Faculty, to ſay nothing of their Idleneſs. I remember, in <hi>Scaliger</hi>'s Epiſtles, he having been told, that an obſcure Fellow had written malepartly against him, expreſſeth himſelf thus, <hi>Mihi relatum fuit, Scarabeum quendam contra me ſcribere, cui reſpondere neque dignitatis eſt, nec otii: I have been told</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that a certain Scarabee writes againſt me, to whom I have neither leiſure, nor doth it become me, to give an Anſwer.</hi> Indeed the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is as unfortunate in his Attempt, as one can be, by pretending to anſwer me, yet I perceive, he hath not ſo much as touched any main string of my Book; onely he endeavours by railing, and with whole Pages of Greek, (for edification of the Engliſh Reader) to juſtifie the Aphoriſms of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and other things of his and <hi>Galen</hi>'s, which I ſaid (and ſtill ſay) are grown out of date, as moſt is that they have written; which. I can, and will make good, againſt all the <hi>Galenick Societies</hi> in <hi>Europe;</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:97616:12"/>though he hardly allows me more than Engliſh, yet I can find Greek enough (and had at fourteen years of Age) to ſerve him and twenty more of the ſame Tribe. But alas <hi>(Sir) hard words cure no Diſeaſes,</hi> unleſs they be Characteristick Charms, and without ſuch as theſe, not a man of the old Faction knows how to conjure down a poor Ague, whilst the old Women and Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks every where do ſhame them, even quite out of City and Country.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, as Illiterate as I am, I am content to ſhare in the Imputation with other Brethren of our Society; the whole Buſineſs of the old Brotherhood is now to brand us with <hi>no Letters,</hi> but they ſhall find we have; and this <hi>vir Trium Literarum</hi> may in time come to underſtand it, as well as the reſt. I hear alſo, that there are other ſmall Beagles at the Preſs, ready to open againſt me; but thoſe little Doctoral, Fellows are to know, neither I nor the Book-buyers ſhall take notice of them, in a Conteſt which it rather concerns their grave and formal Leaders to clear, if they can, and the World hath reaſon to expect it from them. But if what I have done will not
<pb facs="tcp:97616:13"/>ſerve to ſettle their minds, I promiſe you they ſhall have enough; for as my manifold diverſions give leave, I am collecting for them.</p>
            <p>As to the Reports ſown up and down by ſome of the <hi>Grave Sirs,</hi> as alſo by their Pedees of the Faculty, as for example, That I was chidden rather than countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at our Audience at the King's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil-Table; you know the contrary, and with what Princely Grace an ear was given to every man of us: ſo that things are like to thrive with our Adverſaries when their Refuge is in Lies. But they go further yet, and whiſper up and down, that I proclaim all people to have the <hi>Pox,</hi> and I know not what; whereas 'tis plain, I maintain in my Book no more than this, that ſince the prevalencie of that diſeaſe in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Europe</hi> it hath exceedingly alter'd their Nature, and the Nature of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, ſo that the old definitions of the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> and their dull Remedies, do not reach any conſiderable Maladies; but if you, and I, and others that I know, be Maſters of ſuch Specifick Medicines as will do the Work, when theirs cannot, I ſuppoſe
<pb facs="tcp:97616:13"/>'tis eaſie to conclude from the Nature of our Medicines the Truth of my Poſition, That even thoſe who never were formally infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, may yet by Contagion at a diſtance, Inheritance, and divers other ways, come under a Fermental Change in the Frame and Conſtitution of their Bodies.</p>
            <p>Others there are of the Faculty, that would fain ſeem to be more wiſe than their Brethren, and they forſooth do acknowledg, There is ſuch an alteration in the State of Diſeaſes as I contend for, but they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all tell men, that they knew ſo before, and that I needed not have taken ſo much pains to convince them of it: But if they did know ſo, the more—They for conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; and why then do they not alter the State of Medicine, exclude the Old un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Remedies, and introduce new ones more effectual, Agreeable to ſuch Alteration of Maladies? Why is it that the Bead-row of Antiquated Remedies, invented by Forein Authors, and Calculated for other kind of Climates, is ſtill held forth as ſufficient under the name of <hi>Pharmacopeia,</hi> ſeeing (as I hope ſhortly to make appear) there is not one Medicine in the whole Book that
<pb facs="tcp:97616:14"/>will reach any one radicated or deplorable Diſtemper?</p>
            <p>But they ſay, That what ever is wanting there in Vertue of Medicine, they can ſupplie in the uſe of them by strength of Wit, which is that they call <hi>Method.</hi> Oh, here is the <hi>Diana,</hi> the great Goddeſs <hi>Method,</hi> or the <hi>Round of the Mill-horſe,</hi> which every one can run that hath bought <hi>Sennertus,</hi> or <hi>Riverius</hi> in Engliſh; and that is the Reaſon why other Folk ſpoil their Trade much more than the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> do, and for thirty or forty ſhillings worth of Books, ſoon learn to become as compleat <hi>Methodiſts</hi> as themſelves: Whereas you know <hi>(Sir)</hi> that Medicines ſhould alter as Diſeaſe alter, and ſhould be ſo made as to command <hi>Method,</hi> and when a Noble Medicine is once found, it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits in the uſage no Method but what is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to it ſelf, and reſults out of its own Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral power and propriety, and thereby inables him that is acquainted with its energie, to puzzle and fool him that ſails only by the Card and Compaſs of Books. And if Men will not believe words, thoſe few Medicines which you mean to publiſh, and more which you and I know of, and others of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious
<pb facs="tcp:97616:14"/>Aſſociates, will abundantly convince them, if they pleaſe to obſerve the admirable Operations and effects, in little time, and ſmall Quantities.</p>
            <p>They ſay alſo, after they have abuſed the Apothecaries in publick, when they lately endeavored to get a power to inſlave them, that I chalk out the way to the undoing of their Trade; whereas the Truth is, I only point out the way they must go to preſerve their Trade; for, I know none of our Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety that ever thought of diſobliging them, but when we have ſettled our publick place or College, with a grand Laboratory ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſo worthy an Undertaking, we pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (God willing) to turn the ſtream of Practice out of the <hi>Galenick Channel,</hi> and furniſh the Apothecaries with ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations at reaſonable rates, upon the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of our Society, as may inable us to correſpond with that ingenious Company, by ſending our Bills to them, and employing them with a fuller Trade, more for the Reputation of the Profeſſion of Phyſick, and of themſelves, as ſuch of them who will looſen their dependence upon <hi>Formaliſts,</hi> and come over to us in compliance, ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:97616:15"/>quickly find; in the mean while, 'tis but reaſon they ſhould practiſe with their own Medicines, ſeeing the Road and Method of uſing them is open and plain to every one that can read; and more Trust is to be given to the Skill that comes by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in the preſent time, than by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Authors of other times and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, who could not poſſibly leave directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Books, to fit the preſent State of Men and Diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Conſider that deplorable diſeaſe the <hi>Lues Venerea;</hi> of what Value are all the Rules and Remedies of writers? He that in this Age, when the Diſeaſe is quite another thing than it was twenty or thirty years ago, ſhall attempt the Cure of it with the old Meſſes, or the common Mineral Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, will be extreamly mistaken, and that is the reaſon of ſo many Semi-Cures and Relapſes. What ſignifie all the tedious Decoctions of <hi>Guajac, Sarſa, &amp;c.</hi> which you never uſed, and I have long ſince given over? A few of your <hi>Solar Pills,</hi> no big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than Pepper-corns, ſhall effect far more than Firkins of Diet-Drink, to ſay nothing of other high <hi>Arcanaes</hi> which no wit can
<pb facs="tcp:97616:15"/>reach that hath not your Skil and Induſtry in Operation, with which I have ſeen dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſeaſes Removed, as it were by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment.</p>
            <p>The World hath no cauſe to ſuſpect You, or Me, to be out of love with Learning; and yet I ſay, the common Learning, that is in uſe for gaining Knowledge in Phyſick, ſerves rather to puzzle and confound than inform a Student, eſpecially the ſingle fangle Notions about Anatomy, foraſmuch as the Inveſtigation of Cauſes, and the Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating of Curations, <hi>Secundùm Ductus Anatomicos,</hi> and <hi>Secundùm Artem,</hi> have Slain their ten Thouſands, and will do more, if Matters be not amended by Men of other Principles, and who labour night and day another way, to apprehend the manner of Nature's Operations, with the various <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena</hi> of Diſeaſes in Man's Body, and how Medicines may be made of ſo compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive a Power, as to anſwer all particulars, and ſupply all the defects of Ratiocination or Opinion, which is generally the meer product of Phant'ſie.</p>
            <p>'Tis not fit (my Friend) I ſhould quite tire you; I ſhall only add, that what I
<pb facs="tcp:97616:16"/>have Written in my <hi>Medela,</hi> I have no Cauſe to repent of; <hi>Habent ſua fata Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belli,</hi> Books have their Fates, and mine hath had the Luck (ſo great is the force of Truth) to find a general acceptation in the Land, eſpecially among the Nobler and the Learneder part, (from many of which I have received Thanks) yea, and among all Phyſicians that are not of the Intereſſed Faction; and yet even ſome of them have been ſo Ingenious, as to confeſs, I have in many things done well, only they ſay, I ſhould not have publiſhed ſo much in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh: But I would ask them, Why am I faulted for this? Did not the Old repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Princes of the Profeſſion write all they wrote in their own Country-Languages? as <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> in Greek; the Arabian <hi>Avicen</hi> and his Fellows in Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick; therefore, if I have eſpied faults in the common Doctrines and Practice, why ſhould not our Country-men be made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them, ſeeing they are the Perſons that are concerned, and most likely to promote that which the ſplendid Faction oppoſe? Who would fain hold up the old Myſtery, not the Art, but the Craft of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:16"/>
            <p>One would wonder, after all the reaſon that hath been given againſt the frequent ſpilling of precious Blood by <hi>Phlebotomie</hi> in our Climate, ſome Men ſhould ſtill have the madneſs to deal with us, as if we were in <hi>France, Italy,</hi> or <hi>Spain.</hi> For God's ſake <hi>(Sir)</hi> do you take them a little to task; for, I am weary and ſick of them, and I every day ſee the people begin to be ſo too: Their main ſhelter now is in ſome few noble Houſes; for, the generality de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them. If you would once more take Pen in hand, I dare ſay you would be able to give them a final Paſsport; and this I hope you will do, as ſoon as we have ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Affairs of our Society or College, which we hope, in as conſpicuous a manner as the <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> ſuddenly ſo to manage, as that it may conduce effectually to the end we aim at; which is the honour of Phyſick, by Men of ſound Chymical principles, Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and Learned. If any Perſons among us chance to be Defective in the common Literature, we ought not to value them the leſs, as long as they have ſo much of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort of Learning, as inableth them to the inventing excellent Remedies, ſuch as the
<pb facs="tcp:97616:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:18"/>vulgar Letter-men never had the honour to be acquainted with, by any Endeavour or Operation of their own.</p>
            <p>Forgive me (my noble Friend) all this tedious Diſcourſe, for, I could ſay a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more, and think you never the worſe of me, becauſe I am zealous in this Matter; but let me prevail with you to print your Papers as ſoon as you can; for, the true Sons of Art will be exceedingly pleaſed with it, and among the meaneſt of them, I that honour you, who am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithful Friend and Servant</hi> Mar. Nedham.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Thomas <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>10</hi> May <hi>1665.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:18"/>
            <p>Some <hi>Errata's</hi> have Slipt the Preſs, which thoſe that are not Malicious will Correct as they Read.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Licenſed,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>April</hi> 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:19"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97616:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MEDICINA INSTA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATA;</hi> OR, A brief Account of the true Grounds and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Art of PHYSICK.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Inding by a daily experience the ſmall virtue, efficacy, and power of the generality of Medicines, and the great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of performing any notable and worthy Cure, by their means and operation; I reſolved upon a more diligent ſearch and inquiry after ſuch Medicines, as, with confidence of ſome good effect, I might more fully rely upon,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97616:20"/>after a ſerious conſideration therefore of the cauſe why vulgar Remedies, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, ſo rarely or ſeldom performed the promiſed and expected Effects; I at laſt found the true and onely cauſe to be the great quantity of droſs and impurity by Nature in their production and growth ſtrongly united with the Medicinal or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaurative Eſſence, choaking and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering the true Phyſical part of them, ſo that it cannot, as it ſhould, perform its Office, and produce the deſired Effects it was adminiſtred for; for the body of Man being already clogged and ſtuffed up with Obſtructions, and Nature's royal courſe and prerogative being by that means hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and oppoſed, the Body by little and little feels the approaching decays of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and accordingly calls for a powerful and able aſſiſtance to free her (if poſſible) from thoſe Enemies of Life, that ſo Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>(Spiritus innatus &amp; custos corpori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oeconomus)</hi> the enlivening Inhabitant of the Body, being by ſome timely, ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical, and friendly aid and aſſiſtance (before her too great Debilitation) again impowred and re-inforced, may be able
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97616:20"/>to eject and caſt out her potent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Antagoniſt, and again re-aſſume her wonted and deſired courſe, and ſo reſtore the pining, pale and decayed Body to its priſtine blith, healthful, and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition. Being by theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other moſt ſtrong and undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Reaſons, ſufficiently confirmed what kind of Medicines Nature required, as moſt abſolutely neceſſary and needful; as alſo that the true cauſe of the weak effect of common or vulgar Medicines, was the Phyſical parts being ſo much over-ballanced and debilitated, and, as it were, extinguiſhed by the multiplicity of Dreggs and foeculential Impurities, cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly joyned and mixed with it in its Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and progreſſive Growth, I at laſt of neceſſity concluded, that the freeing of Medicinal Subjects (or thoſe things we would uſe in a Phyſical way) from ſome part (if not all) of thoſe their foeculen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, droſſy, and terrene parts, muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly (in reaſon) render the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of much more Efficacy and Power; of more power, becauſe of more purity, and, conſequently more ſpiritual and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97616:21"/>and becauſe more ſpiritual, therefore more fitting to aſſiſt the decayed and fainting Spirits of the infirm and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Body, and ſo (as being of her own condition or quality) re-inforce, inable, and aſſiſt Nature (the Body's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver) to expel and drive out her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent and health-deſtroying Oppoſers: And this certainly was the intent and meaning of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> where he tells us, <hi>Contraria contrariis curari debent:</hi> Contraries muſt be driven away, and cured by contraries, viz. <hi>Corruptibilia per incorruptibilia, immunda enim per munda &amp; non per immunda mundantur, &amp; purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur:</hi> Pure things only are fit to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie, and not dirty and impure; Diſeaſes are the beginnings of the corruption of the Body, and to remove corruption by corruption, or corrupting and corruptible things, the way and means rather to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and haſten it, to me ſeems (in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) impoſſible, as doubtleſs it is, and therefore could no ways be imagined to be the meaning of ſo Learned a Phyſitian; his meaning therefore muſt conſequently follow, that the Cure of Diſeaſes (the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97616:21"/>deſtruction and corruption of the Body) muſt needs be performed by ſomething of a contrary nature, <hi>viz.</hi> Incorruptible and pure: If therefore we would either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from, or drive out, Diſeaſes and Corruption, it muſt ſurely be by ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is of a pure and incorruptible <hi>Balſamick</hi> nature and property, which the generality of Medicines (as prepared) are ſo far from, that few or none of them (except ſome few Chymical, or having ſome of their Ingredients in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure purified) are able to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from a total Corruption, or at moſt a great diminution of their Virtues the ſpace of one poor Year, though with much care and vigilancy ſecured and fortified by a cloſe ſtoppage, from the ingreſſion of Air, the Introducer of Corruption into all Porous and corruptible things: The more pure the Medicine, the more potent its Virtue, and conſequently the better able to aſſiſt and ſtrengthen our continually ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted and ſpent Spirits, eſpecially when aſſaulted by a too powerful diſtemper (the effect of ſome corruption) their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemy: And this <hi>Galen</hi> (that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97616:22"/>
               <hi>Oraculum Medicinae,</hi> did we, as we ought, as much mind his Precepts, as make uſe of his Name for a cavilling, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, unprofitable Diſcourſe) moſt plainly tells us, <hi>Lib. undec. de ſimpl. med. facult. cap. undec.</hi> His words are theſe; <hi>Quae tenuium ſunt partium medicamenta, iis quae ſunt craſſarum partium pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s habent efficaciae, etiamſi parem ſortita fuerint facultatem, nimirum quia melius penetrant.</hi> All which in brief tells us thus much, That thoſe Medicines which are of thin or ſubtile parts, are of greater Efficacy and Virtue, than thoſe which are of a groſs quality, (and the Reaſon he alſo gives) becauſe by their thinneſs and ſubtilty they are the more apt and able to penetrate. Thus this once great and experienced Phyſician; he alſo much deſired to have the Aethereal and hot pure Subſtance, or Spirit of Wine, and alſo the Secret of Extracting and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating it from its more groſs, earthy, and watery parts, (an Artifice not known unto the Phyſicians of that Age) for conſidering how excellent, reviving, and cordial a Liquor Wine of it ſelf was, he according to his former Opinion alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97616:22"/>that the hot, pure, and aethereal Subſtance of it, <hi>viz.</hi> Its Spirit, ſeparated from its foeculential and droſſy Impurities, muſt of neceſſity be a moſt high, effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and truly Cordial Medicine. If then the more thin, ſubtile, and aethereal Medicines are the moſt effectual and powerful, the Subtiliſation of thick, groſs and impure, dull Phyſical Subjects, muſt of neceſſity render them far more pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating and noble Medicines: And in this doth that moſt acute Philoſopher and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, the noble <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> alſo ſecond and confirm the fore-mentioned <hi>Aphoriſm</hi> of <hi>Galen,</hi> onely with a little addition, or raiſing unto the height of it the purity of the ſupreme of Elements; his words are theſe: <hi>Tum demum medicamenta corpori accommodanda ad ignis naturam reducta, per hoc enim elementum omnis aegritudo conſumi debet à quolibet medico, Lib. de Vita longa</hi> [in 4.] Page 134. The ſence thus: Then, ſaith he, are Medicines fit to be adminiſtred, when by a due preparation they are made moſt pure, and exalted to the Nature, or Quality of Fire; for by this Element, (or Medicines of the nature
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97616:23"/>and property, or condition of this Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ought Phyſicians to cure Diſeaſes. All which is no more than a Phyſical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, Aphoriſm, and Inſtruction, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently high for the preparation of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, which ought to be of the nature of Fire, that is, moſt pure, ſubtile, ſpiritual and penetrating; for Fire is the moſt ſubtile, pure, and noble of the Elements, <hi>(in quo Deus omnium rerum Creator ſedem &amp; Majestatem ſuam poſuit,)</hi> and indeed the Seat and Chariot of the Divine and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Majeſty of God, &amp;c. We have here then the Precept and Opinion of the greateſt of the old Phyſicians, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniouſly agreeing, that the moſt ſubtile and pure Medicines are the moſt noble and efficacious, and therefore moſt fit and proper for the curing, extirpating, and rooting out of Diſeaſes, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The means to render Medicine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the ſubtil, thin, and penetrating Quality, of aſſiſting and ſtrengthning our over-oppreſſed and fainting Spirits, I found moſt certainly to be by purifying (as I ſaid before) of the Medicinal or Phyſical Subject deſigned for the Cure;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97616:23"/>this Purification, (or Purgation) I after much thought and meditation conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, could no way ſo advantagiouſly be performed and obtained, as by thoſe excellent, incomparable, and truly Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical preparations we uſually call Chymical, a way of making Medicines, (as well as a gate to Nature's choiceſt Secrets) of all other the moſt noble, and every way able to anſwer, yea, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlatively to exceed, the greateſt and higheſt of our deſires. Conſider (O Artiſt) the power and excellency of any one thing or ſubject as Nature hath prepared, created, and given it us ready into our hands! Conſider alſo with the excellency of it, as it is, what a height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned purgation and purification may exalt it to! Conſider the virtue and inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible power of ſpiritual and pure things! Conſider alſo what they may be, and do, being (after purification) fixed! Thou haſt here a very large Field for contemplation, and as large a Gate opened to give thee entrance into the Cloſet, or inmoſt Receſſes of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and her infinite Treaſures, &amp;c.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97616:24"/>But I may not inlarge any further.</p>
               <p>After a firm reſolution of the way of improving, heightning, and exalting the virtue and efficacy of Medicines, I alſo fell to conſider (after a full knowledge of the true Phyſical and Eſſential parts of things) what Subject or Species might yield theſe healing and reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Eſſences, in moſt and greateſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, and of moſt power and virtue; I perceived at laſt that ſome Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles did yield them in far greater plenty and quantity than others, and of a ſtronger and ſpeedier operation. After theſe, I conſidered the uſe of Animals in Phyſick, and learned the great effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, virtue, and ſtrength of them alſo, and that in them the Quinteſſential and Phyſical parts, were yet in greater plenty than in the moſt of Vegetables, and of a higher and more intenſe operation and perfection. I yet (after theſe) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the third and laſt Kingdom of Nature, (<hi>viz.</hi> the Mineral, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallin) and found by many Arguments (after a mature and deliberate Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeconded by Experience, a moſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97616:24"/>ſure guide and teacher) the great power, excellency and ſtrength, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon, and implanted (yea, concentrated) in them by Almighty God, (their great Creator, and Eternal fountain of overflowing and inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible Goodneſs) and have ſince by a continued Series of experience, (and that in ſeveral more than ordinary Caſes and Cures, as well as by the very ample, and yet deſerved teſtimony of moſt eminently Learned, both antient and modern, Phyſicians, the onely true and painful, but ingratefully rewarded, diſcoverers of Nature's unvaluable and admirable myſteries and power) even to admiration, been fully and often ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, that the virtue of Minerals and Metals (if rightly prepared) are of all others the moſt (ſafely) Efficacious, and far exceeding the power and virtue of Animals or Vegetables; yet are theſe two laſt named ſuch ſafe, potent, and benign aſſiſtants, and preſervers of the preſent, and reſtorers of the impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and decayed, health of Man, as, if well ordered, or prepared, and rightly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97616:25"/>applied, he ſhall have but little need of Minerals or Metals, though the nobleſt and beſt of all Phyſical Subjects, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Having by this continued and diligent Inquiſition, not only diſcovered and found out the cauſe of the too ſluggiſh, dull, and ineffectual operation and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of the bulk of ordinary and vulgar Medicines, but alſo attained unto the knowledg of the moſt Phyſical Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, both in the Animal, Vegetable, and Mineral Kingdom, together with the way and method of improving, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing, and raiſing their Innate power, and Medicinal reſtaurative faculties, to a very ſublime degree of purity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; I fully reſolved with my ſelf, to leave the old Galenical road, and apply my ſelf in my practice <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to the uſe of Chymical Medicines, ſome of which I ſhall in this ſmall Tract give ſome ſhort account of, and their virtues: For, conſidering that (care being firſt had of my particular and private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment) there was alſo (as not being Born altogether for my ſelf, nor to bury my Talent delivered unto me by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97616:25"/>God) ſomewhat of a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon me in relation to my doing ſomewhat towards a general good; I at laſt thought fit (being alſo by ſeveral of my Friends, who with much ſatisfaction and benefit had uſed and made trial of many of my Medicines, eſpecially my Solar Pills, daily perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and urged thereunto,) to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate ſomewhat in a more publick way, as well for others good, as my own private benefit, which as the Law of Nature commands, and allows, as moſt neceſſary firſt to provide for; ſo I will not in the leaſt deny, or pretend a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owning of. I here therefore preſent my Country with an offer, of ſix moſt noble, purified, and efficacious Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, pleaſantly and ſafely powerful in preſerving the preſent, and reſtoring (if God pleaſe) the decayed and loſt, health of Man, all prepared by the aforeſaid means and method of Chymical pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and purification: The true and full intent, ſcope and deſign of Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtry (what ever other definition or interpretation may enviouſly or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97616:26"/>be put upon it) being no other, nor to any other end or purpoſe, than to cleanſe, purge and refine whatever the Experienced and Learned Philoſopher and Phyſician intends for a Medicinal uſe, and to raiſe, exalt, and advance to a more than ordinary degree of purity and perfection.</p>
               <p>As to the Medicines ſpoken of in this Tractate (or ſmall Piece) I ſhall not by way of Apology or Preface, much enlarge my ſelf, but both briefly and confidently aſſure Thee, They are ſuch, as, if rightly uſed, will ſufficiently ſpeak their own worth; The firſt (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Solar</hi> Pill) will prove it ſelf ſecond to none, except that great and famous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinal Elixir, or Arcanum of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers; Its goodneſs being the ſame after an hundred years as at the firſt day of its making, Time rather adding than robbing or detracting any thing from its firſt native virtue, excellency and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The other five are truly of ſuch uſeful and noble Quality, that enough cannot be ſaid of them; I ſhall therefore as earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97616:26"/>and truly, as conciſely, affirm them to be moſt friendly, and as powerful as friendly aſſiſtants unto, and preſervers of a deſireable, healthful condition, and conſtitution of body, and as effectual in in reſtoring (by Gods bleſſing and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) the decayed and loſt health of Man, and indeed ſuch precious and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Remedies (and Medicines) as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſufficiently be eſteemed and valued; their vertues (if but any thing carefully and neatly kept) not waſting or decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the length of Time (that univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal deſtroyer of all corruptible things) and the reaſon is, becauſe they are true Quinteſſential and pure Medicines of a true balſamie nature, and ſuch as do not only defend and preſerve themſelves, but all other things, from the entrance of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Putrefaction; of what uſe, power and vertue therefore they may be to the infirm and ſickly, languiſhing under any tedious, troubleſome and chronick Diſeaſe, I leave thee at leiſure to conſider, and by the conſideration to improve thy knowledg of them and their worth.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97616:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Pilula Solaris.</head>
               <p>THis Noble and Excellent <hi>Panacaea,</hi> is ſo wonderfully a Friend unto the continually decaying Nature of corruptible Man, that whatever unnatural, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, and health-oppoſing humor it ſhall in the whole body of Man meet with, be it as the moſt Learned of the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> do aſſure us, either of Choler, Phlegm, Melancholy, or Impurity, or Corruption of blood, or proceeding or ſpringing (as the moſt acute and indefatigable Nature-ſearching <hi>Paracelſians</hi> do inform us) from a Saline, Sulphurous, or Mercurial matter, be it from whatſoever Cauſe, Source, or Fountain it will, and in whatſoever part of the Body it will (for it throughly ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and in ſearching purifieth, both Center and Circumference, that is, both the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and other chief bowels, together with the extreme parts) it doth by its tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleanſing and renewing quality in time radically extirpate and drive it out, and in its place conſtitutes, induceth, or rather creates (may I ſo ſay) a moſt ſound, flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97616:27"/>and healthful conſtitution of body: Its effects I have found ſo truly, and (to miracle) admirable, that I cannot but in full meaſure give credit to thoſe moſt high, and yet as highly and largely deſerved te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, which many, and thoſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Phyſicians, have given of the bare Subject out of which it is prepared; I ſhall for brevity inſtance the Atteſtation of four or five only, and begin with the noble and moſt expert <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> whoſe teſtimony of it runs thus <q>
                     <hi>Eſſentiam in ſe continet quae nihil impuri cum puro relinquit, nec ullus tam inſignis &amp; peritus ſpagirus eſt qui vires &amp; facultates ejus indagare queat, in prima enim Yle adeo exaltatum eſt &amp; inter ſubjecta ab aqua producta adeo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de inatum eſt, ut virtus &amp; facultas ejus nullo diluvio, inſtar aliorum aqueorum cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentium, imminuta aut abſorpta ſit, adeoque omnibus aliis praeſtat, hoc ſeipſam purgat, &amp; una ſecum etiam alia: quod ſi nihil boni in ſubjecto reperitur, impurum corpus in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſimum tranſmutat.</hi> Paracel. <hi>de vita lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga, pag.</hi> 146. 147. <hi>Arch. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 221.</q> The ſumm of which in Engliſh tels us thus. It contains in it ſelf an eſſence, which will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97616:28"/>not ſuffer any thing of impurity to remain with that which is pure; nor can the moſt skilful of <hi>Spagiriſts</hi> fully ſearch out, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, and manifeſt, the virtues of it: for in its firſt <hi>Yle,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or firſt moſt remote matter, for ſo I ſuppoſe he meaneth,) it is ſo exalted and amongſt all other Subjects produced by the Water, ſo predeſtinated, that its efficacy, power, and vertue, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, like other products of the water, be at all conſumed, or diminiſhed, it therefore excelleth all others, it purgeth it ſelf, and with it ſelf all others; and though almoſt nothing of good, of purity, be found in what we would apply it to, or better by it, yet it tranſmutes the impure into a moſt pure body.</p>
               <p>A ſecond, and he a moſt conſcientious and knowing Author, of the ſame Matter or Subject tells us thus: <q>
                     <hi>Studioſis opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè innoteſcit hocſubjectum, non unius gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae ſolummodo, ſed omnium lapidum pretio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum, omnium Mineralium &amp; Metallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vires &amp; virtutes in ſe continere,</hi> &amp;c.</q> The ſence of which in Engliſh take thus; It is well known to ſtudious Artiſts, that this <hi>(Solar)</hi> matter, doth not contain in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97616:28"/>it ſelf the vertue of one Gem alone, as others of this kind do, being attributed to one, but it univerſally contains the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of all Gems, Minerals, and Metals whatever; and by reaſon all vertues are in it, the life of man is too ſhort ever to learn and diſcover its high and wonderful <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's. Ba. Va. Mo. C. T. A. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A third both Famous and Modern Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, with admiration of the ſame, delivers himſelf thus: <q>
                     <hi>In eo ſunt Sexcentae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietates variae ac praeſtantes, ut,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ita ut nunquam ſatis laudari queat hoc medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum. Quercetan in Tetrad. Cap.</hi> 51.</q> In it, ſaith he, are ſix hundred various and excellent properties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And is, indeed, ſuch a Medicine as cannot ſufficiently be commended.</p>
               <p>A fourth, being the excellent and moſt acute Philoſopher and Phyſician, <hi>Peter Faber,</hi> though conciſely, yet moſt fully of the ſame matter, delivers us his Opinion and Judgment (with his moſt profitable experience) of it thus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>In hoc ſolo virtus &amp; proprietas Naturae Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Vegetabilis &amp; Mineralis, tanquam in Arca quadam, pretioſa &amp; Arcana, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97616:29"/>eſt, credat qui velit: Talentum a deo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi concreditum libenter, propter humani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris ſalutem &amp; neceſſitatem, omnibus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municare non erubeſco: gratias agent qui hac de re experientia certiores facti juerint; uſus ſum per viginti annos, &amp; adhuc utor, in curatione omnium morborum, &amp; nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam adhuc deluſus fui ab ipſo medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento, nec deluſi fuerunt aegroti mei, qui ab ipſo ſolo medicamento liberati ſunt a morbis quam maximis incurabilibus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pet. Johan. Faber. Sap. univerſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 201. 202. 227. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> The Engliſh to this effect: In this alone (he ſaith ſpeaking of a Phyſical preparation of the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject) is the entire virtue and property of the Animal, Vegetable, and Mineral Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as it were in a Cheſt or pretious Cabinet, cloſely ſhut up and contained: thoſe that will may believe it; I moſt willingly, for the good of Mankind, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Talent beſtowed upon me by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, thoſe who by experience ſhall find the truth of it will be thankful: I have uſed it, now, this twenty years, and do ſtill uſe it, in the cure of all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; Nor have I or my Patients ever
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97616:29"/>yet been deluded or deceived by it, but by it alone have been cured of very great and indeed eſteemed incurable Diſeaſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Take yet the teſtimony of a fifth moſt laborious Artiſt and unwearied Searcher into the Secrets of Nature, who from his large experience of it and its wonderful effects in Medicine, doth boldly and plainly deliver his knowledge of it thus: <q>
                     <hi>Omnes rerum vires in omnibus Animali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, Vegetabilibus, &amp; Mineralibus ſigilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim diſperſae, cunctae in hoc uno ſubjecto concentratae &amp; perfectè unitae inveniuntur, ita ut inter ſubjecta medicinae apta, primum nobilitatis locum obtineat Auri primum Ens verum; in hoc enim omnium Animalium Vegetabilium &amp; Mineralium vires, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, &amp; facultates collectae &amp; plenè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centratae invenientur, I. R. G. Pharm. Spag. part. ſecund. p.</hi> 61. <hi>&amp;. aliis, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> This is the moſt high and ſignificant, and yet compendious Character which the above mentioned Author delivers of it: The whole Efficacy and Virtue, (ſaith he) found diſperſed in all Animals, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, and Minerals, is fully and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly united and concentrated in this one
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97616:30"/>Subject, ſo that among all Medicinal and Phyſical Subjects or Drugs, this <hi>Primum Ens Auri,</hi> or true Solar Embryon, is indeed the moſt noble; for in it are the powers of all Animals, Vegetables, and Minerals, cloſely heaped up, and, as it were, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into one bundle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To confirm and ſecond theſe moſt ample Teſtimonies already cited, together with my own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this Medicine, and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject out of which it is prepared, I could yet add the Vogue of many moſt famous and learned (both Antient and Modern) Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians; but what is already ſaid, will (I am certain) be ſufficient to the Learned, if at all Chymically and Phyſically ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to know not only the matter out of which it is prepared, but alſo the truth of what I have or ſhall yet aſſert of it. To others (if rational and ingenious) a plain and honeſt declaration of its Virtues, which they may in a due uſe of it (by God's bleſſing, find moſt true) will (I am confident) prove the higheſt and moſt convincing ſatisfaction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97616:30"/>
                  <head>The Virtues and Uſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis moſt efficacious (and yet moſt ſafe) Medicine, as prepared, if taken in its uſually limited Doſe, doth not at all produce any Purgative, Emetick, or Cathartick operation, that is, it purgeth not either by Stool, or Vomit: that being a little exceeded, it (haply) manifeſts its force, in ſome by Urine, in others (if they continue in their Beds, as they may that can) by a gentle breathing Sweat; (for it keeps not one conſtant progreſs and courſe of operation in all Ages, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and Conſtitutions, but according to neceſſity and Nature's beſt advantage, ſets it ſelf to work.) In other ſome again by a more than ordinary or uſual Spitting, (yet not as by a Mercurial Salivation, from which as dangerous as common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and operation it is altogether free) yet in none of thoſe ſo much as to cauſe any diſturbance or weakning to the Body, the proportion of the Doſe being yet raiſed, and the Stomach (<hi>&amp; coquus, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina &amp; culina corporis,</hi> both Cook and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97616:31"/>Kitchin of the Body) with the other Bowels, being much clogged with Vitious and Excrementitious obſtructions and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and its Attraction of thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours (for it mightily attracts) being greater than Nature can ſuddenly diſpoſe of, or carry downwards, it perhaps may cauſe an eaſie diſ-burthening of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, either upwards by ſome few gentle Vomits, or downwards by a Stool, or two, or more, according as the nature and conſtitution of the Patient, and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency for the Evacuation of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding humour, ſhall require; but this laſt and greateſt quantity is not always in all Diſtempers and Diſeaſes abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and therefore is very rarely or ſeldom adminiſtred, unleſs in Chronick, very obſtinate, deeply radicated, ſtubborn, or contumacious Diſeaſes: As the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, Gout, Dropſie, Pox, Agues, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, &amp;c. In all which, it is altogether, yea, abſolutely requiſite and neceſſary, that the Patient (his Age and Strength permitting) do for ſome days, (yet with intermiſſion, but a more continued ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Pills in a ſmaller doſe) reſolve
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97616:31"/>to take the higheſt proportion, which (as I acquainted you before) may cauſe, as it will, ſome gentle Vomits and moderate Stools, and thus to continue until the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe do gradually decline, and at laſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally vaniſh, together with its Cauſe, Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and firſt Original.</p>
                  <p>Some may haply ſay, If this be the manner that your Pill performs its Office in, <hi>(viz.)</hi> A reſolution of the ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in the Bowels, and drawing them into the Stomach, and afterwards caſting them out by Stool or Vomit, what need have we of this Medicine, or in what is it better than other Purges that perform the ſame thing?</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, Though all Purges have in ſome meaſure the ſame property, yet they perform it in another way than this my Pill doth; this doth not only operate upon the more looſe and eaſily ejected Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, but alſo upon the more fixed, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, and ſtubborn, which cannot poſſibly be done by any of the beſt of Purging Vegetables, without a very high prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and purification: And beſides, Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Purges being adminiſtred in ſmall
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97616:32"/>quantities or doſes, operate not, but reſt in the Body, and there do more hurt than good; but this Pill, though given in the ſmalleſt proportion imaginable, doth not only not do any hurt, but inſenſibly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms its deſired Office, and produces, in time, its noble Effects: So that I have not in the whole Vegetable Kingdom, no, not in all Nature, found a Purge in the leaſt comparable with this, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But to return to the buſineſs it ſelf, This extraordinary, or higheſt doſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, is alſo convenient, when common Diſtempers ſhall ſuddenly, or in ſhort time, too much grow upon and invade the Body; as alſo, when debilitated and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate Nature ſhall of neceſſity require a preſent and ſtrong aſſiſtance for over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming her too prevalent Enemy. Some may poſſibly here object, and ſay, that Vomits are too violent a courſe, and that this is the way utterly to deſtroy and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Nature, and her remaining forces: For, <hi>Omne violentum naturae inimicum &amp; contrarium est, &amp; Motus violentos naturam non pati, abſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> laeſione manifeſta.</hi> That is, What ever is violent is inimical and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97616:32"/>to Nature, and Nature is not able to endure violent motions.</p>
                  <p>To which I ſhall firſt anſwer, from a conſideration of Nature's own courſe (the beſt of Reaſons in a caſe of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) ſeconded and back'd by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and next give you (for brevity ſake) the Opinion of one moſt eminent and experienced Phyſician only, &amp;c. Nature, (we may obſerve) if any way diſturbed, clogged, and annoyed in her fortreſs the Stomach, and her adjacent conveniencies, begins (though inſenſibly almoſt at firſt) to diſlike, and in ſome meaſure reject what is there received, (or more properly from her impotency and diſability to diſpoſe of) and (as ſhe ſhould and would digeſt it for the Body's nouriſhment) ſuffers, (or rather cauſeth by her begun diſlike, deſire, and reſolution, to eject and throw out what ſhe perceives ſhe cannot well maſter by her Digeſtive heat) a kind of ſmall ſickneſs or indiſpoſition in the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach; and this it may be for an hour or two, or thereabouts. Time, and her not opportune ſuccour and aid, to free her from thoſe beginning Obſtructions, that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97616:33"/>diminiſh her Digeſtive heat and faculty, gives gradually an encreaſe to this firſt ſmall Indiſpoſition or weak Digeſtion; and by a continued contraction and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thoſe Excrements of Digeſtion, falls to a higher and higher diſlike, diſguſt, and lothing of her uſual food, or at leaſt the uſual proportion of it: And from this at length (after a receipt of any ſmall quantity of it) proceeds not only to the now uſual indiſpoſition of Stomach, but to a kind of motion to Vomit, which now encreaſeth daily more and more, and from a motion arives to a flat deſire, and from this deſire, yet further to the act it ſelf, an evacuation by Vomit, by which means Nature would unload and disburthen her ſelf of (Obſtructions in the Stomach and chief Bowels) the cauſe of this indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and over-powering of both the retentive and digeſtive faculty; yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well, without the aſſiſtance of ſome friendly Medicine or Remedy, fully clear her ſelf, and attain her deſire, (or return to her wonted indiſturbed condition.) Nature hath here by this Eſſay and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of her own to free her ſelf by Vomit,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97616:33"/>ſufficiently demonſtrated and plainly pointed out unto us, the means that ſhe her ſelf (as being her own both beſt Judge and Phyſician in her own caſe) would thus make uſe of, and is conſequently moſt proper for us to follow for her aid and aſſiſtance, and recovery from this impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency and indiſpoſition ſhe now ſuffers under: Vomits then being her own volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and elected way, cannot in reaſon be thought (whatever ſome inconſiderate and ſelf-conceited may affirm) to be ſo deſtructive, and altogether inimical to Nature, and her proſperity: But, indeed (eſpecially when directed by her own motion) the only agreeable and direct courſe to ſuccour and relieve her in this her diſtreſs and impaired condition; and this my Experience hath often confirmed unto me by its happy ſucceſs, to be no way deſtructive, but a truly friendly way of aſſiſting Nature to expel and overcome her Oppoſites, approaching Diſeaſes. Vomits then (though eſteemed, and accordingly by many unadviſedly ſhunned, and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether avoided, as Operations too violent and repugnant to Nature's ſafety and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97616:34"/>being the courſe and method hinted and ſhewed unto us by Nature her ſelf, and her <hi>Archeus,</hi> for the cure of many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, cannot certainly be ſo offenſive or diſturbing to her, as that we ſhould ſo contumaciouſly reject and condemn the uſe and preſcription of them: For Nature doubtleſs would not put her ſelf upon any motion to injure and impair her ſelf, and what ſhe by her own attempts endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to perform by a Vomitive courſe, is certainly the beſt tract for us to follow, to give aſſiſtance and relief unto her decayed forces, and conſequently to reſtore her to her juſt and full power and prerogative; the effect of which is a ſound, ſtrong, and healthful condition, and conſtitution. I argue not, nor contend, thus ſtrongly for Vomiting Potions, as being abſolutely needful in all trivial Diſtempers; but as being very much, yea, abſolutely neceſſary for the full and perfect cure of ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and no way ſo deſtructive, or weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to Nature, (though in ſtrength of Operation ſomewhat exceeding the more mild and ordinary motion of only down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward purging Potions, Boles, Electuaries,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97616:34"/>or the like, good alſo in their kind) as that they (being a way we only follow the tacite preſcriptions and directions of Nature her ſelf in) ſhould to the utter loſs of many ſick people (by this way only recoverable) be wholly exploded, and altogether excluded out of a Phyſical courſe and preſcription, as too many yet think and practiſe, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Take alſo to ſecond theſe operations of Nature, and Experience, the Authority of the truly learned and judicious <hi>Faber</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering the ſame Objections) in his own words; <hi>Hoc philoſopho ridiculum videtur, nam natura facili negotio &amp; via, violentos patitur motus, ut mortem ipſam evitet &amp; ſe ab ipſa tueatur, mors enim omnium motuum violentiſſima est, &amp; natura, ut hanc effugiat, caeteros quoſcunque mavult ſequi, &amp; pati motus, &amp; ſi laedatur aliqua ratione, facili via à laeſione illa ſublevatur, quocirca non timenda est illa laeſio, cum plus utilitatis hinc exſurgat quam nocumenti: Pet. Johan. Fab. Sap. univerſ.</hi> lib. 3. p. 300. in <hi>Cap. primo de obſt. Inteſtinorum, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This, ſaith he, (meaning the former Objection) will to one, ſeriouſly and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97616:35"/>truly conſidering the courſe of Nature, ſeem moſt ridiculous, for Nature doth very willingly and voluntarily ſuffer and thruſt her ſelf into many violent and paſſive Motions, that ſhe may eſcape, keep off, and defend her ſelf from Death; Death is the moſt violent of motions, and rather than ſhe will endure that, ſhe will ſuffer any the moſt violent of diſturbances and preternatural motions whatever: And if ſhe be by theſe unnatural irritations ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for the preſent put out of frame, debilitated, and weakned, ſhe will again recover her ſelf; and thoſe ſmall diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances (ſo that ſhe may acquit and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge her ſelf of Death, her grand An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt) are rather profitable, than any way diſadvantageous or hurtful unto her, &amp;c. <hi>Poſt nubila Phoebus.</hi> And this alſo, the wonted and continued courſe which we daily may ſee Nature of her own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord make uſe of, to free her ſelf from her encroaching Enemies, (Diſtempers and Diſeaſes, the effect of Corruption) may ſtrongly and ſufficiently demonſtrate unto us: For example, conſider thoſe two preternatural motions in a Tertian and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97616:35"/>Quartane Fever, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the cold and hot Fit as we call them. Which are not, as the Vulgar will tell you, becauſe they are ſo ſeldom and rarely cured by Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and therefore their ſhame and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, as well as the Gout, Dropſie, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, &amp;c. <hi>Divels,</hi> or <hi>Witches,</hi> or I know not what of the like Nature; nor do they, as the Scholes do generally tell us, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from their four Humours, Phlegm, Choler, Melancholy, and putrefaction of Blood, as Quotidian from Phlegm, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian from Choler, and Quartane from Melancholy; nor as ſome particular Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians do affirm, <hi>ab efferveſcentiâ Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> (viz.) from a Boyling of the Blood, <hi>(ab inflammato Sulphure)</hi> from an Inflamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sulphur in it, in which laſt they as much miſtake the effect for the cauſe, as in the firſt, one cauſe for another; true it is, the Blood is inflamed, and that (ſometimes) even to an extreme heighth, by which the Body, in which it runs, is (as it were) almoſt burned up, but yet this <hi>efferveſcentia Sanguinis,</hi> is not the cauſe <hi>efferveſcentiae Sanguinis,</hi> but indeed an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the true cauſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97616:36"/>of Nature, by the Excrements of Digeſtion, left by the debilitated Bowels, and other particular Parts, in their ſeveral Offices of Digeſtion, accelerated (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) by a ſtoppage of the Pores by ſome exceſſive Cold, (or other ways) from which ariſeth Obſtruction of Nature, and her <hi>Archeus,</hi> in her Prerogative Royal, and free paſſage and progreſs through the Body, for its preſervation and conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its due equation of Elements, which obſtructions and excrements Nature to free her ſelf from, (after a Concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration, or Collection of her Forces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her abilities) doth by a ſuddain Excurſion, or Sally, from her Fortreſs, the moſt Inward parts, voluntarily, and with premeditation (may I ſo ſay) cauſe this violent (<hi>efferveſcentia Sanguinis</hi> or) Paſſion, or produceth it by her powerfully iſſuing forth, with her Recollected forces, to free her ſelf from thoſe incroaching Obſtructions which began to diminiſh her Royal courſe, and conſequently to corrupt, and putrefie her Manſion, and the paſſage of her Progreſs; Wonder not, that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (by Nature, I here mean the Life,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97616:36"/>Spirit, <hi>Spiritus innatus, custos corporis oeconomus</hi>) wonder (or marvail) not (I ſay) that Nature ſhould be of ſuch power, to cauſe ſo great an inflammation, ſcorching heat, or combuſtion in the Body; for conſider, ſhe is Life, and Life is Fire, and Fire the moſt pure, powerful and ſtrong of all the Elements; conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly her Power, and how ſhe can (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways alſo) both cure and cauſe even the greateſt of Diſeaſes, and this by the ſole power and ſtrength of her own fancy, without any previous matter in the Body for the cauſe, or production; nor doth here end the extent of her Power, for it can perform even Miracles: If you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not me, believe yet Chriſt himſelf, who tells us, that if we have Faith but as a Grain of Muſtard-ſeed, what we may do by it; if you will ſay, that this is not meant of the Spirit, but of the Soul, which medleth not with the curing of Bodily diſeaſes, hear yet our Saviour himſelf; <hi>Go,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thy Faith hath (healed or) made thee whole;</hi> and again, <hi>Be it unto thee according to thy Faith:</hi> You ſee here that Faith is no other than the ſtrong power
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97616:37"/>of the (Soul or) Spirit; This the moſt knowing (and as Religious as knowing) <hi>Paracelſus</hi> (whatever his ignorant Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſts report of him, branding him with the Name of Atheiſt, from which alſo (as their due reward) themſelves in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Opinion ſcape not free) doth moſt plainly tell us, <hi>De fide Chriſtus haud fruſtra tanta nobis inculcat</hi> (viz.) <hi>adeo efficacem eſſe ut nos vel ſanos vel aegros facere poſſit, imo quod majus est, per eam vel ſalvi vel damnati fieri poſſumus, prout ea utimur; legimus ipſum ſanatis omnibus dixiſſe, crede &amp; ſanus eris, aut fiat tibi ſecundùm fidem, &amp;c. Paracel.</hi> lib. <hi>Principiorum.</hi> Cap. 10. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Thus this moſt Conſcientious and Chriſtian Phyſitian: Yet ſome of his idle Enemies <hi>(viz.)</hi> ſuch as from others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports and mouths only hear (but falſly) what he was, have, in my hearing, affirmed that in his whole works, from one end to the other, He never ſo much as mentioned the name of God, or Chriſt, which how falſe a thing it is, who ever ſhall pleaſe to peruſe his works, muſt of neceſſity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them either very Envious, or very
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97616:37"/>Ignorant of him, and what he wrote; for there is hardly a Page in ſome part of his Works, in which he doth not, and that more than once, or twice, with a true Chriſtian regard, and reverence, name and mention both the Name of God, and alſo of our Saviour himſelf: But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to this moſt excellent Phyſician's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery in the aforeſaid words, He tells us thus, that Faith is moſt powerful, and can both cauſe, and cure Diſeaſes, nay more, it will both Save and Damn; it was not therefore (ſaith he) in vain, that Chriſt ſpake ſo much of the power of Faith, who, when ever he cured any of Diſeaſes, ſaid, <hi>Believe, and thou ſhalt be made whole, or Be it unto thee according unto thy Faith, &amp;c.</hi> Wonderful certainly is the ſecret power of the Spirit. (But of this enough.) I could even with the greateſt of truth be here Voluminous, as to the ſtupendious effects of Faith, or ſtrong perſuaſion and imagination, and what power we have by it, not only upon our own Bodies, but alſo on the Bodies (and not only the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but alſo the Spirits) of others; for it is ſaid of Chriſt himſelf, that he did no
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97616:38"/>great Miracles there, becauſe of their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief; <hi>at Cynthius aurem vellit, neque omnia in vulgus ratio ſuadet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And returning to the power of Nature, and to confirm it by ſome familiar exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; conſider, as I ſaid before, the hot and cold Fit, (as we call them) in Agues, &amp;c. Nature finding her power begin to decay by ſome Obſtructing matter or other in her paſſages of Circulation, Peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, or Progreſs, calls in all her Forces to the Centre; Her forces (the Spirits) being called, and with-drawn from their ſeveral ſtations, or parts of the Body, (of which they are the Life and only Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) thoſe Outward parts are oh a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain over-taken with a Chilneſs, (or, as we call it, a cold Ague fit) the true effect of Nature's calling in her Forces, there to Concentrate and Muſter them up toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that by her ſuddain Sally, or Return with thoſe her united Forces, and utmoſt Strength, ſhe may expel and drive out (either in part, or wholly) her Incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Death-threatning oppoſite; the Body is now again by this means, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Nature's Return with her united Strength
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97616:38"/>to expel her Enemy, by degrees over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with a fiery and fluſhing heat (<hi>viz.</hi> the hot Fit) a moſt certain effect, and ſign of the Spirits again re-entring and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming their former Stations, and with all the power and force ſhe is poſſibly able to make againſt her powerful Adverſary; This Conteſt, or Duel, laſts as long as Nature is able to maintain and bear it out; and having for that time done her utmoſt devoir, (for according to her Strength ſhe will with greateſt vigour maintain the Battel with her Antagoniſt) ſhe ceaſeth, and is for ſome time (and this according to her remaining ſtrength and ability) more quiet and calm, than in the heat of her paſt Paſſion, (or <hi>Spiritus exſcande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentia</hi>) which is not as improperly termed preternatural, for it is really natural, and the work of Nature (or the <hi>Archeus</hi>) her ſelf, and is only preternatural, <hi>quoad gradum non quoad calorem,</hi> for it is the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> irritated, or advancing her ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond her uſual courſe, &amp;c. If ſhe be ſtrong, ſhe will by a Quotidian Fever (or conteſt) indeavour to free her ſelf of thoſe Obſtructions ſhe feels begin to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97616:39"/>her; If her ſtrength be more ſlack and remiſs, by a Tertian; if feebler, and yet more weak, by a Quartane; and if not able every ſecond, or third Day, &amp;c. to fight or encounter her Enemy, ſhe will yet as often as poſſibly ſhe can, and this (perhaps) but once in ten or fourteen days, but then is ſhe weak indeed.</p>
                  <p>That this is truth, a daily Obſervation of theſe paſſages in the Sick, will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently aſſure and convince us, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the ſtronger Nature is, the more frequent her Encounters, and Excurſions are againſt her Oppoſite: Our own vulgar Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and Rules, or Maxims, will alſo teſtifie and inform us the ſame; for we account a Quotidian Ague (or Fever) more eaſie to cure than a Tertian, and a Tertian yet more eaſie and facile than a Quartane, for if it vary (or alter) from a Quotidian to a Tertian, we think the worſe of it; If from a Tertian to a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, we account it yet worſe, and of more dangerous conſequence, and much more difficult to remedy than the former; and why is this, but only that we eſteem Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the more weak, and the Cauſe greater,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97616:39"/>and more hardly to be removed; and conſequently Nature (though well aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) will have the harder task to expel it; for though Nature may not be yet very much weakned and debilitated, yet the Diſeaſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Obſtructions of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's right and privilege, being ſtrong, and ſtubborn, Nature will the more hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be put to it in the conqueſt and extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of it, and cannot therefore ſo often draw forth her impaired ſtrength and forces (being already in ſome meaſure infeebled) to expel and force out her yet prevailing Deſtroyer; but what ſhe doth, ſhe muſt do by degrees, and as her power and ſtrength will bear, allow, and admit of; and this is Nature's daily courſe: Thus you ſee that Nature her ſelf ſtirs up, and that voluntary, (even to the utmoſt of her power, and ſtrength) thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts and inflammations in her Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſo ſhe may free, and quit her ſelf of thoſe unwelcome, and unpleaſing Gueſts, which would otherwiſe turn her quite out of her Poſſeſſion.</p>
                  <p>This is my Opinion, and I think not diſagreeable to Reaſon, however I want
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97616:40"/>not to back it the Authority of two great Lights, moſt Eminent, Expert, and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Modern Phyſicians, <hi>Van Helmont,</hi> and the moſt acute <hi>Faber,</hi> from whom, whoſo deſires more ſatisfaction, may peruſe their ſeveral Tractates, <hi>de Febribus, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to return from this Digreſſion to the two former Aſſertions of Nature's moſt willingly, and reſolvedly Suffering, or rather throwing, and putting her ſelf into preternatural Motions; Conſider the violent diſturbance in the <hi>Epileptical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultus,</hi> or in the Falling-ſickneſs, with the like violent motions, perturbations, and preternatural, and unuſual diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances, more or leſs, in all or moſt Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Diſtempers, and Diſeaſes whatever. If therefore violent, and preternatural, unaccuſtomed Motions were altogether deſtructive to nature, why would ſhe make ſo conſtant and certain an irritation of them by her <hi>Archew,</hi> as we daily in moſt Diſtempers may perceive, and obſerve ſhe doth? If it be anſwered, it is not Nature, but the Diſeaſe that doth it, and is the cauſe of it, and that it is no way pleaſing to Nature, but altogether oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97616:40"/>to her: I anſwer, I well know that the Diſeaſe is in ſome ſence or part the cauſe of it, but how? the Diſeaſe is not the Agent that ſtirs up thoſe violent and unnatural Motions of it ſelf, but is the cauſe that excites Nature to do it, to free her ſelf from the Diſeaſe, and drive it out before her, by thoſe her violent Motions and Paſſions, which ſhe thus willingly and of her own accord ſtirs up and ſuffers, that ſhe may overcome and conquer the cauſe, (corrupting Obſtructions and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements) the oppoſites of her royal and wonted indiſturbed progreſs; and this will appear moſt evident, as well in her conqueſt or victory over the Diſeaſe, as in her final overthrow and deſtruction by Death it ſelf: For if Nature, either by the ſtrength of her own force, and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus,</hi> or by a timely and powerful aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, do extirpate, overcome, and maſter the Diſeaſe, ſhe is then quiet, and no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger frets, wearies, and vexeth her ſelf, by ſuch violent Motions, but quietly keeps her wonted, deſired, and uſual courſe and progreſs; if by the Diſtemper ſhe be at laſt overcome, and Death drive her to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97616:41"/>her Habitation, neither doth the Body then ſuffer under any violent motion or diſturbance; for (the <hi>Spiritus innatus, cuſtos corporis,</hi> is departed, and) there is no Life left, and where there is no Life, there can be no ſuch Motion, though the cauſe of the motion be ſtill left as copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in the Body as before; I mean the cauſe that moved Nature to ſtir up theſe paſt violent Motions, and Symptoms, to have freed her ſelf, (if poſſibly) from that moſt violent of motions, Death it ſelf, which at laſt ſhe is forced, <hi>nolens, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens,</hi> to undergo and ſubmit to; for it is appointed for all Men once to Dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The virtues of this <hi>Solar</hi> Pill.</head>
                  <p>THe Operation of it is managed ſometimes in a ſenſible, ſometimes an inſenſible manner, according to the quantity adminiſtred; but if kept in its uſually preſcribed and limited Bounds or Doſe, it is, I ſay, rather inſenſible than any way perceptible, unleſs in its wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Effects, by which it giveth perfect Cure unto the Head-ach, Vertigo, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97616:41"/>Lethargie, Epilepſie, Convulſion; with thoſe many other Diſtempers that uſually afflict the Head, as difficulty of Hearing, noiſe in the Head and Ears, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Moſt effectual alſo it is in opening all Obſtructions of the Stomach, Liver, Spleen, and other the noble Bowels, the true original and foundation of many high Diſtempers, and grievous Diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p>Excellent are its effects in the Cure of Agues, and Fevers of all ſorts, as Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidian, Tertian, Quartane, &amp;c. (but taken in the higheſt Doſe, if the Patient's ſtrength and age permit, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Moſt powerful alſo, and never failing in the Cure of that lothſome and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Diſeaſe the <hi>French-Pox,</hi> though of long continuance, and gotten even into the Bones. Nor doth it thus admirably Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in theſe more common and ordinary Diſtempers and Diſeaſes, but alſo in thoſe deſperate and (almoſt) accounted incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Maladies, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Leproſie, Gout, Dropſie, &amp;c. all which it in time perfectly Cures, and radically takes away the Cauſe.</p>
                  <p>A moſt noble and effectual Antidote it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97616:42"/>is in keeping out all ill Airs, and that moſt ſwift and poyſonous Infection the Plague, and, if taken, a moſt potent Medicine to expel and drive it out again, provided it have not wholly ſeiſed and over-powred the Vitals.</p>
                  <p>To Women, a more ſafe and powerful Medicine cannot be given, it being almoſt an univerſal Remedy for thoſe many Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, that uſually attend their weak, unhealthy, cold and moiſt Bodies; all which, I out of reſpect to their modeſty do here purpoſely forbear, and omit the reciting. A moſt admirable virtue and faculty hath God given it, to render and make fruitful even the moſt barren of Women, provided the cauſe be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and accidental, as in moſt, (that is, by ſome remediable indiſpoſition of Body, and not natural, or by the will of Almighty God) and being uſed after Conception, (but taken in the ſmall or inſenſibly Operating proportion) it won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully availeth in ſtrengthning thoſe that are apt to miſcarry, and makes them bring a moſt ſound, healthful, and thriving Child into the World, though the Parents be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97616:42"/>of an infirm, and a moſt ſickly conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diſpoſition of Body, &amp;c. And this I have often to my own and others great ſatisfaction and content Experienced, by many of my Friends, Acquaintance, and Patients, to whom I have in this point moſt ſucceſsfully adminiſtred them.</p>
                  <p>In Virgins, it ſpeedily eradicates, and takes away the cauſe and fountain of the Green-ſickneſs, ill habit, and conſtitution of Body, cauſed by Obſtructions of the Bowels, and Nature's due and wonted courſe, and cauſeth in them a lively, freſh, and chearful countenance, with a moſt ſound and healthful condition, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>To Children, it is a moſt potent pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt the Convulſion, Falling-ſickneſs, Worms, Meaſles, Small-pox, together with thoſe other too numerous Diſtempers, uſually afflicting, and ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſuddenly from their ſorrowful Parents.</p>
                  <p>This Medicine is ſo truly ſafe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, that without any the leaſt danger it may be given to the moſt Aged, moſt Weak, and alſo to Infants, (though but new Born) one half or the fourth part of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97616:43"/>one of the Pills, for Children, if weak, in a little of the Mother's milk, as moſt fit and proper for it, which, then taking it, ſhall never after be troubled with Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leptical or Convulſion-fits; if they are taken with thoſe Fits, it ſhall, being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred to them, by degrees gently and ſafely mitigate, and at laſt quite take them away; moſt excellent things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for Women, Mothers of Children, to have ſtill by them in their Houſes: And for my own part, I ſeldom, either for my Self, or any other of my Family, (or Friends) really depending upon my care upon any Diſtemper, (which, by God's bleſſing upon a convenient uſe of this Pill, or Medicine, doth rarely happen, though I have many other excellent ones ſtill in readineſs by me) do uſe any other than this one, (as a true cleanſer of the whole Body) with two other pleaſant refreſhing Cordials, hereafter mentioned, which I once in a quarter of a year, with much freedom, do give unto the leaſt Child I have, and in the higheſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but ſuitable to their Strength and Age, beſides an oftner taking of the Pills
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97616:43"/>in the ordinary inſenſibly operating Doſe and quantity, according alſo to their Age and Diſpoſition; and truly, I think there is not either in the City, or within twenty Miles of it, more healthy, luſty, and thriving Children than they are; all which, next to God Almighty's provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and bleſſing, I cannot attribute to any thing more, than to the Virtues of this Medicine, and a due and moderate uſe of it.</p>
                  <p>It exceedingly cleanſeth, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſtrengthneth all the principal Bowels and Members, and by that means eaſeth and cureth all afflictions of the Head, Stomach, Ventricle, Liver, Spleen, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>It extremely promoteth, and pleaſantly helpeth forward, the Cure of all internal and external wounds, in ſhort time bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to perfect Cure, and that by its Balſamic and cleanſing Quality; and to moſt outward wounds or hurts, (with the daily uſe of theſe Pills in the inſenſibly operating Doſe) you need only defend the hurt, or wound from the Air and Duſt, with a plaiſter of pure Bees-wax, freſh
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97616:44"/>Butter, Turpentine, and ſome Mineral or Metallin flowers or calx; and ſo you will ſee a very quick and ſure Cure, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>It miraculouſly accelerateth the Cure of all Ulcers, Cancers, Fiſtulaes, <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> Wolf, Scrophulous humors, or Kings-evil, and the like troubleſome or filthy Maladies, totally conſuming and drying up (as the Sun doth the Earth's ſuperfluous moiſture) the very root, cauſe, and corroſive fountain from whence they ſpring.</p>
                  <p>In ſhort, this moſt noble Medicine is ſo potent a purifier of the whole Body of Man, and that by its true cleanſing and ſearching Quality, that no Diſtemper (God Almighty's determined and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time being not yet come) is able long to withſtand and reſiſt the effect of its power and virtue; but time (to this as to all others, though never ſo good) muſt be given for the manifeſtation of its effects, and a courſe and continuance anſwerable to the Diſtemper, allowed and obſerved in the taking of it; eſpecially in Chronic Diſeaſes, or Diſtempers of deep radica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and habit.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97616:44"/>
                  <p>The ſimple, raſh, and inconſiderate, hearing the admirable Virtues of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, will without doubt as much deſire it as any; but imagine, that as ſoon as they have taken it into their Bodies, or at far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt within three or four days, that their Infirmity, Diſtemper, or Diſeaſe, of what kind, degree, and nature ſoever, and of what continuance ſoever, muſt of neceſſity preſently vaniſh and be gone, without any the leaſt ſign, ſymptom, or relict of it remaining, which no ingenious or diſcreet perſon muſt or will expect; but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the nature, radication, habit, and continuance of the Malady or Diſtemper, Age, Strength, and Conſtitution of their Bodies, to bear its operation in a greater or ſmaller Doſe, expect the deſired ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, in the reſtauration of their health, which (by God's bleſſing, and an orderly uſe of this Medicine, a due time) they will moſt aſſuredly find. I have already exceeded my intentions in this diſcourſe, and ſhould be too tedious, indeed, ſhould I give a relation of the many notable Cures, which by my ſelf, and others, that have had it of me, have been performed
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97616:45"/>by it, which truly have been ſuch, and ſo great, that I (though well acquainted with the ſtrangeneſs of its effects) have many times extremely wondred at them, that it ſhould in ſuch ſmall Doſes as it uſually was given in, produce ſo great and extraordinary effects, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If (perhaps) the Pills do in the time of their Operation, or Working, cauſe any ſmall Griping, either in the Stomach, or other Bowels, as poſſibly in ſome, they may ſometimes do, let them not therefore preſently unadviſedly ſlight, reject, and diſlike them, as ſuppoſing them (from thence) an unſafe, dangerous, and ill-prepared Medicine, and a too harſh, ſtrong, and violent ſort of Phyſick for them, (or their Conſtitutions) but rather let them conclude it (as juſtly, and truly, they may) to proceed from ſome error or other of their own, either in the taking, or diſordering themſelves in the time of their Operation, or elſe that their Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, or other Bowels began to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, or filled, with a Slimy, Clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or Viſcuous matter; (or ſubſtance) which would not eaſily be Evacuated by
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97616:45"/>the Medicine, without that ſmall trouble and inconveniency, (well to be tolerated, or born with, in reſpect of the great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit they will reap by it, <hi>viz.</hi>) the prevention of ſome greater Miſchief, (or Diſtemper) which might ſuddenly have aſſaulted, and invaded, even Life it ſelf, if not by this means diſperſed, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented of ſo bad a Conſequence; and that this is true, I have ſufficient, and large Experience, knowing many, who have ſuffered ſome ſuch ſmall trouble in the firſt taking of them, but their Bodies, by a continued, and moderately repered ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, (for ſome time) being fully empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and free of thoſe Stubborn, Groſs, and Viſcuous humors, (Matter, or Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) they afterwards felt not any the leaſt trouble, diſturbance, or Griping by them; for the more obſtructed, clogged, and foul the Bowels are, the more will they Operate, and poſſibly cauſe (in ſome) ſuch ſmall Gripings, (a profitable incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency) the more free, and clear, the Body is, the more mildly, gently, and with leſs trouble do they perform their Office in Operation.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:97616:46"/>
                  <p>Though I well know, that no Diſeaſe, or Diſtemper whatever, is indeed (natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally) Incurable, unleſs the immediate hand of God, for ſome cauſe or other, do hinder and oppoſe the Cure; and alſo by Experience have often found, that theſe Medicines come not at all ſhort, but far exceed what I have here ſaid of them. I yet alſo, as well know, that the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of all Medicines are of no force, power, and validity, againſt the decrees, will, and pleaſure of Almighty God; all things, both in Heaven, and Earth, muſt ſubmit to his call, and appointment; the moſt powerful of Medicines, when He will call for our Souls out of this Vale of miſery and corruption, is then no longer able to do us any good, or prolong our Life one minute beyond the time and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod appointed by himſelf; It being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for all Men once to Dye, to Live again (according to his good will and pleaſure) to another Life. Medicine is indeed a great bleſſing, created, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully beſtowed upon us by Almighty God, but can ſerve us no further than to preſerve, and reſtore Health, ſo long as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97616:46"/>he in his Goodneſs ſhall afford us Life; for, though without the knowledge, and help of good Medicines, we may long linger, and lie under Diſeaſes, and by the help of them, being well known, and as well prepared, quickly expel, and quit our ſelves of them; yet ought we not to dote upon, or put greater confidence in their Virtue, (though of greateſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and perfection) than with, and in the uſe of them, to crave his bleſſing, and for the effects, wholly to rely and caſt our ſelves into the Arms of his Mercy, who, if he calls, we ſhould as willingly reſolve to be diſſolved, and return unto him; if not, we cannot but in reaſon (and with his bleſſing) expect, and aſſuredly (in time) find the deſired effect, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the return, and reſtauration of our Health, from the due uſe of pure, powerful, and ſafely efficacious Medicines, of which number theſe are none of the meaneſt, but truly noble Remedies, and moſt ſafe, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and friendly aſſiſtants unto human Nature, and therefore I ſhall give a brief Account of the Virtues of the other five in order.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:97616:47"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Quinteſſentia Sali Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mica, &amp;c. <hi>OR,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Moſt excellent Balſamic Oyl, or Quinteſſence of Salt, highly impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, tinged, and Philoſophically united, with the true and pure Eſſences of the moſt Aromatick and Cordial of Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables. So that the eſſences of the Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables are by the Spirit of Salt improved, heightned, and exalted to a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary degree of efficacy and perfection, and the Spirit of Salt made Cordial by the eſſences and power of the Vegetables, by which means it as well refreſheth the Spirits, as opens them a paſſage through the whole Body, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Virtue of this Aromatiſed precious Liquor, or eſſence of Salt, are ſuch, and ſo many, as no one is able fully to render an account of them. I ſhall therefore give you only ſome few heads of them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my own knowledge and experience of it: which may lead the Ingenious to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97616:47"/>a farther conſideration of the infinite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It renews the whole Maſs of Blood, and ſo purifieth it, that with a continued (preſcribed) moderate uſe of it, for ſome time, it doth in a wonderful manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive and ſtrengthen the whole Body, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it vigorous, luſty, and of a florid and ſtrong Conſtitution; it extremely quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Senſes, helps the Memory, and maketh lightſome the whole Body, and this by its cleanſing the Stomach, and ſtrengthning both the retentive and dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive faculty, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A moſt excellent and certain Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num (or ſecret) it is in Curing the Stone, either in the Reins, Kidney, or Bladder, or any Tartarous obſtruction, or degenerate Salt humor in the whole Body; it retardeth Old-age, keepeth back Grey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hairs, and preſerves the Body in a health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and flouriſhing condition: It is a moſt pleaſant and ſafe extinguiſher of all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural heats, as in Fevers, and the like, none almoſt comparable unto it, either in preſervation, or reſtauration.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It openeth all Obſtructions of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97616:48"/>Body, killeth all manner of Worms, Stomach-worms, Maw-worms, &amp;c. It prevalently advanceth and promoteth fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility, (or fruitfulneſs in Women) and is exceeding good and profitable for thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready with Child, with much ſafety pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving them from many troubleſome and dangerous Diſtempers (and Symptoms) incident unto them; highly reſtaurative and ſtrengthning to the Conſumptive, Ptiſical, Hectical, and all this becauſe it preſerves, nouriſheth, and increaſeth the <hi>humidum radicale</hi> of the Body; It is ſo excellent a Medicine, that it cannot almoſt in any kind of Malady, Diſtemper, or Diſeaſe whatever, either Inward, or Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, without ſome eminently profitable ſucceſs and advantage, be made uſe of. I ſhall therefore ſay no more of it, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to the Ingenious and Diſcreet, as a moſt high gift of Almighty God, freely and in great Plenty beſtowed upon us; for ſhould we be diligent ſearchers into Nature and her Treaſury, the great bleſſings of a greater and moſt omnipotent Creator, we ſhould clearly ſee, that thoſe things we have moſt need of, and which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97616:48"/>would do us moſt good, are every where by God in greateſt plenty ſpread before us; but we are blind, and alſo hate know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and to have our way directed unto us, by thoſe whom God hath been pleaſed out of his Goodneſs to inable to be a light and guidance unto us, &amp;c. Salt in its groſs Quality, and involved or mixed with thoſe Impurities which Nature pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it to us accompanied with, is ſo noble a Creature, as (except the Soul of Man) there is nothing ſublunary, equal, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable unto it. And this thoſe many excellent uſes it daily ſerves us for, will (if we conſider them) ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us of, Chriſt himſelf ſaid, there was none good but God; Yet of Salt he ſaith, it is good, <hi>Salt is good, &amp;c.</hi> If ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then, and truly good, as it is groſs and impure by reaſon of the Dreggs and Impurities mixed with it, what may it be by a Philoſophical purification, purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and other convenient Chymical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations advanced and exalted to. I will not tell thee my utmoſt thoughts of it, for ſo great Myſteries depend upon a true knowledge of Salt, and its purification,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97616:49"/>and preparations, as the Vulgar would count fabulous, and therefore as unfit for their knowledge, as beyond their reach and contemplation; it is (even as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Servant of the moſt high Creator, prepares it for us) ſo great and high a bleſſing, as we are no way capable of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning him ſufficient thanks for, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Concerning the virtue and excellency of Salt, beſides that grand, moſt ſignal, and high Character and Epithite of GOOD, beſtowed upon it by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by him denied to all but God himſelf; I could alſo at large (if not too large for my preſent intent) give you the Teſtimonies of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in his <hi>Herbar,</hi> (in Quarto) pag. 3, 4, 5. pag. 103, 104, 106. &amp;c. of <hi>Peter Faber</hi> in his fourth Book, <hi>Secret. Chymicon.</hi> pag. 443, to pag. 448. alſo in his <hi>Mirothe. Spagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum,</hi> lib. 3. from pag. 613, to 616. See alſo the ſaid <hi>Faber</hi> in his <hi>Panchimic,</hi> lib. 4. from pag. 574, to 576. Who alſo pleaſeth, may at leiſure, in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Works, peruſe the ample and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Virtues aſcribed unto it by <hi>Scroder, Glauber, Crollius, Sennertus, Agricola, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guin,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97616:49"/>Untzer, Hartman, Tentz, Gluckraht, Keſler, Querortan, Kunrath,</hi> and many others. There lately came to my Hands a ſheet of Paper printed in <hi>December</hi> laſt, (the Publiſher I know not) entituled, <hi>The excellency and uſefulneſs of the true Spirit of Salt, being a Collection of the Atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſeveral Authors and Phyſicians, of the eminent Virtues of Salt.</hi> It treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth only of the ſimple Spirit of Salt, well prepared, which doubtleſs, even in that ſtate and condition is a very excellent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine; but that you may know I write not of the Spirit of Salt ſimply of it ſelf, I have in the Title told you, it is impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, tinged, and Philoſophically united with the eſſences of the moſt Cordial and Aromatick of Vegetables; by which means it is exalted, and become a far more noble, pleaſant, and efficacious Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The uſe of this Philoſophical Spirit of Salt, is thus: Let the Infirmed (or Sound) that is pleaſed to take it, put ſo many drops of it into a Glaſs of Wine, Beer, Ale, or the like, (as after ſtirring them well together, will give a pleaſant rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh)
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97616:50"/>and let them Drink it twice or thrice (or only once) a Day, if they will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or at Meals, and with thus uſing of it for ſome time, they will aſſuredly find (unleſs ſtupid and void of perceivance) its noble Effects; thoſe that would uſe it outwardly, muſt mix it alſo with Wine, Water, or ſome other Vehiculum, fit for the purpoſe it is intended for; and if it be for Sores, or the like, waſh and bathe the place affected, and they will alſo in ſhort time perceive its cleanſing, healing, and wonderfull Balſamic quality, even to their great benefit and admiration, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Pilula nobiliſſima Purgans.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe ſome, either to gratifie their own Fantaſie, or Conceit, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deterred therefrom by the too great Folly (or other ends) of ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, or elſe more dreading the ſmall trouble in a Vomit, than valuing their own Health, had rather have ſuch a Medicine as may operate only by Stool.</p>
               <p>I have alſo taken the pains, to prepare, and have in readineſs, ſuch a Pill, or Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97616:50"/>for them, pleaſant in Taſte, and very mild in Operation, yet very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in all, or moſt Diſtempers, that our frail Bodies do commonly labour under.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Tinctura Mirabilis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VEry Numerous, and (indeed) as Great, and Excellent, as Numerous, are the Virtues aſcribed by the moſt Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of Phyſicians, unto the bare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prepared Subject of this noble Tincture. I ſhall in brief acquaint you with ſome of them, together with my Authors, and then give you a Glimpſe, (and but a Glimpſe) of thoſe moſt deſirable Effects, which it is by this Subtilizing, and Exalting pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration yet farther enabled, (after a due adminiſtration) Convincingly to produce and benefit thoſe by, that ſhall rightly make uſe of it.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Jovivenerean</hi> Subject hath been, and ſtill is, by all knowing, diligent, and induſtrious Phyſicians, much eſteemed, and highly valued. <hi>Paracelſus</hi> (that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of Medicine) hath (and that doubtleſs from his great Experience of it,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97616:51"/>and its Virtue) given it this very ample Character; <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>most effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and powerful against all inward Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whatever, Radically plucking up, and rooting them out.</hi> Moſt prevalent againſt all Faſcinations, Incantations, Night-frights, Poyſons, Epilepſie, Melancholy, and doth reſtore the Body with a kind of Celeſtial vigour, to a moſt temperate Habit, exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, and moſt ſound Conſtitution. Nor is this the Teſtimony of the Experienced <hi>Paracelſus</hi> alone; but alſo of the Knowing and Learned, <hi>Hartman, Crollius, Penotus, Sennertus, Baſilius, Valentinus, Kunrath,</hi> and <hi>Quercetanus,</hi> with many other moſt indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, expert, and eminent Phyſicians. Take now the Virtues, Efficacy, and Power of it, as here prepared, (and preſented) ſuch, and ſo great is the Potency, Efficacy, and Virtue of this noble <hi>Tincture,</hi> both in purifying the Blood throughout the whole Body, and reſiſting all Effects, proceeding from the Corruption of the ſame; that it is with admirable ſucceſs given in all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, ariſing from a corrupt, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified Blood; and this by reaſon of its ſweet Balſamic, penetrating Salt, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97616:51"/>noble Tincture; from hence it moderates, and in time quite taketh away, both the <hi>Leproſie,</hi> and its root, or fountain, an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure and degenerated Blood. It ſtoppeth all preternatural Fluxes, both in Man, and Woman, and this by reaſon of its Styp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Salt, and Mature Sulphur, hid in its Blood-like Tincture. It comforteth, and ſtrengthneth the Heart, and Stomach, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, and cheriſheth, our <hi>humidum Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicale,</hi> and this by its own <hi>humidum Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicale,</hi> which is in a manner very like, if not equal with the <hi>humidum Radicale</hi> of our Bodies. It diſſolveth congealed Blood, and this by its Spirit, and diſſolved Salt, moſt profitable in all poyſoned Wounds, and a high remedy for all Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, if mixed with any Balſam, becauſe by its Styptick, and Blood-cleanſing Salt, it accelerateth the Cicatrization, and ſo produceth a perfect Cure. In brief, it is ſo noble a Medicine, that it deſerves a far higher Character than I ſhall now trouble my Self, or the Reader, with an account of; for, it mundifieth the Blood ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and throughly, that it may in all affects, diſtreſſes, and debilitations, or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97616:52"/>weaknings of Nature whatever, moſt ſafely and ſucceſsfully be made uſe of, and adminiſtred, and this both to Old and Young in ſome appropriate Vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Balſamus Vitae.</head>
               <p>THe Virtues of this pure Quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential and Balſamick Liquor, are alſo ſo numerous and large, that enough cannot be ſaid of it, being ſuch a one as would (were it poſſible) reſtore even the Dying to Life: Of how great benefit therefore it may be to the Living, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing under painful, tedious, and lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering Infirmities, (which otherwiſe, by the help of good Medicines might ſoon recover) I leave to the Judicious to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. In ſhort, it exceedingly reſtoreth the Aged, Ptiſical, Hectical, Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, &amp;c. and beyond expreſſion ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, comforteth, and raiſeth thoſe that are ſpent, and almoſt quite waſted by a tedious and long fit of Sickneſs: In ſhort time (reſpect being had to their low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) reviving their low and decayed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97616:52"/>Spirits, and reſtoring the Body to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer deſired and healthful condition. In brief, it is ſo excellent a Balſamick, and Cordial Liquor, and of ſo pleaſant and fragrant a Smell, ſweet and grateful a Taſte, that it far excelleth the moſt famous <hi>Syrian</hi> (<hi>Aegyptian,</hi> or <hi>Mechaan</hi>) Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, which is of ſo high worth, that three or four pound of it is Yearly a Preſent for the great Turkiſh Emperour: Yet as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious as it is, it is far exceeded by this moſt excellent Cordial, and pleaſant pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Quinteſſential Liquor, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Specificum Anodynum Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimum.</head>
               <p>THis moſt noble, (ſpecifick) and benign Medicine, is ſo truly friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto diſtreſſed Nature, and her op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and debilitated Forces, that even in the moment almoſt that it is taken, (unleſs Nature be irrecoverably ſpent, and no way again to be re-inforced for a longer continuance in her clayie Manſion) it doth not only afford a preſent ſuccour, and relief, (and that by a moſt Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical)
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97616:53"/>and not cold Stupefactive means, (as ſome may happily imagine) but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, and that by its moſt truly genuine Specifick quality, to an utter Extirpation, and Eradication of the Diſeaſe, by its powerful opening unto Nature, her Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed paſſages, Royal walks, and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, and this through all parts of the Body, by which Nature's frequent, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, unuſual, and preternatural Paſſions, are preſently allayed, and Nature moſt quietly again aſſumes her wonted courſe, and undiſturbed progreſs.</p>
               <p>I can with much confidence give the ſame Character of it, that <hi>Quercetan</hi> once did of another preparation of the ſame Subject; <hi>Hoc praeſtantiſſimum medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum omnes ardores extinguit, &amp; arcet, omnes defluxiones ſiſtit, omneſque dolores mirum in modum ſedat, atque hoc totum ut calorem nativum non extinguat quin potius conſervat &amp; tuetur (imo multiplicat) Spiritus innatos corroborando, tantum abest quod ipſos ſtupefaciat, vel (quod dictu ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculum est) partibus adimat, ſed mira qua pollet facultate vires juvando, &amp;c.</hi> Quercet. <hi>in Reſponſ. ad</hi> Aubert, &amp;c.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97616:53"/>This opportune and friendly Operation by ſome (to render it more taking and facile to ordinary apprehenſions) hath been called a laying of the Diſeaſe to Sleep, or a mitigation of the Diſeaſe, which indeed it is; but how? Not by Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pefaction, but only by its prevalent aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and inabling Nature to do that, which, with her own feeble and over-powered Forces, ſhe was no way able to perform, and ſo ſhe ceaſeth, or leaveth off, her fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther furious aſſaults, and ſtruglings, (called a Diſeaſe) with her now vanquiſh'd and departing Antagoniſt; hence, it is moſt uſeful in all Diſeaſes, Diſtempers, and Maladies attended with extremity of Pain, and want of Reſt, as Fevers, Agues, Phrenſie, Deliriums, &amp;c. where Nature, by her continued Duel and Combat, hath ſo infeebled, both her Self, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence, that no other remedy almoſt will give her that preſent ſuccour, relief, and aſſiſtance, that her deplorable Condition of neceſſity calls for, and requires. I ſhall ſay no more of it than this, that it is a truly noble Specifick Anodyne, ſafely aſſiſtant, and friendly unto ſpent Nature,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:97616:54"/>and her wearied and languiſhing <hi>Archeus,</hi> being ſuch a one as may, without the leaſt doubt or fear, be made uſe of in any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition whatever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A word touching the State of Phyſick and Phyſicians.</head>
               <p>HE was never yet Born that could pleaſe all, it is therefore but Folly to expect it; nor indeed ought a wiſe Phyſician ſo much to ſtudy ways for the ſatisfying every Nurſe, old Goſſip, and the indiſcreet Patient, as truly good Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines (together with his Care) for the performance and diſcharge of the Duty that lies upon him; and whereas the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Phyſicians were had in great eſteem and reſpect for the worthineſs of their Calling, it is now altogether contrary, and this through the great Folly of (even) Phyſicians themſelves, each one ſeeking to Ingratiate himſelf, and this by Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, by mean and pleaſing Conceſſions, in plain Engliſh a ſervile Sycophancy, though not at all profitable to their Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, rather than really to perform that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97616:54"/>Duty that a true Phyſician ought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, ſeeking more to pleaſe the Fancy than Cure the Diſeaſes of their Patients, thereby Curing in a ſhort time, inſtead of their Patients, their own ſickly, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt expiring Purſes; and he that doth otherways is not now eſteemed, ſuch is the Folly (and ſo much doth Cuſtom prevail with the generality) of people;</p>
               <p>And if any Phyſician be ſo honeſt, and careful, as induſtriouſly to ſeek for, and prepare, good Medicines, he is preſently as it were excluded out of the number of the putatitious Doctors, more honoured for their Name, and ſome formal outward Accoutrements, than any thing in them, that may in the leaſt render them worthy that Honourable Name they aſſume, and uſurp, or is otherways without their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert put upon them; many other are the reaſons of that great Diſ-reſpect, and Cloud, that this moſt worthy Profeſſion doth now lye under; but doubtleſs, there are many, both induſtrious, and ingenious Perſons now of it, which are (and will as Pillars uphold and maintain) the Life of it, and the time (I hope) is now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97616:55"/>wherein it will recover its due Eſteem and Splendor; for many of the moſt Learned, Sober, and Diſcreet Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior (Doctors or) Phyſicians, of this Age, well obſerving the great Diſ-eſteem it now ſuffers under, and conſidering the Cauſe of it, do find, that it is partly from the ſmall benefit their Patients receive from their chargeable Viſits, or more truly, from their moſt ineffectual (though moſt chargeable preſcribed) Medicines; obſerving (I ſay) this Defect to ariſe (and that moſt undoubtedly) from the great inefficacy of their preſcribed Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, they do now begin (though but privately, as being partly aſhamed) to quit their former obſtinacy, refuſal, and contempt of the only pure (Chymical) and well prepared Medicines, and partly for fear of being Eſteemed by others De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters of the Old (and as they have ſtrongly pretended, the only ſafe, though indeed moſt ineffectual and rotten) foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and method of Phyſick. They begin, (I ſay) though but ſecretly, to conſider, open, and ranſack the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and rich Caskets, and Cabinets of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97616:55"/>Nature, thence to draw forth, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare, thoſe moſt excellent <hi>Arcanaes,</hi> and <hi>Quinteſſences,</hi> there ſtored up, and in plenty beſtowed upon us by Almighty God; by which, doubtleſs, the infirm and languiſhing (though it may be afterwards ingrateful) Patient, will quickly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his former Health, and the Doctor not ſo frequently, as now of late, hear, Thus, (his Patient's moſt earneſt intreaty) <hi>For God's ſake put me not into a tedions and chargeable courſe of Phyſick;</hi> This being performed, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the rich Store-houſe of Nature being unlocked, and opened by the skilful and learned Phyſician, then will Phyſick, and its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, again acquire that due Eſteem, Reward, and Honour, which the Antients ſo deſervedly reaped by it; But this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and reſtauration muſt this Science receive, only from thoſe which <hi>Paracelſus</hi> calls <hi>Aſtrales diſcipuli,</hi> its <hi>Aſtral diſciples,</hi> or thoſe by God, and Nature fitted for it, with a <hi>Genius,</hi> diſpoſition, inclination, and real ability for an unwearied and deep ſearch into Nature, and her inmoſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes; It is not a Superficial Academick
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97616:56"/>Learning, and Fruitleſs diſputation, (of <hi>ens, &amp; non ens</hi>) nor is it, as <hi>Paracelſus</hi> (in his Epiſtle to <hi>Christ. Clauſer. Med. &amp; Philoſo.</hi>) tells us, <hi>Titles Eloquence, the Knowledge of Tongues, or the Reading of many Books, but a profound Meditation, and Knowledge of Nature, and her Myſteries, which eaſily ſupplies all other Defects, and alone is able to make a true Phyſician.</hi> I would not from this Citation of <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> be thought to vilifie, ſlight, contemn, and diſcountenance Learning, and hereby excite, and incourage, every Dull-pated Mechanick (fit only to be a Mechanick) to the Study of the moſt abtruſe, ſublime, and myſterious Secrets of Nature; No, I am one that truly eſteem and highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Learning, and all thoſe that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched and adorned with ſo deſirable a Jewel, as being not ignorant, but well weighing, and knowing how great an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage (and as great an Ornament) it is to thoſe, whoſe propitious Fates have added it (as a bleſſing) to their other moſt acute and great natural Abilities; yet do I not, for all this, Idoliſe, and ſo Adore it, as to diſ-eſteem thoſe modeſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97616:56"/>and truly ingenious Spirits, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Stars have deprived them of that which they not only own as an (almoſt) incomparable Treaſure, and being ſenſible of the want of it, and their great Defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency by that want, do not only priſe, but earneſtly deſire it, and at laſt obtain (by a continued diligence) no ſmall Portion, or Improvement in it; for I very well know, and have often found, even admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conceptions in ſuch as have ſcarce attained to the reading of their own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-tongue, God beſtowing extraordinary natural parts, as well in Cottages, as in Regal Courts, on Peaſants, as on Princes, which, if poliſhed, by the Artifice, and advantage of Learning, would (doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) prove even the wonders of their Age, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe I eſteem, and would alſo incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and cheriſh, and not thoſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ignorant Fellows, whoſe Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance prompts them, and their Confidence and Impudence imboldens them, to bid Defiance to all above them, and will tell you, that it is not Greek, Latin, and ſuch ſtuff and traſh, that will cure Diſeaſes.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97616:57"/>This the Wiſe well know, and yet as well know, that thoſe moſt Confident, and Impudent (and as Ignorant as Impudent) Boaſters, muſt be, and are beholden, (if at any time they have any thing that is good) not only to thoſe that have the advantage of them in Latin, Greek, and other improving Education, but alſo to thoſe that have neither Latin, Greek, nor any thing of what the World calls Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, more than themſelves, and yet far exceed them in all, but a more than Bruitiſh confidence, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe (I mean theſe modeſt, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Spirits, though not improved by the moſt deſirable help of Learning, and Education) may certainly, (with theſe who exceed them in ſo great an advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) not improperly, be accounted in the number of thoſe <hi>Aſtrales diſcipuli,</hi> which <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> and others, tell us, are only fit for the ſtudy, and ſearch of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and conſequently the true, and only able Phyſicians, being, ſaith he, <hi>(ad hoc à Deo nati)</hi> created, and ſent into the World only for that work and purpoſe; and that this is true, variety of Examples in every
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97616:57"/>or all Ages may ſufficiently convince us, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe, and theſe only, are thoſe that Providence hath ordained for the reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Phyſick, that moſt noble, and myſterious of Sciences. But to recede, and give period to this Digreſſion, which my juſt and natural Zeal to the proſperity of this laudable Science, hath led me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; My requeſt (as a truly well wiſher) to all the Learned, Diligent, and Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Profeſſors of Phyſick, is, that they inceſſantly labour to repair the breaches of their Profeſſion, which indeed is no way to be performed, but by a ſerious converſing with the Wiſe; I mean the Books (or Monuments) left unto us by the Antient, Learned, and Nature-ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Philoſophers, to which, as a Teſt and proof of the reality of their Theorical knowledge, they would alſo add a moſt unwearied Manual operation, which only is able to manifeſt the verity of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of their Speculations in a Phyſical way, and detect, and produce, the moſt large and admirable of Nature's infinite Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; for God hath not included any
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97616:58"/>thing in the Creature, but he hath given abſolute power unto Man, (as Lord of the Creation) to make himſelf fully Maſter of it, and that in its higheſt degree of Purity and Perfection; then will they attain unto ſuch noble Secrets, and Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, as ſhall eaſily expel, not only the ſmalleſt, but alſo the greateſt, and moſt contumatious, or ſtubborn, venomous, and chronick Diſeaſes, provided the Infirm have not yet attained <hi>ad justam metam aetatis,</hi> to the juſt and utmoſt limits of time appointed by God himſelf, for then the ſlighteſt, ſmalleſt, and moſt trivial of Diſtempers is (as <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> in his Book of the Myſtery of Worms, tells us) <hi>Introitus ad mortem,</hi> an Inlet to Death, which (as being the Will of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty) there is no farther reſiſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, nor redemption from, nor can any, even the beſt of Medicines, prevail againſt it; Otherways pure Nature is ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to aſſiſt and ſtrengthen Nature to the expulſion of the moſt violent of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, ſuch is the power of pure <hi>Arcanaes,</hi> which being had as altogether neceſſary for the Cure of chronick and contagious
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97616:58"/>Diſeaſes, there will then be no need of the now too numerous Phyſical Muſtard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots, nor of the dubious <hi>Diacritick and Diagnoſtick</hi> part of Phyſick, but only a true knowledge of the ſtrength and doſe of the Medicine; and this the moſt honeſt (and as learned as honeſt) <hi>Faber</hi> tells us, <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito uno Arcanorum, vel Animantium vel Vegetabilium vel Mineralium, non est opus ſcire &amp; cognoſcere undenam morbus oriatur, &amp; qua via procedat ad interficiendum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſed opus est ſcire doſim Arcani, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinare ipſam cum juſculo aut vino, in quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque morbo; tunc temporis enim ab ipſa propinatione Arcanum jungitur naturae, &amp; Natura roborata &amp; fortior facta ab ipſo Arcano, morbum aggreditur, &amp; expellit materiam morbificam quacunque in parte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideat; nam ſemper natura morborum est Curatrix, &amp;c.</hi> Pet. Fab. <hi>Sap. Univerſa.</hi> lib. pri. cap. 21. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Having</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>any one</hi> Arcanum, <hi>be it either of the Animal, Vegetable,</hi> or <hi>Mineral</hi> Kingdom, there is then no need of the uncertain Indications, Diagno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, Prognoſticks, and the like Verbal impertinences, <hi>(fruſtra fit per plura quod
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97616:59"/>fieri poteſt per pauciora.)</hi> We need then do no more, but learn in what Doſe, and Vehicle, to adminiſter ſuch a Medicine; we need not then trouble our ſelves whence the Diſeaſe ſprang, or which way it proceeds, for ſuch a pure Medicine will effectually do all that is requiſite to be done, to corroborate debilitated Nature, and caſt out the Morbifick matter, or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's oppoſite, and obſtructor. Nor is this his ſingle Teſtimony, of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and power of ſuch pure and quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential <hi>Arcanaes,</hi> but a confirmation of the Teſtimonies of all others that have had, and been Maſters of, ſuch exquiſite, Celeſtial, and pure Medicines. From the ſame conſideration doubtleſs did the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arace ſus</hi> thus adviſe us, <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ignis in omnibus morbis ſummum eſt Arcanum, &amp; quicunque medicorum Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ignis in ſua (liceat ita loqui) ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canitate (ſive Medicina) non habet, is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum verum &amp; probatum (adeptum) me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum non jactet, ſed tyronem &amp; loculorem expilatorem.</hi> Paracel. <hi>in Tract. de Sulp. Emb. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Phyſician (ſaith he) that hath not
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97616:59"/>raiſed his Medicines to the Nature of Fire, ought not to aſſume the Name of a Phyſician, for he (indeed) is no other than an Impoſtor, and Cheat, for the Element of Fire is the great <hi>Arcanum</hi> in Curing all Diſeaſes. Take yet his farther Inſtruction, though in a more dark and Philoſophical manner of expreſſion, <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus ſit deus altiſſimus &amp; glorioſiſſimus qui ex immenſo ejus amore &amp; ſumma miſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia tales medicinis puriſſimis conceſſit ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los quales medicis, etiamſi peritiſſimis, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gavit.</hi> Paracelſus <hi>in Xenodoch, (nondum typis excuſ.) Bleſſed be</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>our moſt high and glorious God, who of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite love and mercy towards us, hath given thoſe Eyes to good and pure Medicines, which he hath denied to the most able and skilful of Phyſicians.</hi> What theſe pure Medicines are, he hath already told us, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Medicines exalted by purging and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Chymical preparations, even to the nature of Fire, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the higheſt purity and perfection; for then are they <hi>Galen's medicamenta partium te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuium,</hi> or Medicines fit to be adminiſtred for the freeing oppreſſed Nature, from
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97616:60"/>her languiſhing, and infeebled Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Great is the favour theſe moſt excellent Men have in the fore-going Aphoriſms, or Inſtruction, afforded us, but we are both Fooliſh and Ingrateful, for while we thirſt after Wealth, we neglect the only Men and Means that would direct us to it, and do not, with the wiſe King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> firſt ſeek and deſire the fountain that would effectually, and plentifully bring us, not only thoſe ſmaller Streams, or Rivulets, we ſo much deſire and pine after, but alſo the full Streams of the higheſt of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary Bleſſings.</p>
               <p>But to return from this Digreſſion to our <hi>Arcanaes,</hi> and the Subjects fit for ſuch a degree of Exaltation, you may, if you pleaſe, conſult the moſt expert <hi>Paracelſus</hi> in his <hi>Mannuale de lapide Phyſico;</hi> His <hi>Archidoxis lib. de vita longa,</hi> and other places of his Writings, to which you may add, and peruſe, <hi>Quercetan, Faber, Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, Sennertus, Hartman, Crollius, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius, Marſilius, Ficinus, Baſilius, Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> with (almoſt infinite) others, who, with much Charity, and Sincerity, have
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97616:60"/>delivered unto us moſt admirable Secrets, would we with an anſwerable and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Diligence, peruſe, elaborate, and make uſe of them, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If ſome (haply) ſhould object, and tell me, that it cannot poſſible be, that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, how highly ſoever elaborated, and prepared, can effect ſuch Miracles, and ſuddain Cures, as are attributed to them; Let me tell him from the wiſe <hi>Hermes,</hi> that, <hi>quicquid ſuperius est, idem est etiam inferius;</hi> if there be power in the Planets, or Stars, thoſe great Miniſters of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the Angel Guardians, and ſucceſſive Rulers of the World under him, as certainly there is, and far beyond even the beſt and largeſt of our wiſhes, to all intents and purpoſes whatever, then can we not deſpair (if we will credit <hi>Hermes</hi>) of obtaining (upon a diligent inquiſition) the utmoſt aim and ends of our deſires; for, doubtleſs, he hath not placed any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, or virtue whatever, in thoſe ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Bodies, that we ſhould ſuppoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for us to procure, and attain to, (for our own good, and his glory) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are out of our hand-reach
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97616:61"/>placed in the Heavens; for whatever is below, hath the ſame Virtue with that which is above hath, and that which is above, but the ſame with that below; whatever is above hath its likeneſs below, and what we have here below in our reach, and power, hath in its Centre and Purity (as being produced by the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior rays and influx) the ſame virtue, efficacy, and power, that thoſe moſt bright, and ſuperior Bodies, we ſo much admire and gaze at, have, and contain in them, would we begin where Nature leaves, and help her in what ſhe cannot perfect for us: <hi>At hic labor, hoe opus est,</hi> This is a work only for the Wiſe and Prudent. If any one ſhall yet Cavil at this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and tell me, this is no way agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with the Inſtructions; and Method left unto us by <hi>Galen, Hippocrates,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the only Founders, and Pillars of Phyſick, whoſe preſcriptions direct us to diverſity of Medicines, for diverſity of Diſeaſes, and that they made no uſe of poyſonous Minerals, and Metals, but of the moſt ſafe, and wholſome of Animals, and Vegetables, &amp;c. To thoſe that ſhall
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97616:61"/>thus object, let me tell them, That I think they have as little Verſed themſelves in the Writings of thoſe whoſe followers they pretend themſelves to be, as in theirs, whom they are only able, through Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, Malice, and Cuſtom, to rail at, and revile, but no way able to Confute, or in the leaſt overthrow their Doctrines, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and built upon the Rock of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and confirmed by daily innumerable examples of Experience; and this in the moſt deſperate of Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>As to their uſing only the moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and ſafe of Vegetables, and Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, let them call to mind their <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor. Albus</hi> and <hi>Niger, Elater. Colocynth. Tithymal. Thapſia. Turpethu. Bryon. Scam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. Cyclamen,</hi> with ſeveral others of the like violence in Operation, which, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a due Correction, and Chymical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, come not much (if at all) ſhort of the moſt violent, and (as termed) moſt venomous of Minerals: but becauſe we will alſo let them ſee how well grounded and perfect they are in their Maſter's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, that tell us of our Venomous and Health-deſtroying Minerals; and would
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97616:62"/>ſo ſilence our new Doctrine, as they very Gravely are pleas'd to call it; Let them conſult <hi>Myre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſus</hi> in his Book of Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, of the choiceſt, and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent compoſitions of their (Hodg-podg) Antidotes, and theſe from the moſt ſelect and able of <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> and they ſhall there find few leſs, if not ſomewhat more, than an hundred of thoſe Antidotes, which have in them, as their chief Ingredients, Ground, or Baſis, either Minerals, Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minerals, or Metals, and thoſe in a moſt crude and unprepared condition.</p>
               <p>See now the great Obſtinacy, joyned with a no leſs Ignorance, of many, that pretend themſelves the ſtrict followers of thoſe ſedulous and moſt laborious Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> his Temple. And ſeeing <hi>nihil perfectione in principio gaudet,</hi> certainly thoſe Men, <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> (to whom we cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelves extremely ingaged, for delivering over unto us, their then more than ordinary Light, and Knowledge) intended not their Labours (ſo freely communicated for the good of Poſterity) as <hi>Herculean Pillars,</hi> or a <hi>non plus ultra,</hi> to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97616:62"/>the indeavours of thoſe ingenious Spirits that ſhould ſucceed them, and by decree of Providence enter upon the Stage of the World after them, and that for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Glory of Almighty God, as the Men and means provided, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by him, for the diſcovery (or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation) of ſome larger part of thoſe innumerable Treaſures of Wonders, and Knowledge, which he is (infinitely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the apprehenſion of all Mortals, that ever were, or ſhall be) able to draw forth, and beſtow upon frail Man, for his ſolace, comfort, and admiration, to his Creator's glory. And this will well and clearly appear by the Ingenious confeſſion (or rather admonition, and excitation) of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> to a farther diſcovery and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement; whoſe Conceſſion, let us take for the unanimous conſent of all thoſe moſt acute <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or antient Founders of that Fabrick, which we ought with all diligence and ſincerity (for a publique good) to build up, and adorn. <hi>Medicina</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non eam aſſecuta est adhuc perfectionem, cui nihil addi poſſit, ſed in qua ſemper vel aliquid modo reprehendi,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97616:63"/>modo corrigi, modo addiſci queat,</hi> Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, &amp;c. In this, this great and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Phyſician tells us, that Medicine (or the Science of Phyſick) had not then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to ſo great Perfection, that nothing could be added to it, but that it yet ſtood in ſuch a condition, as might well admit of reprehenſion, correction, and farther inquiſition and addition. Words truly worthy, ſo worthy a Perſon, and ſuch a one, as, were he now in being, would (I dare be confident) not only allow of thoſe rational and real amendments which Poſterity hath added to their Labours, but with greateſt Alacrity, and Cheerfulneſs, imbrace the means and knowledge of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding yet a greater Perfection to ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, and laudable a Science; and not, as ſome of their wilful and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Diſciples, and Succeſſors, malitiouſly ſtop both Eyes, and Ears, againſt what only would make them what they ſhould be, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Phyſicians in Knowledge, and Deed, and not only Putatitious <hi>(&amp; ſolùm nomine &amp; togaetenus)</hi> pretenders to the greateſt of Contemplations, and Nature's Secrets, of which they yet know nothing,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97616:63"/>but only by their (Methodical) Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance keep the generality of people in a Maze, and ſervile adoration to their empty Noddles.</p>
               <p>This only to thoſe pretended <hi>Galeniſts,</hi> who uſe the name of <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> together with other moſt deſerving Learned Men, their followers, only as ſtalking Horſes, to ſhadow and hide their Ignorance from the World's Eye, and a Warrant (at pleaſure and large) to rail at, and caſt ignominy and reproach on the Names and Repute of ſuch moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Hermetick Philoſophers and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, as themſelves are no way worthy to mention, and whoſe Works, (the only means and evidence left us to judge of Antiquity) together with thoſe of their pretended Patrons, <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> they have as little peruſed, as they have ſtudied the <hi>Turkiſh Alcoran,</hi> much leſs concocted, to make a right uſe of them, to the benefit and aſſiſtance of their languiſhing (deceived) Patients, &amp;c. I think not thus of all that are diligently Studious, and moſt ſtrict followers of thoſe Fathers of Phyſick, <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97616:64"/>for I know many of them moſt learned, judicious, and diſcreet Perſons; and what they are not yet ſatisfied in, or cannot yet well aſſent to, they will not however preſently with a raſh Malice, conclude, and condemn as Erroneous; Many of them alſo (ſometime ſtrong Aſſertors of the Antient Dogmatical me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Phyſick, as the only ſafe, and moſt effectual way) have at laſt thought it no ſhame to give place unto their better Conſiderations, and allow of Purity as the only means to Perfection, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly owned, and profeſſed themſelves <hi>Med. utriuſque ſtudioſos,</hi> Perſons allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Studious as well of the Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical, as Galenical way of Medicines. Otherſome of them have been ſo much farther (from a daily clear Experience) convinced of the excellency of Medicines purified, and ſeparated from their dirty and droſſie Parts, (which are the only Obſtructors of thoſe admirable effects, they would otherways produce) that they think nothing fit for adminiſtration in a Phyſical way, that hath not (in ſome meaſure) paſſed the Teſt of Chymical
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97616:64"/>preparation, and purification, which, (in brief) let the Sons of Art (I mean ſuch as have made ſome happy progreſs in their Labours, and ſo apprehend in few words things of great moment) accept of, and receive from me as followeth: As to the preparation of Medicines, out of Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, or Animals, thus. If thou wouldſt have an <hi>Arcanum</hi> of Vegetables, firſt bring them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Vegetables, to a due putrefaction, and fermentation; then ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract the volatile Parts; ſeparate their Flegm, and other Impurities by due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration; then, after a due Incineration, or Calcination of their <hi>Cap. Mortuum,</hi> or <hi>Faeces,</hi> extract, and purifie the more fixed; joyn the fixed, and volatile in due order; digeſt, and fix the <hi>Arcanum</hi> by fitting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Heat; increaſe, or multiply it both in virtue and quantity, by a due Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, <hi>ex quo aliquod naſcitur ex eodem nutritur;</hi> do the like with Animals, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in fermentation, which, in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration may be excuſed: As to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Metals, Bodies of all other the moſt compact, and (almoſt) incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, much might be ſaid, not intended
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97616:65"/>at this time to be divulged; of Minerals, I ſhall at preſent ſay nothing, and only give a ſhort (and but a ſhort) account of the preparations of Metals for Phyſick, and to a Medicinal uſe; As to the making of moſt rich Perfumes, we commonly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the moſt pleaſing and Odoriferous of Nature's products; ſo doubtleſs, the beſt of Animals, and Vegetables, muſt of neceſſity be the fitteſt Subjects to make, and prepare into the beſt of (ſuch) Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; We will alſo (as in reaſon we ought) ſuppoſe the like of Metals, and therefore for Metallick Medicines, or our <hi>Metalline Arcanaes,</hi> aſſume and take the beſt of Metals, <hi>(viz.) Gold,</hi> and <hi>Silver;</hi> The manner and method to prepare theſe, is various, I ſhall only touch at two, and leave the reſt to the ſearch of thoſe that ſhall not in theſe find the Satisfaction they deſire. The one is by a Retexion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weaving, or opening (may I ſo ſay) of what Nature ſo carefully hath, as it were, bound up, and concocted, and wholly, or in part, fixed, (after her utmoſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Purification.) This by ſome hath been called a reduction of the ſubject
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97616:65"/>Philoſophical into its firſt matter, <hi>Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> (a Spiritual Body) &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This by otherſome (and thoſe ſuch as think themſelves no mean Proficients in the ſearch of Nature, and her choiceſt Secrets) hath been laughed at, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed only a Philoſophical fable: However, I dare, and do here affirm the truth, and poſſibility of it, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Reduction, or Retexion of ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a Body as Gold is, hath by one moſt excellent Engliſh Philoſopher <hi>(G. R.)</hi> been called a paſſing it <hi>per Rotam Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophiae,</hi> a carrying or paſſing it through the Wheel (or ſubtile preparations) of Philoſophy; and as Nature had her own Fire for the production of this Phyſical Subject, <hi>(viz.) Gold,</hi> the perfecteſt of her Works, ſo (to ſhorten ſomewhat our intended Operation) may we uſe the ſame Fire for the Deſtruction, Reduction, Retexion, Regeneration, and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this her utmoſt Maſter-piece, to bring it to that heighth, which ſhe of her ſelf could not advance it to, but left the Maſtery to Art's Induſtry, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the heightning her begun (and ended) Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97616:66"/>to a ſupernatural degree of purity and perfection, and that in a double, tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ten-fold, or an hundred-fold degree, &amp;c. beyond what ſhe was of her ſelf able to exalt it to.</p>
               <p>I ſay, to this Operation we may (as moſt neceſſary) make uſe of her Magical, yet natural Fire, the true Univerſal and Balſamic <hi>ignis Naturae,</hi> (or rather <hi>contra Naturam,</hi> as here to be uſed, yet) the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal preſervation, and conſervation of all products that the Eyes of Man do behold. The ſecond, and laſt preparation, I ſhall point at, is, the Reduction of our aſſumed, Medicinal Subject, <hi>(viz.) Gold,</hi> by its Specificated <hi>humidum Radicale,</hi> (a true Metalline fire) <hi>in ſpeciem Naturae,</hi> into the ſame ſpecies of Nature, with this Metallick volatile Fire, which, being by a true Philoſophical skill, brought to this paſs, and Nature, it will not then be any hard matter to make a true Union of our now Spiritual Body, with its true (Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificated) <hi>humidum Radicale,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This is that great Philoſophical Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, whoſe Clue hath been ſought by many, but found by few. This is the Key
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97616:66"/>that only opens unto us a Gate into the greateſt of Nature's Medicamental Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; It hath therefore been very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly mentioned by Philoſophers, and if at any time touched upon, as ſuddenly (as it was frugally, and ſparingly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, or unveiled) again clouded by ſome following Sophiſm. The moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found <hi>Lully</hi> is (indeed) herein, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more charitable than moſt others have been, where he tells us, <hi>Spiritus non potest miſceri cum corpore perfecte, niſi edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum fuerit corpus in ſpeciem Naturae, id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circo qua do vis miſcere corpus cum ſpiritu, reducendum eſt corpus illud in ſpeciem Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae per vinculum amoris naturalis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Spirit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>cannot be rightly joyned with a Body, unleſs that Body be firſt brought in ſpeciem Naturae with that Spirit. If therefore thou wouldst (at any time) joyn a Spirit with any Body, thou must bring that Body into an equality with that Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Conſider now well what I have here given thee a Light to; and weigh well the great Charity of the ſaid Venerable <hi>Lully</hi> in the following ſentence, <hi>Corpora praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97616:67"/>&amp; reducenda ſunt ad unam aequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem cum ſpiritibus, &amp; ita ſimul ponantur, &amp; fiat verum matrimonium &amp; conjunctio; niſi enim corpora &amp; ſpiritus quae conjungere vis, ſint reducta ad unicam eſſentiam &amp; unam Naturam, non permiſcentur &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungantur, ut aqua cum aqua; decipiuntur igitur Stulti, qui putant poſſe conjungere ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus cum corporibus, in eorum craſſitie &amp; diverſitate Naturae, quoniam non fieri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, donec deducantur in unam aequalitatem formae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thoſe Bodies (ſaith he) that thou wouldſt joyn with Spirits, thou muſt firſt reduce to the Nature of Spirits, ſo may they be put together, and a true Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, Union, or Conjunction be made; and herein are thoſe Fools deceived, that think to joyn Spirits with Bodies, in their groſsneſs, and diverſity of Nature: This is altogether impoſſible, and therefore are they deceived in their intentions.</q> To ſtrengthen this moſt rational Counſel of the moſt expert <hi>Lully,</hi> take yet the farther advice of that great and knowing Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher <hi>Calid, Non morabitur ſpiritus in corpore, nec cum eo ullatenus remanebit, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97616:67"/>ipſum corpus habeat ex ſubtilitate &amp; tenisitate, ut habet ſpiritus, nam cum corpus attenuatum fuerit, &amp; ſubtiliatum &amp; à ſua denſitate exierit, ſpiſſitudine, craſſitie &amp; corporeitate ad ſpiritualem eſſentiam, tunc commiſcebitur ſpiritibus ſubtilibus &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibitur in iis, &amp; ſic uterque evadit unum &amp; idem, &amp; non ſeparabuntur, ſicut nec aqua mixta aquae,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Then (ſaith he, ſpeaking of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of Spirits and Bodies to a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical uſe) will Spirits remain with the Bodies (thou wouldſt joyn them with) when the Bodies are firſt brought back to the nature of Spirits, and a Spiritual Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from their groſs and heavy Bodies, then will they remain with one another, as Water with Water, inſeparably, and never again be parted, <hi>Nam naturâ Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura gaudet, &amp; ſimile ſimili jungitur,</hi> &amp;c. I have here given you the Unanimous advice of two great Philoſophers, towards the preparation of Gold, and Silver, into the moſt excellent of Medicines. What I have here, with the Authority of two ſuch eminent Philoſophers, intimated, (or rather plainly declared) will haply by
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97616:68"/>ſome be thought too trivial, and of ſmall moment, or concernment, towards the diſcharge of my promiſe in this point; and further, demand how this is to be done, and when done, how farther to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed with them to the true conjunction, and creation of Medicine.</p>
               <p>To theſe I ſhall anſwer, (in brief) thus, That, which I have here, in relation to my promiſe declared, though I give it them (for their better ſatisfaction and opinion of the thing) in the words of ſo great Authors, and not as from my Self, and in my own Style and Dialect, (which I could alſo well have done) is not, as they may deem it, an Admonition ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be paſſed over, and forgotten; but ſuch an one, as, if ſeriouſly conſidered, may in time bring them no ſmall way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the enjoyment of their beſt of wiſhes.</p>
               <p>As to the way and practice for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, I have alſo ſaid more than will, without much meditation, and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be preſently diſcerned: To thoſe that think I have done too little, I have done too much, and ſhall therefore, leſt I
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97616:68"/>receive a worſe reward, for a better and larger diſcovery, leave them to their own Inquiſition after that they deſire. To the Grateful, Modeſt, and Ingenious, I may poſſibly hereafter make ſome farther Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of my meaning, and the true method, and means (but in a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical ſtyle) to attain to their deſire (in a Phyſical way.) For I expect not in the generality of the Students of Phyſick, the ſubtility of <hi>Geber,</hi> nor the profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Raymond Lully.</hi> I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hereafter (haply) in my (inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) <hi>Aurora,</hi> give the Students of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and ſearchers into Nature's admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and moſt myſterious Secrets, thoſe advantageous Inſtructions, which my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſe will not allow of; and therefore, if not yet underſtood, muſt (till then at leaſt, for any thing from me) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a Secret, and indeed, ſuch an one, as being the Gate into the (Phyſical) <hi>Roſary of Philoſophers,</hi> is only attainable by the Aſtral Diſciples, and Sons of Art, or thoſe by Providence deſigned for it, by their own indeavours: But to give (if poſſible) ſome preſent ſatisfaction to the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97616:69"/>more quick apprehenſions, how the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond way of reducing Gold into a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual nature, by its proper Specificated <hi>humidum Radicale,</hi> (in its natural form, or diſſolved) and after into a moſt noble, and fiery (purple) Medicine, may be performed: Take the following moſt clear light, and inſtruction of <hi>Bernard, Treviſan. Nulla aqua</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>naturali reductione ſpeciem metallicam diſſolvit, niſi illa quae permanebit ei in materia &amp; forma, &amp; quam metalla ipſa (diſſoluta) poſſunt recongelare.</hi> No water (ſaith he) will naturally diſſolve the Metallick body, (Gold, or Silver) but that, which will, after diſſolution, remain inſeparably with it, both in matter, and form, and which will afterward be congealed with (or by) the Metallick diſſolved Body, &amp;c. The weight and clearneſs of this Inſtruction, I ſhall not more inſiſt on; I have now opened the Gate, where thou mayſt enter into the moſt ſpatious, and delightful of Nature's Courts; nay, I have farther led thee into the path that will bring thee into her own choiceſt of Secrets, where I alſo hold up the Curtain to thee, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97616:69"/>(<hi>Magnalia Naturae,</hi> or) Nature in the greateſt of her Majeſty; but I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſpeak more of theſe Myſteries, known unto ſo few, leſt I too much violate the juſt, and moſt reaſonable Injunctions of the Wiſe. I have ſaid more than enough to the Ungrateful, and ſufficient to the Grateful, and Ingenious, <hi>Qui oculos habet videat, Qui aures habet audiat, &amp; capiat qui capere poteſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If any one, from what I have in this friendly manner communicated as to the preparations of Metals (and indeed the beſt of Metals) to a Phyſical uſe, ſhall ſo far miſ-conſtrue my Inſtructions, as to imagine them to have relation to Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, as well for Metalline, as Human Bodies. It lieth not in my power to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand (or ſet bounds unto) his Thoughts, nor would I, if I could; let him therefore freely, and fully uſe his liberty, and, if he can, make a benefit of it beyond my Intentions, which are only Phyſical: He ſhall not yet fail of my well-wiſhes to attend him, and his labours; Nor ſhould I at all envy, but rather rejoyce at his happineſs, that out of ſo poor a Mine,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97616:70"/>could draw ſomething towards ſo Rich a Jewel; and though they are things I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to, yet will I not raſhly deny the poſſibility of them, (being in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſenſible of the great Riches, and Treaſures of Nature) and as I will not deny their reality, ſo neither will I affirm their certainty, but (whatever my acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental, yet poſſible as much ſatisfactory, as wiſhed for, or deſired experience in ſome ſmall things (for I aim not at great ones) may have gained upon my belief, and confidence of them) leave them in their own ineſtimable and unvaluable worth, to be judged by more able and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Perſons, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I have haply ſaid more than Diſcretion would I ſhould, or than I ſhall receive thanks for; of the Fooliſh, Empty, and light Criticks, I expect it not: To the truly Ingenious I know it will be as accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as it is freely delivered; To thoſe only I write, and to thoſe alſo I wiſh a proſperous ſucceſs in their honeſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and Search into the ſuperabundant, and moſt ineſtimable, Treaſures of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:97616:70"/>
               <head>A Continuation upon farther Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</head>
               <p>TO give the Ingenious yet a farther Teſtimony of my good and candid Intentions towards them, and their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſucceſs in Chymical Elaborations, and to prevent the laſie, empty, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Critick, of his ſeemingly juſt Cavil againſt my Obſcurity; (as poſſible for want of Knowledge he may call my (rather) too clear, and open Inſtruction) I here offer, both the one, and the other, a moſt free and honeſt Expoſition of my former hints and admonitions, and that in the very words of the greateſt and moſt able Maſters in Phyſick and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</p>
               <p>The ſpecified <hi>Humidum Radicale</hi> of Metals, which I before ſpake of, (to be now more plain, and charitable than there I was) points only at the <hi>common Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver,</hi> or <hi>vulgar Mercury:</hi> For, that being firſt rightly prepared, and as rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and diſtilled into a clear whitiſh Silvery and Cryſtalline Liquor, is then
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97616:71"/>the Specifick, and only true Metalline diſſolving <hi>Menſtruum,</hi> or Philoſophick <hi>Mercury,</hi> amicable, or friendly to all Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and that only that can radically re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them and all Minerals to their firſt moiſt and unctuous form and Eſſence. And now I have told them thus much in my own ruder Style, I will yet, for their greater and fuller Satisfaction, let them alſo hear what a moſt charitable and honeſt <hi>Adept</hi> tells us of the ſame thing, <hi>Ex mercurio vulgi miris modis fit aqua &amp; oleum, albiſſimum, veluti lac, cui ſi impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur vel aurum vel argentum, diſſolvitur, &amp; aurum &amp; argentum in eo liquore, ſicut glacies in aqua calida, liqueſcit, &amp; ita in ſua principia ſeminalia reducuntur &amp; tunc ſummam cum principiis vitae nostrae confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatem habent. Et hoc modo, &amp; tuta &amp; efficaciſſima adverſus quoſcunque naturae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae morbos reddere poſſis. Sunt quam plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimi qui hanc eſſentiam Mercurialem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere norunt, &amp; perinde non opus eſt ut hic doceatur, &amp; omnibus communis &amp; vulgaris fiat; etſi vulgaris eſſe meretur propter neceſſitatem in Medicina: praeſtantiſſimum enim, imo divinum Medicamentum eſt, quo
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97616:71"/>doctus &amp; prudens medicus &amp; laudem &amp; gloriam ſibi comparare queat; Nihilominùs cum haec ſt totius Alchymiae Margarita, neque prostitui neque indignis communicari debet. Secreta omnia Alchymiae ab illa de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent; is igitur qui eam cupiet, studeat Alchymiae &amp; ejus operibus ſecretis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this as candid as plain Sentence, he tells us, that out of the <hi>Vulgar Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> or <hi>Quickſilver</hi> may, after a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful manner, be made a Water, or Oyl, in which if we ſhall put either Gold, or Silver (firſt rightly thereunto prepared) they will ſweetly <hi>(&amp; ſine ſtrepitu)</hi> be diſſolved in it, as Ice in warm water, and are thereby reduced into their firſt ſeminal principles (or moiſt Eſſence) and have then a moſt near affinity, or conformity with our <hi>Archeus</hi> or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of life (or more plainly with our life it ſelf) and are alſo thereby render<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt ſafe and Efficacious Medicines againſt all diſeaſes whatever that afflict our weak bodies. There are (ſaith he) many that know how to prepare, or make this <hi>Mercurial Liquor,</hi> or <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and therefore it ſhall not be taught,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:97616:72"/>and made common to all, though truly for its admirable Excellency, and vertue in Medicine, it deſerves to be made publick; for it's a moſt noble and a divine Medicine, and ſuch a one as by which the Prudent and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Phyſitian may acquire both praiſe, and glory; yet ſeeing it is, as it is, the onely Pearl, or great <hi>Arcanum</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymie,</hi> it muſt not be proſtituted <hi>(viz.)</hi> communicated to the unworthy. All the ſecrets of <hi>Alchymie</hi> depend upon it. He therefore that deſires it, let him diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply himſelf to <hi>Chymistry</hi> and its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Operations &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not here ſpend time to anſwer the objections and cavills of thoſe that will perhaps tell me, that the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher's Mercury</hi> is not the <hi>common Mercury,</hi> nor is it prepared out of it; this in ſome ſence is true, and I well know (and it may be better than themſelves) that the Philoſophers point at and direct us (though aenigmatically) to <hi>another Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi> and alſo a <hi>compound of Mercuries,</hi> or <hi>Mercurius duplicate</hi> called alſo their Mercury. But I as well know that, that
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97616:72"/>is not (always) their crude, acute, and ſharpe Menſtrual, or diſſolving Mercury: But as <hi>Rich. Anglus, Albertus, Rhaſis,</hi> the <hi>minor Roſary,</hi> and all others, do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, their matured or ſweet concoct, and <hi>Congeling Mercury; cum mercurio ſeu argento vivo diſſolvuntur corpora, eorumque naturae reſerantur &amp; aperiuntur, &amp; in primam materiam reducuntur. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius autem ex corporibus congelatis hoc facere non potest, quia illud ſulphur per congelationem alteratum est in Natura, quod non corrodit ſicut primum.</hi> Rich. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glus, &amp;c. And again, <hi>aqua quae in auro, &amp; argento eſt, est dulcis, nec diſſolvens eſt, ſed potius coagulans, &amp; conſolidans, quia est dulcis, non habens virtutem aceto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam.</hi> Albertus magnus; <hi>Omnia corpora ex mercurio ſuam originem habent, &amp; ex ipſo generantur, &amp; iterum in eum conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuntur; aurum quod ex puro &amp; vivo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curio generatur, iterum ac Mercurium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum convertitur, &amp; hoc ſolummodo per Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentum vivum &amp; nullam aliam rem, omnia corpora in Argentum vivum convertuntur; attamen, Argentum vivum ex auro longe majoris virtutis eſt, figitque citiùs quàm
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97616:73"/>illud argentum vivum quod nunquam fuit, corpus, quia hoc ab isto multum ſuperatur, quantum ad vim ſulphuream, quia argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vivum ex auro calidum eſt, maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linum &amp; ſiccum: Attamen ista duo, quoad materiam, nullam habent differentiam; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lummodo ſecundum digeſtionem differunt, in quantum alterum istorum per calorem na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalem in viſceribus terrae decoctum eſt,</hi> Roſar. minor, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>You may now, by what I have thus freely produced from ſeveral Authorities, eaſily diſcern the difference of their <hi>Mercuries;</hi> the one called their <hi>Crude</hi> and <hi>diſſolving,</hi> the other <hi>Concoct</hi> and <hi>conge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;</hi> this <hi>congeling Mercury</hi> (as one rightly tells us) is called theirs, <hi>Sicut filius patris, quia non producitur abſque adjutorio Philoſophi; quare meritò dicitur ipſorum, quoniam eum uſque ad effectum producunt.</hi> This their <hi>congeling,</hi> or <hi>ſweet coagulating Mercury,</hi> is <hi>Mercurius aut auri aut argenti (viz.)</hi> the <hi>Mercury either of Gold or Silver;</hi> that is, thoſe bodies reduced into a <hi>running Mercury,</hi> or <hi>Quickſilver,</hi> and this by ſome is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (ſubtilly) called onely Theirs,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97616:73"/>amongſt which <hi>R. L.</hi> in effect tells us the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nos dicimus quod Argentum vivum vulgare non poteſt eſse argentum vivum Philoſophorum quocunque modo praeparetur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true; <hi>common Mercury</hi> in this ſence cannot be made their <hi>congeling Mercury,</hi> or <hi>Mercury of bodies,</hi> becauſe it is Crude, and never was yet a perfectly decocted body, and ſo cannot be their <hi>Mercurius corporum,</hi> or <hi>Mercury of bodies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet doth this not hinder but it may be made their <hi>diſſolving</hi> or <hi>Menstrual Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury;</hi> for, though they tell us that the <hi>Mercury of bodies</hi> is altogether neceſſary, yet do they not tell us (except deluſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) that <hi>common Mercury</hi> is not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and this <hi>R. L.</hi> is ſo charitable and genuine as really to confeſs and declare unto us, where he thus ſaith in <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orica Testamenti in clauſula, quae dicit quod argentum vivum vulgi non valet unum ficum putridum; hoc diximus quia multum valet:</hi> and further affirms, that <hi>abſque hac aqua Glorioſa argenti Vivi nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Sulphur naturae ſublimari potest.</hi> But to return to our <hi>congeling Phyſical Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury,</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:97616:74"/>the bodies of Gold and Silver be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reduced into running Mercury will then Inſeparably (and as <hi>R. L.</hi> tells us) <hi>per vinculum amoris naturalis,</hi> joyn, unite, and mix with the common Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury prepared, which then (compound) <hi>Mercury</hi> is alſo many times called theirs. Sometimes their <hi>Rebis,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their red, and white Oyl, and this is animated either with Gold, or Silver: Sometimes by one Name, and ſometimes by another: But to be ſhort, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they tell us of theſe <hi>Mercuries</hi> (as <hi>Geber</hi> doth in a cloſe Philoſophical way, <hi>Mercurius Mercurio facilius jungitur, &amp; Mercurius Mercurio adhaeret</hi> is only to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, that not the bodies, but the <hi>Mercuries</hi> of thoſe bodies, or the <hi>Mercury</hi> extracted out of thoſe bodies, or thoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies reduced into <hi>Mercury,</hi> will then radically, and inſeperably unite with the <hi>Vulgar Mercury,</hi> or Mercury of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or <hi>Saturn,</hi> firſt Philoſophically prepared for ſuch a Conjunction; which, while they remain in their groſs bodies, they will never do; for, <hi>nullum corpus</hi> (as <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> tells us) <hi>in natura ſua manens Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curium
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97616:74"/>coagulare poteſt</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Corpora cum ſpiritibus minùs conueniunt, neque radicali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conjungi poſſunt, quouſque corpus habeat ex Natura ſpiritus, &amp; in unam aequalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem naturae deducuntur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then, and not before, will they duly unite and joyn for the creation, or production of Medicine; and then will the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> of the body, whether of Gold, or Silver, which in <hi>opere Philoſophico</hi> is <hi>loco maſculi,</hi> becauſe <hi>calidus &amp; ſiccus,</hi> congele, dry up, and fix, the <hi>common Mercury,</hi> or Mercury of imperfect bodies, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it ſelf, into a moſt Noble Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſons why, are too tedious (if not too great) here to be declared; but my intention being to inform, (or at leaſt to communicate my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſmall abilities with) the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious <hi>Pyroes,</hi> and diligent Searchers into the Science, and its Meandrous paths, not weary my ſelf with oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, (if they believe not what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid, and produced, as to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving Menſtruum, or Metalline Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Philoſophers) I deſire yet to lead
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97616:75"/>them as it were by the hand a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and let them hear the Modern (but moſt ingenious) <hi>D' Eſpagnet, Lunam Philoſophorum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſive eorum Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curium, qui Mercurium vulgare dixerit aut ſciens fallit, aut ipſe fallitur; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curium enim Philoſophorum argentum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum eſſe, non tamen Vulgare, ſed ab e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> extractum ingenio Philoſophico, Geber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſcripta nos docent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If this ſuffice not, let them with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience hear him yet again in as clear a diſcovery, <hi>Mercurius ex imperfectis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallis ſolus tincturae ſolis &amp; lunae ſuſcipiendae in opere Philoſophico aptus est, ut ipſe tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ plenè imbutus caetera uberrime tingat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> De Eſpag. Opus Arcan. Hermet. Scient.</hi> And <hi>M. S.</hi> in his <hi>Nov. Lumen Chymicum</hi> tells us that <hi>Luna noſtra eſt (non argentum vulgi) quae recipit ſemen Auri</hi>—What this <hi>Luna</hi> is you have but juſt now been informed by <hi>D' Eſpagnet</hi> (viz.) <hi>that it is their Mercury,</hi> and their <hi>Mercury</hi> is their <hi>Luna,</hi> and this <hi>Luna</hi> is <hi>common Mercury</hi> prepared. But this way, though it be to the ſame effect and end with that intended by me, yet it is not the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97616:75"/>ſame manner of proceſs with it; for, this is by a reduction of the perfect Bodies, <hi>(viz.) Gold,</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> into running Mercury, by vulgar Mercury prepared, (then called theirs) and <hi>Mercurius anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> or <hi>Rebis;</hi> or elſe a reduction of thoſe Bodies by ſome Philoſophical Artifice into running Mercury, which was alſo called, as I have ſaid before, <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cut filius Patris)</hi> their Mercury. This Mercury, <hi>loco maſculi,</hi> becauſe <hi>calidus &amp; ficcus,</hi> they joyned, or united with the common Mercury prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or the Mercury of the other imperfect Bodies, and ſo proceeded farther, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their ſecret Cabaliſtical and Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical inſtructions: But there being (as Experience as well as <hi>Geber</hi> aſſures us) more ways than one to one and the ſame end and purpoſe in this moſt noble Art, My intention is to give ſome glance, or glimmering Light, to another way, which ſome (from a more deep conſideration of Nature, and as proceeding to a higher Subtiliſation, both of the <hi>vulgar Mercury,</hi> and alſo of the Bodies by it) have given the name of Univerſal to; whereas the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97616:76"/>other, (they thought) in reſpect of this, merited only the name of particular, which particular was, doubtleſs, that of <hi>Bernard. Treviſan</hi> already cited, <hi>Nulla aqua Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali reductione, &amp;c.</hi> But this of <hi>Treviſan</hi> being not (as I ſaid) the method by me driven at, though to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the production of a moſt excellent Medicine, both for conſervation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of Health: I will not longer with-hold the deſirous Reader from what I intend, and I hope will be for his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and Advantage.</p>
               <p>I have already declared, (my Thoughts) that the common Mercury prepared, and afterwards diſſolved into a clear, milkie, Cryſtalline, and Silvery liquor, or water, is the true Menſtrual, or Metalline diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Mercury of Philoſophers.</p>
               <p>I have alſo already, by ſome eminent Authorities proved the ſame, <hi>(viz.) Ex mercurio vulgi miris modis fit aqua &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leum, &amp;c.</hi> But if that moſt rational In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction be invalid for the begetting a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Verity of it, hear to ſecond it, the moſt profound <hi>R. Lully, Super omnes
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97616:76"/>aquas mundi Aqua mercurii vulgi neceſſaria est, quoniam ſi haberes omnes aquas Mundi (praeter hanc) non poteſt cumillis tranſire, quiaista aperit &amp; claudit noſtram artem, &amp; ſecum portat clavem, &amp; ſeram; ideo cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſiman habeas, &amp; nulli reveles, quia eſſes excommunicatus à deo &amp; Maledictus; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canum enim est, et donum Dei, &amp; Deus qui cognoſcit corda hominum tribuit illud quibus illi placet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that are not yet convinced, and ſatisfied, as to the Subjects, for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the Philoſophers both <hi>diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> and <hi>congeling Mercuries,</hi> muſt (for any thing from me) acquire their content by their own pains; if we muſt and ought to believe Artiſts in their own Art, as moſt requiſite it is, till either our own reaſon, or experience, can better inform us, then doubtleſs if we will meddle with Chymiſtry, and expect good from it, or our attempts in it, we muſt for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſatisfaction, give credit to thoſe that have been, (or at leaſt ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted) the chiefeſt, and choiceſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in it; upon this ſcore then, ſurely
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97616:77"/>we may with more than common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, truſt to, and believe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Authors, not as the meaneſt, but moſt profound, learned, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in their Art; and conſequently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly conclude, that That moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and as much hidden as famous, and neceſſary Menſtrual, or diſſolving Metalline <hi>Mercury</hi> of Philoſophers, (for, I mean not their <hi>congeling Mercury</hi>) is to be prepared out of the <hi>common Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> or <hi>Quick-ſilver.</hi> I pretend not my ſelf a Maſter in theſe things, I only give my Conceptions, and my Authority, or Ground for them, and ſo will not ingage my ſelf in the leaſt, as to a diſcovery of the preparation (whatever my Thoughts, or Experience may warrant me to do) either of the <hi>vulgar Mercury,</hi> as to the <hi>Univerſal,</hi> or of the <hi>Mercury of Bodies,</hi> with the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> to the particular; but I ſuppoſe, firſt method of the Antient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. In the preparation, if we may credit <hi>D' Eſpagnet, Herculeus libor operanti incumbit;</hi> Nor indeed doth it require leſs skill than pains, nor a meditation inferior
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97616:77"/>to either, for indeed theſe things call for an immenſe Meditation, and invincible Patience, as well as an Herculean labour, eſpecially to the inexpert, and ſeeking Artiſt: But not to be too tedious, for I have much exceeded my firſt intentions, which allowed not the giving my Thoughts in ſo plain a Diſcourſe as I have.</p>
               <p>What I have done, I dare preſume will ſave the Ingenious (not too Incredulous) no ſmall time, coſt, and labour, which haply he might in vain ſpend about Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous matters, beſides that perplexity, and vexation of Spirit, which moſt, with very little of ſatisfaction, do undergo in the ſearch of it.</p>
               <p>But to be yet a little more charitable, by a freeneſs in delivering of my Opinion and Thoughts to the more diligent Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors after real Knowledge in this Art. I will yet give them the Admonitions of the moſt Knowing in it, together with my own Conceptions (and indeed my Experience from ſome often repeated Experiments) on them; and this to diſſuade them from a fruitleſs expence, both of time, coſt,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97616:78"/>and labour, in the diſſolution of Metals, for the preparation of any noble Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, by Corroſives, Salts, or Saline li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors; of which, how high an eſteem ſoever ſome may have, I dare preſume, their future Experience, will, with their loſs, reduce them to my Opinion, and a Grateful acknowledgment of the honeſty of Philoſophers, in diſſuading them from that Deſtructive deceptory, and Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way. Firſt therefore, let us hear <hi>R. L. Qui cum aquis fortibus diſſolvunt, ignorant vegetabilia</hi> (viz. <hi>ſalia eorum</hi>) <hi>menſtruum nostrum</hi> (<hi>Vegetabile</hi> viz. <hi>aut Minerale</hi>) <hi>acuentia; ignorant etiam aquam Mercurii vulgi quam nos ſcripſimus in Testamento noſtro; diſſolutio enim quae cum aquis for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus fit, Non eſt ſicut Natura poſtulat; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; argentum diſſolvuntur cum rebus radicalibus ſui proprii generis, Non autem cum aquis fortibus quae corrumpunt potiùs, quoniam illae aquae repugnant Naturae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hear to ſecond it, <hi>Arnoldus,</hi> that plain and honeſt Maſter of the ſubtile <hi>R. Lully; Aquae ſolutionis ex ſalibus, Aluminibus, &amp; id genus aliis confectae, quae cum metallis
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97616:78"/>nullam cognationem habent, ſpecies metallorum non conſervant, at è contra destruunt &amp; diſſipant; His aquis contraria est aqua Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophorum, quae metalla conſervat, ſubti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liora reddit, deinde diſſolvit, &amp; magno con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu naturae ea in primam materiam trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have now the advice and caution of two of the moſt eminent Maſters in Phyſick, and Philoſophy, that precedent Ages have produced, ſeriouſly admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not to endeavour a ſolution of Metals into their firſt Matter, by corroſive and ſaline Spirits: What then is to be done, or what is the means and way to diſſolve Metals, and Minerals, radically to a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical uſe. Certainly, no other than, <hi>cum rebus Radicalibus,</hi> as <hi>R. L.</hi> tells us, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by their true Specificate <hi>humidum Radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cale,</hi> or firſt Matter, which (whatever ſome may imagine to the contrary) is no other than <hi>common Quick-ſilver,</hi> or <hi>vulgar Mercury.</hi> He that will, hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, without my regret, to ſlight what I here freely offer; I value it not, I have already my reward, and command, for
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97616:79"/>this my good will, and ſeek it not from him, or any other: I deny not, but ſome Corroſive (or Corroſives, in ſome ſence) may be helpful to the Phyſician, or Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, towards the diſſolution of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and Minerals, to their Phyſical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents: And this <hi>R. Lully</hi> tells us, <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis aliquantulum repugnat Naturae diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere per ignem contra naturam, tamen ſiquis noverit iterum confortare per ignem Naturae, opus complebit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To imprint yet the moſt neceſſary Uſe and Virtue of vulgar Mercury prepared, in the Artiſt's good liking and opinion, and this for his own, not my advantage; I deſire him to hear yet this following ſhort ſentence of the expert, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Avicen. Argentum vivum, dum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum fuerit, habet quaedam opera; cum Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum, alia quaedam; cum autem diſſolutum fuerit, habet opera maxima. Sapientes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt ipſum ſpectare ignem, &amp; tunc facit opera mirabilia, &amp; tranſmutationes, quia ſicut mutatur, mutat, &amp; ſicut tingitur, tingit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> or <hi>Argent vivum,</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97616:79"/>he) <hi>while it is in its running form, or vive Nature, hath one kind of Operation; when mortified, other Operations; but when diſſolved, it performs the highest, and greatest of all.</hi> (And this <hi>R. Lully</hi> alſo affirms, <hi>in Mercurio diſſoluto abſconditur magnum Secretum.</hi>) <hi>Wiſe men know how to make it abide the Fire, and then it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms Wonders: For, as it is changed, it changeth, and as it is tinged, it tingeth;</hi> That is, as it is impregnated, or anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, either with Gold, or Silver, <hi>(viz.)</hi> either of the Luminaries, to a Phyſical uſe; ſo doth it not only receive, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically unlock, or open their Bodies, but is the <hi>Vehiculum</hi> that transfers their Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues to us in a Medicinal way; and this for the preſervation of Health, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of our infirm and decaying Conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>Though I have thus fully, (and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) becauſe warranted by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the moſt Eminent, and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced of the Philoſophers, (and poſſibly by ſomewhat of Experience) aſſerted the Verity of <hi>vulgar Mercury,</hi> or <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:97616:80"/>being the true Subject, out of which their Mineral Philoſophick Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, or Menſtruum, is to be had, and prepared; yet am I not ignorant, but well know, that ſome of them, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially <hi>R. Lully,</hi> doth in moſt of his Writings point at, and direct us to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more excellent, and noble Phyſical, or Philoſophical Menſtruum, which he ſometimes calls his <hi>Aqua Caelica,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his <hi>Menstruum Circulatum,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his <hi>Menstruum Caelicum,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his <hi>Menstruum Vegetabile,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by one name, and ſometimes by another, by which, all the Metals may be radically reduced into their <hi>firſt Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Cum conſervatione formae Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivae,</hi> and without which, the common, or vulgar Mercury is not eaſily to be prepared, and made their Philoſophick Mercury, or <hi>Aqua glorioſa,</hi> as <hi>R. Lully</hi> hath before called it.</p>
               <p>Nor doth here end the bounds, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of their <hi>Mercuries,</hi> not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to one, or two; for, they have had ſeveral, (beſides the <hi>Univerſal</hi>) as the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97616:80"/>
                  <hi>Mineral, Vegetable,</hi> and <hi>Animal Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury;</hi> ſometimes both joyned in one, I mean the <hi>Mineral,</hi> and <hi>Vegetable,</hi> which produced that potent diſſolvent, or G. <hi>Vegetabile</hi> of <hi>Raymund Lully,</hi> which few yet have well underſtood, or perceived; of this, hear the profound <hi>Raymund</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Et potest altum ingenium miſcere modos Mineralium &amp; Vegetabilium &amp; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Medicinas breviore via componere;</hi> an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and acute Genius, may, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixtion of the Mercuries, much ſhorten the Works in production of Medicines, &amp;c. But of theſe laſt <hi>Mercuries,</hi> or <hi>Menstruums,</hi> I intend not at preſent to inlarge, they being the Gate into the greateſt of Chymical ſecrets; Let it ſuffice the Ingenious, that I have here given him a Manuduction to the Fountain where I now leave him to draw, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh himſelf with the Healing, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical waters, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I once more requeſt the Ingenious, not to interpret any thing, either of my own Conceptions, or Inſtructions, or the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities of Philoſophers produced by
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97616:81"/>me, to be by me underſtood, to ſpeak ſuch a thing, as now, even the Thoughts of the Vulgar are much buſied about, but little underſtand, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the great <hi>Elixir;</hi> What I mind, is only Phyſical, and in relation to a Medicinal uſe, for infirm and languiſhing Nature, which I firmly believe, was the intent, and only chief intent, of the Antient Philoſophers, and not the Tranſmutation, (or more properly) as indeed it is, the Maturation of imperfect Metals, and Minerals, into Gold, and Silver.</p>
               <p>We now daily ſee the great benefit that is received from Metals, and crude Minerals, in a Phyſical way, though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed very little, if any thing more than externally altered from their Mineral, and Metallick form, and eſpecially from thoſe of a <hi>Solar,</hi> and <hi>Lunar</hi> Nature, as <hi>Gold, Silver, Mercury, Antimony,</hi> &amp;c. Which, even by thoſe crude and ruſtick (for I cannot well call them Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical) preparations, do ſhew, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert their wonderful power, and virtue, (and that moſt ſafely being rightly and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97616:81"/>diſcreetly adminiſtred) in a Medicinal way. What then would they not do, if more Curious Artiſts did Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, and prudently prepare, open, and exalt them by ſuch preparations (as certainly they may, or can) to a height of Purity, and Virtue, a thouſand times beyond what thoſe trivial and weak pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations do give them. And if Crude Mercury may ſafely be adminiſtred, and alſo to good effect, and ſomewhat pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared yet, to a better effect; and if Gold in its firm and ſolid body, as the <hi>Galenists</hi> tell us, only boiled in broth, be ſo reſtaurative and comfortable; what may not theſe and the like Metalline, and Mineral ſubjects be exalted, raiſed, and advanced to, for Phyſick, by a true Philoſophick knowing Artiſt? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they muſt needs be (and I think I may with confidence affirm, that they will then be) the true <hi>Aurum &amp; Argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Medicum</hi> of Philoſophers, and Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, or the true <hi>Potabile,</hi> or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Medicine ſought by many, but found by few.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:97616:82"/>
               <p>I have now ſaid all I yet will, and (as I ſaid before) much more than I at firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. It is very plain, and indeed too plain, if I did not know that a Providence attends the Actions of all, and that it ſhall be for their good, and light only, that are <hi>Astrales diſcipuli,</hi> and whome God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends (and hath fitted) for it; to whoſe alſeeing Providence, guidance, and tuition I commend it, and under that ſeal do leave and bequeath it, to thoſe prepared for it, and a fundamental inſpection into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of Nature. Let none imagine I know more than I have here delivered, and ſo attempt in vain (by ſubtility of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) a farther diſcovery from me, I aim not at great matters; to know God, and the Natures of the Creatures, is all I ſeek, and all I deſire in this World. My inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and higheſt ambition in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a diſcovery of Natures ſecrets by Chymical Operations, is only Phyſical, and more I will never pretend to, nor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, what ever I may be bleſſed with. Let none therefore expect that from me that I own not my ſelf Maſter of; he
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97616:82"/>that doth, and fails of his expectations, let him not hereafter blame me, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. I wiſh happineſs unto all, but more particular unto the induſtrious, and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and while I live, will not be wanting in ſome meaſure by my mean abilities, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and acquired experience, faithfully to admoniſh, and further them, in their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious ſearch and inquiry, into Nature's Medicamental and Magical ſecrets, and her ample (and indeed) infinite trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and this to render our lives both happy and healthful, till God call for our Souls.</p>
               <p>I court not any for their good Opinion of me, or what I have done; If any traduce me as immethodical, I am not diſpleaſed with his Cenſure: Such a one throughly knows not either me, or my intent; by this diſcourſe I ſhall pleaſe thoſe I intend it for; for others, as I leave to their humour, ſo I deſire them freely to allow me my Liberty. <hi>Velle Suum cuique eſt, nec voto Scribitur uno.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:97616:83"/>
               <head>An Expoſtulatory Concluſion to my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Countrymen, in behalf of Chymiſtry and Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Medicines.</head>
               <p>WHen I conſider how great an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition truth and knowledge do yet find, and that even from thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves the only and greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancers of her Ends, and Intereſt, I am no leſs amazed at their unworthineſs than at the dullneſs, ſtupidity, and folly of others, that ſuffer themſelves, like Children, to be cheated with Pebbles, inſtead of Pearls. I freely and from my heart proteſt, I have not any thing of prejudice, or envy towards the Perſons of any; what I now do, or hereafter (poſſibly) may do, is only out of an innate Zeal I have to truth, and real knowlege: That which we Cordially fancy, we are all of us apt to defend, and ſpeak well of; for my own part, I do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things under the Sun highly and truely eſteem and value knowledge; nor
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:97616:83"/>have I ſpared either time, pains, or means (according to my ability) to improve thoſe ſmall Talents beſtowed upon me by Almighty God. Nor ſhall I, as long as God ſhall pleaſe to continue me amongſt the living, think any thing in this world comparable unto it; it hath been, is, and I hope always ſhall be (with King <hi>Solomon</hi>) the ſumm of my petition unto my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that he would vouchafe me Wiſdom, and a knowing Heart, and with the wiſe <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> in his <hi>Pimander, Deum cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere rerumque cauſas;</hi> To know God and the cauſes of things. To know God (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept by immediate inſpiration of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit) I know not, nor have the wiſe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto found, any better way or <hi>Medium,</hi> than by a diligent ſearch into Nature, that ſo <hi>per viſibilia inviſibilia,</hi> by the work, the workman might in ſome meaſure be known unto us: Or the great Creator, by the many ſmall Creations ſet before us. If this be true, and Knowledg the only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable Jewel for us, to ſeek and ſearch after, I hope none can blame me for my good intents, nor think other ways of my
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97616:84"/>oppoſits than <hi>Scientiae inimicos; &amp; Scientia non habet inimicos niſi ignorantes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile ſimili facile jungitur, Natura Natura laetatur &amp; gaudet, &amp; contrarium ſuum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarium non minus facile oppugnat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for Chymiſtry, in whoſe defence (without envy unto any) I purpoſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend theſe few lines, it hath been, and ſtill is moſt deſervedly eſteemed by the Wiſe, the moſt excellent of Arts, and Queen of Sciences, and hath therefore been ſtill kept ſecret amongſt them, and ſuch Papers, or Manuſcripts, as treated of it, or the excellency of it, ſtill delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from one to another as their chiefeſt Teſtimonies of favour and friendſhip, and accordingly with greateſt care pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved amongſt their choiceſt Jewels, and this becauſe it was the only Gate that led us into the greateſt of Natures moſt admirable ſecrets, and unvaluable Treaſures, and that not only in relation to external accommodations, and the large benefits which might many ways be attained unto (as daily experience doth now teſtifie unto us) but alſo for
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:97616:84"/>that it gave us the means to prepare us ſuch moſt wholſome, ſafe, and effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Medicines as, by their quick, ſafe, and pleaſant curing both external, and internal maladies, and diſtempers, might render our lives much more happy than otherwiſe they could poſſibly be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them. Innumerable, certainly, are the benefits we receive, and ſtill ſhall receive, by Chymiſtry, and Chymical preparations; for, taken in its true ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine definition and intention, it is no other than an Art that doth both teach and inable us (for our exceeding good and benefit) to ſeparate Purity from Impurity, exalt, and advance what God and Nature hath given us, to a farther and higher perfection than we receive it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with; in which ſence, if we ſhall well and truly conſider it, what have we in this curious, and nice Age, either for Back, or Belly, Pleaſure, or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, that hath not in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure been obliged to <hi>Chymistry,</hi> and its beneficial Operations, for that perfection we receive it in? What calling may
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97616:85"/>be ſaid to have attained to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and height it now glories in, without her help in ſome one or other of her (more ſublime, or trivial) Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? Conſider our daily Viands, Conſider our Bread, our Beer, our Wine, our ſweet Confections; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der even what you will that can any way render our lives happy or ſatisfact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory; conſider it ſeriouſly, and you will find it in one degree or other to have paſſed under the hand of <hi>Chymistry,</hi> and her various Operations or Preparations. Can we then be thus inſenſibly led to admit of her daily help and aſſiſtance in things of ſmalleſt value, and can we be ſo ſtupid, dull, ignorant, and blind, as to neglect her aſſiſtance in things of greater moment, and the greateſt of Concerns? And not only neglect her advice, but deny her friendly, and moſt profitable hand in thoſe things which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all other (our reaſon will tell us) we moſt need her help in? Nay, we do not only deny her to make us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, but we ſeek by all means poſſible
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:97616:85"/>to diſgrace, ſlander, and make her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, nay, odious to the whole World. Doubtleſs, in theſe our Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, (for I cannot call them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways) we declare our ſelves, either very Ignorant, (which we all ſhun, and hate to be eſteemed) or elſe very Self-ended, and Malitious. Can we, with Alacrity, and the greateſt of Content, admit, and allow her favours, (nay, greedily ſeek after them) to improve, and maintain our Purſes, and Pleaſures? and cannot we admit, and embrace her help for the preſervation of our Health, without which, the other will be of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle benefit, and leſs pleaſure? As for my ſelf, I am reſolved to follow the Dictates of Reaſon, that only and ſure Ballance, given Us by Almighty God, to weigh what may be moſt for our preſent, and future good: <hi>Et Ratio ſat luminis habet &amp; ipſa Lumen est, quo res omnes ut ſe habent percipere poſſumus.</hi> Faber, cap. 33. Panchim. lib. 2. Nor will I in the leaſt oppoſe her ſacred Admonitions; I own her as my Miſtriſs,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97616:86"/>and will accordingly ſtand for her, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micus Galenus, Amicus Hippocrates, at magis amica Ratio, veritas, et ſapientia;</hi> I acknowledg the few favours we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from <hi>Galen,</hi> and the little good we reap by <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> but yet will not deny Verity, or forſake Wiſdome in favour of either. I acknowledg, we are obliged to their Labours, for the Knowledge left unto us by them, but think not my Self, or any other, at all ingaged there to ſet up our Reſt, and <hi>Herculean</hi> ſtops, or a <hi>non ultra,</hi> to all farther inquiſition and ſearch after Knowledg. God is ſtill the ſame, and hath infinity of Knowledg yet to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon Man in his own good time of Providence, and Diſpenfation, and therefore not to be bounded, or confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the narrow Pages of a London <hi>Galenical,</hi> or any other, <hi>Pharmacopaea;</hi> and this we daily are, or may be, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of: Therefore, whereas I in ſome meaſure honour <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> and have alſo a due eſteem for thoſe that profeſs themſelves their
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:97616:86"/>followers, and truly more ſhould have, were they not ſo ſtrong Aſſertors of their failing Doctrines; yet cannot I think thoſe of them Unblameable, who ſo Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, and Obſtinately oppoſe Truth, and a farther manifeſtation of VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Why ſhould we not as readily admit, nay, with all our power incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage an improvement in the Science of Phyſick, or Medicine, as in all other Mundane affairs? If to render our Lives happy, in the time of Nature's greateſt Vigour, we muſt not only admit, but ſtudiouſly endeavour all ſuch ways as may continue and promote our Health; Why may we not with as great (if not greater) care and reaſon, do the ſame in the time of her impaired For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, debilitation, and fear of her utter loſs? If our uſual Food be rendred by ſeveral Chymical, or preparing means, much pleaſanter for our Pallats, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for our Stomach's Digeſtion, where Nature and her <hi>Archeus</hi> are yet power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; Can we in the leaſt queſtion, but Phyſick may alſo be rendred much more
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:97616:87"/>ſafe, delightful, and proper for her, (by the ſame means) when ſhe moſt needs out aſſiſtance, and utmoſt help? And if Nature by ſome decay be weakned, and oppreſſed, that ſhe cannot accept of her uſual and accuſtomed Food, ſo as ſhe would, and ought to diſpoſe of it for the ſupply of her Spirits, and the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of her Habitation; If ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, (I ſay) here in her ordinary courſe, ſo play the Chymiſt, as uſual; Doubtleſs, ſhe is leſs able to do it, in that which the very Name, as well as the Nature of it, makes her utterly to abhor, and reject; and, if ſhe be not ſtrong enough to ſeperate the Quint-eſſence of her daily and accuſtomed Food, how ſhall ſhe extract any thing from her Phyſick, that may give that relief her preſent Condition requires, and calls for? She hath here a double task to perform, firſt to extract her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and then to make uſe of it. It would doubtleſs, therefore, in this caſe, be far better, to ſave her that labour of ſeparation in this her weakned Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:97616:87"/>for, of neceſſity, either the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, or Nature, muſt officiate, or act, as Chymiſt, before Nature can have, or receive, what ſhe calls for, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires for her help, and aſſiſtance. Who therefore, not Drowned in Ignorance, or Drunk with Malice, and Envy, would ſo ſtrongly oppoſe ſo great a Good, as <hi>Chymistry</hi> is the Author (and ſole Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) of? How lothſome is even the very name of Phyſick unto debilitated Nature! and what is the reaſon? Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the hard task ſhe hath put upon her by it, and even when ſhe is leaſt able to perform it, and hath more need of ſuccour, than of a farther trouble. How ſhall ſhe receive ſo great a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of lothſome Medicines, being weak, when, even in the greateſt of her Strength ſhe would loath (not only) to take (but alſo be troubled at the ſight of) it! and this from a ſecret Senſe and Antipathy, her <hi>Archeus</hi> hath againſt its nauſeating and foeculential Quality, as well as the greatneſs of its Quantity. What remedy is then to be uſed? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:97616:88"/>no other or better can any way be found out or propounded, than to fit and prepare thoſe Subjects we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for her relief, and that, by ſuch means, and ways, as may make them fit for her weakeſt of Conditions, and they can no way elſe be ſo fitted, as by <hi>Chymistry,</hi> and its (Spagirical) O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, which ſeperates all Impurity, from the pure and Medicinal part, and ſo renders it apt and fit for Nature's more eaſie Reception; and the end ſhe requires it for. Why then ſhould any ſo Obſtinately oppoſe ſo clear a truth, as the Excellency of <hi>Chymistry,</hi> in the preparation of Medicines, if compared with the other moſt rotten, and ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual foundation of Phyſick? Or why do the <hi>Galenists</hi> cry out againſt us in things they underſtand not? Or, if they will ſay, they underſtand them to be ſuch, as they inceſſantly rail at them to be, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Dangerous, Poyſonous, and no way fit to be adminiſtred; Why do they make any uſe of them? Why do they ſteal our <hi>Extractum Rudii, (alias,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:97616:88"/>Extract Catholicum Paracelſi?)</hi> VVhy our <hi>Laudanum? Pilula Alaephang?</hi> Why have they any thing to do with our <hi>Oleum Vitrioli, Oleum ſalis Communis, Oleum Sulphuris per campanam, Mercurius Vitae, Infuſio Croci Metallorum, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, ſublim. Dulcis, Mercurius praecip. Dulcis?</hi> Why our Chymical Diſtilled Oyls, as Oyls of Spices, Oyls of Woods, Oyls of Seeds? Why adminiſter they, or preſcribe they any of our ſimple, or compound Diſtilled Waters? Shew me any of theſe Oyls in <hi>Galen,</hi> or any of thoſe Cordial Spirits in <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> Why do they Rail at us, and yet make uſe of our Medicines, as the beſt and moſt effectual they have? and can they thus make uſe of our worſt of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and yet enviouſly ſlander the beſt? Certainly, it ſavours of much Malice, and more Folly. But to give Limits to this my juſt Zeal, for Truth, and a publick Good, I ſhall give my Country-men (yet Ignorant of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of <hi>Chymistry,</hi> and Chymical Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines) ſome ſmall and brief account
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:97616:89"/>of <hi>Chymistry,</hi> in its Genuine, and true Sence; and ſome Reaſons for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Chymical Medicines, above thoſe we uſually tearm <hi>Galenical,</hi> and then leave both the one, and the other, to their better conſideration. <hi>Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry,</hi> that moſt noble of Sciences, and beneficial of all Arts, is not (as yet falſly by many ſuppoſed) a Tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Operation only about Metals, but it is an Art invented, and adorned, by the continual Meditations and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of the moſt Wiſe and Prudent of Men, and ſuch a one as teacheth us to improve, and make uſe of, as well Animals, and Vegetables, as Minerals, and Metals, both to Phyſical, and all other neceſſary Uſes, though at firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed intended more properly to Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and a Medicinal uſe. The word is a Greek word, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, its Derivation or Compoſition from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>id est, (quaſi) Salem fundere,</hi> to melt Salt, or a fuſion of Salt, or which was, and is more properly the true Sence of it, and intent of Chymiſtry
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:97616:89"/>in it, as to Phyſick, to prepare Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine ſo, as to bring it to the nature, and form, of a fixed, and fuſible Salt, <hi>Quo habito (ſive ex Animalibus, Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilibus, aut Mineralibus) Laudandus ſit Deus:</hi> and ſo indeed ought all Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine to be, before it can be ſaid to be perfect Medicine. Now ſeparation, as well as ſeveral other Operations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt neceſſary for the Completion of this ultimate intent, and perfection: The Art was alſo by the Wiſe called <hi>Ars Spagirica,</hi> that is, <hi>Ars Separatoria,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Separo,</hi> becauſe Purification, which muſt of neceſſity alſo precede the ultimate intent of this Art, could not be performed without due, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten repeated ſeparation. See now in two or three words, the true and full in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ſcope, and deſign of Chymiſtry, that moſt excellent (and therefore moſt unworthily deſpiſed) Science. I ſhall not therefore be tedious, I ſhall now give only a ſmall Light, as to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Chymical Medicines, (above all others) if rightly prepared, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:97616:90"/>commend them to my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, as the moſt ſafe, moſt pleaſant, and moſt effectual, and which is alſo no ſmall argument for their welcom, (all things conſidered) the moſt cheap of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</p>
               <p>Chymical Medicines are, of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, being rightly prepared, the moſt noble, and excellent, and this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as well by Reaſon, as daily Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; the later is now ſo common, I need not ſay more of it: As for Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, take theſe few following, Let us conſider, what it is that gives eminency, and perfection, to any one thing we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem as excellent, we ſhall find that it is the purity of it, and that, either in the Animal, Vegetable, or Mineral Nature; if we conſider then, what we are now ſpeaking of, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Medicine, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Chymical preparations, we muſt alſo conclude its efficacy, and excellency, to proceed from its purity, or purified Nature. Let us yet farther conſider what it is for; it is to help, and reſtore decayed Nature, and her languiſhing <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus.</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:97616:90"/>What is this Nature, and her <hi>Archeus?</hi> It is the moſt ſubtile, and pure Spirit of Man, or Woman, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no way to be aſſiſted, but by that which is of purity, and likeneſs with it, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Medicines of a pure, ſubtile, and penetrating Nature. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Nature will tell you, what her Medicines ought to be; and a true conſideration of ſuch Medicines, will teach, and tell you, what Nature is, ſo that the quality of the one, will inform you what the Nature, and Eſſence of the other ought to be; a ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then of Nature, will tell you the quality of the Medicines you ought to uſe for her relief, and aſſiſtance, which is, that they be of moſt ſubtile and thin parts. This made <hi>Hippocrates</hi> tell us, that the excellency of Medicine conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in its ſubtility, and thinneſs, by which it was the more able to protect, and aſſiſt, decayed Nature in her diſturbed Condition; and though amongſt many things, (or <hi>Species</hi>) ſome may be ſaid to be of more thin, and ſubtile parts,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:97616:91"/>in reſpect of ſome others; yet the moſt thin, and ſubtile, as Nature produceth them, come extremely ſhort of that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility, which this Art, by its purging preparations, can raiſe even the moſt dull, and groſs of Specificks to: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in then is the excellency of Chymical Medicines, above Galenical, Chymiſtry being able to exalt the moſt dull, and inactive of Medicines, to the greateſt of ſubtility, and far beyond what Nature preſents them to us in. Nor doth ſhe thus exalt their purity, and efficacy, as to the Cure of all, both inward, and outward Diſtempers, but renders them (may I ſo ſay) in a manner Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, that is, Incorruptible; Which, the beſt of <hi>Galenical</hi> Medicines, cannot in the leaſt boaſt of, few, or none of them being able to continue one poor Year, without ſome notable (if not a total) expiration of their Virtue. How then ſhould theſe poor, dirty, and droſſie Medicines, anſwer thoſe great Ends we adminiſter them for? How ſhall they root out inveterate, fixed, and chronick
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:97616:91"/>Diſeaſes? How ſhall they purifie the Impure, or help the Infirm, who are not yet Cured of their own Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Infirm condition? If it ſhall be, as uſually it is, unadviſedly, and very inconſiderately Objected, that their Medicines are ſafe, and that ours, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quickly Cure, or quickly Kill; Let me tell them, they in this very Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, grant much more than they are aware of, for nothing can quickly Cure, but what is really Efficacious, and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſo great a good, which, nothing can be, that is not in ſome meaſure pure, and like unto the Nature it ſhall ſo aſſiſt; Herein then, inconſultly do they affirm, the excellency of our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines. If they ſay then, they as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly Kill, I muſt return them this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that it is, when adminiſtred by their hands that know them not. <hi>Ex quovis ligno non fit Mercurius, Galeniſts</hi> are not fit to uſe <hi>Paracelſian</hi> Medicines, (until they have entred the Chymical Schools, and Laboratories) which, by reaſon of their excellency, ſubtile, and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:97616:92"/>enlivening Faculty, are not to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by Quarts, or Pints, but by Drops in proper Vehicles; not by Pugils, or Ounces, but by Grains, half Drachms, or Drachms, (at moſt) being to help Nature, not ſtuff up the Body, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready too much Obſtructed) and ſo hinder, rather than farther her Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. However, knowing ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the dulneſs, and inefficacy of their own Medicines, they muſt ſtill be nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at ours, and yet revile them, when they have anſwered their deſires; and, if at any time they are too Keen for their Skill, and Knowledge, they are then moſt Damnable, and preſently to be Curſed with <hi>Bell, Book, and Candle,</hi> and not one of them to be left in their <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenical Antidotaries.</hi> I would, they would turn them quite out, or elſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them, (as indeed they are) the beſt Flowers in their Garden; Let them not uſe ours, and we will faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully promiſe them never to make uſe of theirs. Ours decay not by length of time, theirs putrifie, and corrupt,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:97616:92"/>even in a Years time; Ours ſafely, pleaſantly, and quickly Cure, theirs do rather hinder, than farther Nature in her own Operation, and can only, when Nature hath Cured her ſelf, rob her of the praiſe and glory of a Cure, which ſhe her ſelf hath performed: But I hope the time is now coming, when Ingenuity ſhall flouriſh, ſeeing many of thoſe that not long ſince op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed this ſo noble a Science, do now at laſt begin to appear its real Friends, Defenders, and Propagators; and when declaredly ſuch, I ſhall wiſh them their utmoſt due, with a continued remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their Names unto ſucceeding Generations, as the worthy Promoters of ſo publick and great a Good.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:97616:93"/>
            <head>A POSCRIPT To the Ingenious and Phyſically Studious READER.</head>
            <p>I Intend alſo (how ſoon I cannot yet ſay) to preſent unto the Ingenious, Induſtrious, and Knowledge-Seeking-Engliſh, whoſe ſullen Fate, ſlender and mean Education affords them only the benefit of what is publiſhed in their own Mother-tongue, a ſmall, but very plain,
<pb n="941" facs="tcp:97616:93"/>and Methodical Treatiſe in Engliſh, as the (ſmaller <hi>Radii,</hi> glimmering Beams, or) <hi>Aurora,</hi> to a greater approaching Light, teaching a Spagirical (or Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical) preparation of Animals, Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, Minerals, and Metals, to a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical uſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Separation of their Quinteſſential, Medicinal, Fix'd, and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile parts; the Purification, Reunition, or Conjunction, and Coction of the ſaid parts, into moſt noble, efficacious, and powerful Medicines, <hi>Arcanaes,</hi> and <hi>Phyſical Elixirs,</hi> and this in a higher, or lower degree, according to the Subtile Genius, Induſtry, and Prudence of the Artiſt; Moſt uſeful, and beneficial for the Preſervation of the preſent, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, or Recovery, of the decayed, or loſt Health of Man. The improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and farther conſideration, may (haply) prove a Gate to other Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets; Yet, if any One, in the mean time, either diligently Studious of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or otherways curious in the ſearch of the ſecrets of Nature, and Art, be deſirous to be inſtructed in the Grounds
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:97616:94"/>of <hi>Chymistry,</hi> or the <hi>Spagirick Art,</hi> and ſhall in a reaſonable and modeſt way requeſt my inſtruction, and aſſiſtance in it, I do hereby promiſe him a faithful Manuduction, and Introduction, and that by plain Demonſtration, and Practice, to the true and full grounds, intent, and ſcope of <hi>Chymistry,</hi> and this either as to Phyſical preparations, or other Nature-ſearching, delightful, and pleaſant Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; <hi>Chymistry</hi> being the moſt noble, and tranſcendent of Arts, and, by which only, and not otherways, and this in a more ſublime, or mean degree, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Acute Ingeny, Patience, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and Neatneſs of the Operator, whether in Medicinal preparations, or other choice <hi>Arcanaes,</hi> may ſomething of excellency be expected, and produced, and perhaps the wiſhed perfection, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt aim and end of our deſires (at laſt) be obtained. My earneſt deſire of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing, improving, and promoting (more for a general Good, than my own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Benefit) this ſo noble a Science, and opening a Gate for entrance into the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:97616:94"/>infinite Treaſures of Nature, both for Health, and other Happineſs, cloſely ſhut up and contained in the Creature, is the chief inducement to this Additional proffer, and the publick Notice of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>E. Bolneſt,</hi> Med. <hi>Lond.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Jewen-ſtreet, <hi>near</hi> Cripplegate, <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:95"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97616:95"/>
            <head>Books Printed at the <hi>Theater</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Sold by <hi>Peter Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> at the <hi>Leg</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> viz.</head>
            <p>A Fair Printed Bible, with Biſhop <hi>Uſhers</hi> Chronology, with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer and Apocripha, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them: in <hi>4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The third part of the Bible, <hi>viz. Job, Pſalms, Proverbs, Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> and <hi>Canticles,</hi> of a fair Print; to which may be added the Common-Prayer, New Teſtament and Singing-Pſalms, in Octavo.</item>
               <item>2. An <hi>Engliſh</hi> New Teſtament, with a Fair large Print, for weak eyes, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Another Teſtament, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. Another Teſtament in Twelves, of a fair Print for Children to learn by.</item>
               <item>5. A very curious Church Bible, with the Chronologie of a fair large Print, in Foiio.</item>
               <item>6. A Latin Teſtament of a fair Print in Twelves, for the uſe of Schools.</item>
               <item>7. Senecae Tragaediae, in Twelves,</item>
               <item>8. Elegantiae Poeticae, in Twelves.</item>
               <item>9. Cornelius Nepos, in Twelves.</item>
               <item>10. Juſtini Hiſtorici, in Twelves</item>
               <item>11. Homeri Illias notis Didymi, in Octavo.</item>
               <item>12. Plinii Epiſtolae, in Octavo.</item>
               <item>13. Quintiliani Declamationes, in Octavo.</item>
               <item>14. Theocritus in Greek, in Octavo.</item>
               <item>15. Maximus Tyrius, in Twelves.</item>
               <item>16. A Greek Teſtament with Curcelleus's and others Notes, in Twelves.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:96"/>
               <item>17. Saluſtius cum notis, in Twelves.</item>
            </list>
            <p>There is now in the Preſs at the Theater, a large Quarto Bible of a fairer Character than ever yet was extant, with Chronological Notes and other uſeful tables.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Books of Divinity Printed at <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The <hi>Key of the Bible,</hi> unlocking the richeſt Treaſury of the Holy Scriptures; whereby the Order, Names, Times, Penmen, Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Scope, and principal Parts; containing the Subject matter of the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, are familiarly and briefly opened, for the help of the weakeſt capacity in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the whole Bible: A Book ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly uſeful for private Families. By <hi>Francis Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> D. D. <hi>Rector</hi> of <hi>Wrington</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire, in Folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nineteen Sermons, being the firſt Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Eſſay of the Pious Labours of that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Orthodox, and indefatigable Preacher of the Goſpel Mr. <hi>Joſiah Shute,</hi> Publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Edward Spark,</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sions proſpect in its firſt View,</hi> preſented in a Summary of Divine Truths, conſenting with the Faith profeſſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed from Scripture and Reaſon, illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Inſtance and Alluſion: Compoſed and Publiſhed to be an help for the prevention of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> Conviction of <hi>Hereſie,</hi> Confutation of <hi>Error,</hi> and Eſtabliſhing in the <hi>Truth.</hi> By <hi>Robert Moſſom Dr.</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> in <hi>4to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Index Biblicus,</hi> or an exact Concordance to
<pb facs="tcp:97616:96"/>the holy Bible according to the laſt tranſlation, whereunto are added the marginal readings, with the acceptations, and various ſignifications, of the principal words contained in the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in a new and moſt comprehenſive Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and adorned with divers ſignificant and and pregnant Scripture phraſes, By <hi>John Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Mulſea</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> in Quarto.</p>
               <p>The works of Mr. <hi>Richard Allen</hi> Late Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of <hi>Batcomb</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> in four parts, <hi>viz. Vindiciae Pietatis,</hi> or a Vindication of Godlineſs in the greateſt Strictnes and Spiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it, from the imputations of Folly and Fancy, together with ſeveral Directions for the Attaining and Maintaining a Godly Life, in Octavo.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Godly mans Portion and Sanctuary, in Octavo.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Heaven opened, or a brief and plain diſcovery of the Riches of Gods Covenant of Grace, in Octavo.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The World conquered, or a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers victory over the World, laid open in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Sermons, on 1 <hi>John.</hi> 5.4. in Octavo.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Pagans</hi> debt and dowry, or a brief diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion of theſe queſtions, Whether, how far, and in what ſenſe ſuch Perſons of Mankind a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom the letter of the Goſpel never came, are notwithſtanding bound to believe on Jeſus Chriſt? with ſome other particulars rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hereunto. Whereunto is added the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors opinion concerning Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, the Death of Chriſt, the Grace of God in and about Converſion, the Liberty or Power
<pb facs="tcp:97616:97"/>of the Will or of the Creature man, the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of the Saints, &amp;c. By <hi>John Goodwin</hi>-Miniſter of the Goſpel, in Octavo.</p>
               <p>A Metrical Paraphraſe upon the Four E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, being the Hiſtory of our Lord and Saviour. By <hi>Eliſha Coles.</hi> in Octavo.</p>
               <p>The beſt Acquaintance and higheſt Honour of Chriſtians, or a Diſcourſe of Acquaintance with God, upon <hi>Job</hi> 22.21. Acquaint thy ſelf with him, and be at Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Mathew Newcomen</hi> late Miniſter at <hi>Dedham,</hi> in Octavo.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Progreſs upon Earth about a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce betwixt Chriſt and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by reaſon of her Diſſoluteneſs and Exceſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to all Tender-Conſcienced Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, A freſh fancy full of Various ſtrains and ſuitable to the times. Tranſlated out of <hi>Italian</hi> into <hi>Engliſh</hi> in Octavo.</p>
               <p>Divine Meditations upon ſeveral Subjects, whereunto is annexed Gods Love and Mans Unworthineſs, with ſeveral Divine Ejaculations. By <hi>John Quarles.</hi> in Octavo.</p>
               <p>The Prayer of Prayers, Or the Lords Prayer Expounded. By <hi>Thomas Bevan.</hi> M. A. in Octavo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hiſtorical Contemplations,</hi> as alſo <hi>Scriptural</hi> and <hi>Occaſional Obſervations,</hi> together with their <hi>Divine Improvement</hi> and <hi>Applications.</hi> By <hi>Caleb Trenchfield,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Cheapſted</hi> in <hi>Surrey</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Murtherer puniſhed and pardoned, or a true Relation of the Wicked Life, and ſhameful happy Death of <hi>Thomas Savage,</hi> Impriſoned, juſtly condemned, and twice Executed at <hi>Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliff,</hi> for his bloody Fact in killing his Fellow Servant. On <hi>Wedneſday October</hi> 26. 1668. To which is annexed a Sermon preached at his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. in Octavo.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:97"/>
               <p>The Souls preparation for Chriſt, or a Treatiſe of Contrition; wherein is diſcovered how God breaks the Heart, and Wounds the Soul in the Converſion of a Sinner to Himſelf. By <hi>Thomas Hooker,</hi> Twelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Supplications of Saints,</hi> A Book of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for every day in the week, and for all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, by <hi>Thomas Sorocold,</hi> the 39th. Edition, Twelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacred Principles, or a Manual of Devotions made up of three Parts,</hi> 1. The Grounds of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, and the Doctrine <hi>of the Church of England,</hi> as differing from the now <hi>Roman,</hi> and the new <hi>Reformed</hi> ones. 2. Daily and weekly Forms of Prayers, fortified with holy Scriptures, Meditations and Rules, to keep the Soul from the common Roads of ſin, and carry it on in a mortified courſe. 3. Seven charges to Conſcience, delivering (if not the whole body,) the main limbs of Divinity, which is the Art not of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting, but living well, by <hi>Will. Brough,</hi> D. D. late Dean of <hi>Glocester,</hi> twelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The return of Prayers,</hi> A Treatiſe wherein this Caſe how to diſcern Gods anſwer to our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers is briefly reſolved, with other obſervations upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85. and the 8th. concerning Gods ſpeaking peace, by <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> D. D. twelves.</p>
               <p>Several pieces written by the Author of the <hi>Whole Duty of man,</hi> viz.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Ladies calling, in Octavo.</item>
                  <item>The Government of the Tongue, Octavo.</item>
                  <item>The Art of Contentment, Octavo.</item>
                  <item>The Chriſtians Birth-right, Octavo.</item>
                  <item>The <hi>Sinners Tears,</hi> made up of Meditations and Prayers, by <hi>T. Fettiplace.</hi> Twelves.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:98"/>
               <head>Books of Philoſophy, Phyſick, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, Mathematicks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOſaical Philoſophy,</hi> grounded on the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Truth, or Eternal Sapience writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Robert Flud,</hi> Doctor in Phyſick. In Folio.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maximes of State and Government,</hi> in divers Politick diſcourſes written in <hi>Italian</hi> by <hi>Paulo Paruta,</hi> A Noble <hi>Venetian.</hi> Engliſhed by a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of honour. Folio.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Anatomy of Melancholy,</hi> What it is, with all the Kinds, Cauſes, Symptoms, Prognoſticks and Several Cures of it, in three partitions with their ſeveral Sections, Members and Sub-ſecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Philoſophically, Medicinally, Hiſtorically opened and cut up by <hi>Robert Burton,</hi> with a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrical preface conducing to the following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. The 9th. Edition Corrected and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, Folio.</p>
               <p>An <hi>Engliſh Dictionary,</hi> Explaning the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult terms that are uſed in <hi>Divinity, Husbandry, Phyſick, Philoſophy, Law, Navigation, Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks,</hi> and other Arts and Sciences, very uſeful (for ſuch as are ignorant in the Latin and Greek Languages) for the better underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they read. By <hi>Eliſha Coles</hi> late of <hi>Magd. Col. Oxford.</hi> in Octavo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cottoni Posthuma,</hi> divers Pieces of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Antiquary, Sir <hi>Robert Cotton,</hi> Knight and Baronet. in Octavo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Manner of Raiſing, Ordering, and improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Forreſt and Fruit-Trees: alſo how to Plant, Make and Keep Woods, Walks, Avenues, Lawns,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:97616:98"/>with ſeveral <hi>Figures</hi> proper for Avenues and Walks to end in, and convenient <hi>Figures</hi> for <hi>Lawns;</hi> Alſo <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Tables</hi> ſhewing how the ingenious Planter may meaſure Superficial Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, with Rules how to divide Woods or Land, and how to meaſure Timber and other Solid Bodies, either by Arithmetick or Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, ſhewing the Uſe of that moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Line, the <hi>Line of Numbers,</hi> by ſeveral New Examples; with many other Rules uſeful for moſt Men, by <hi>M. Cook,</hi> Gardiner to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> 4to. to which is added a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of ſubterranean Treaſure, by Sir <hi>H. Platt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An Introduction into the Greek Tongue,</hi> in moſt plain manner, delivering the principal matters, of the <hi>Grammar</hi> thereof, ſo far forth as may help toward the underſtanding the Greek Text of the holy Goſpel, compoſed for their ſakes that underſtand not Latin, and yet are deſirous to have ſome competent knowledge in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Sacred Scripture. By <hi>Edmund Reeves,</hi> Dr. in Divinity, and Inſtructer in the <hi>Oriental Tongues.</hi> 4to.</p>
               <p>A Treatiſe concerning Tongues, appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to learning the <hi>Hebrew, Greek, Latin, Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dean, Syrian</hi> and <hi>Arabian Tongnes,</hi> ſhewing and in how ſhort a time a ſtudent may receive ſuch Inſtructions and Directions in any one of them, as whereby he may proceed in the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Language, uſing the books requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite thereunto, &amp;c. by <hi>Edmund Reeves.</hi> 4to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Certain Grammatical Chapters ſerving to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce into the Common Grammar,</hi> whereunto is added a brief declaration, how this and ſome other <hi>Grammatical</hi> Books are to be uſed. By <hi>Edmund Reeve.</hi> 4to.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:99"/>
               <p>The conſtruction of thoſe Rules in the <hi>Latin Grammar,</hi> which were omitted in the book called <hi>Lillies Rules</hi> and <hi>Syntaxis</hi> conſtrued, being helpful to young Scholars, alſo to others for their further progreſs in the <hi>Latin Tongue:</hi> by <hi>Edm. Reeves.</hi> 4to.</p>
               <p>Obſervations on the preſent manners of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> briefly Anatomizing the Living by the Dead, with a uſeful detection of the Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks of both Sexes. By <hi>Richard Whitlock</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of Phyſick. Octavo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Morbus Polyrhizos &amp; Polymorphaeus,</hi> a Treatiſe of the Scurvy. Examining the different opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and practices of the moſt ſolid and grave writers concerning the Nature and Cure of this Diſeaſe, by <hi>Everard Manwaring</hi> Doctor in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. Octavo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Unheard of Curioſities,</hi> concerning the <hi>Talis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manical Sculpture</hi> of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and the reading of the Stars, written in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>James Gaffarel,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>Edmund Chilmead</hi> Maſter of Arts and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain of <hi>Chriſtchurch Oxon.</hi> A Piece ſo excellent that it was thrice Printed in <hi>France,</hi> in the ſpace of ſix Months. Octavo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tachygraphy</hi> or Shortwriting, the moſt eaſie exact and ſpeedy, by <hi>Tho. Shelton.</hi> Octavo.</p>
               <p>The neweſt, plaineſt, and ſhorteſt Short-hand containing, 1. A brief Account of all the Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hands already extant, with their <hi>Alphabets and Fundamental Rules.</hi> 2. A plain and eaſie Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod for beginners, leſs burthenſom to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory than any other. 3. A new invention for contracting words, with ſpecial rules for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting Sentences, and other ingenious Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, both pleaſant and profitable unto all, let
<pb facs="tcp:97616:99"/>their Character be whoſe or what it will, by <hi>Eliſha Coles,</hi> Schoolmaſter, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Academy of Eloquence, containing a Comple at <hi>Engliſh</hi> Rhetorick exemplified, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-places and formula's digeſted into an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and Methodical way to ſpeak and write flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, according to the mode of the preſent times, with letters both Amourous and Moral upon emergent occaſions, by <hi>Thomas Blunt</hi> of the Inner-Temple Barriſter, the 4th, Edition, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Collection of the neweſt Songs, Poems, and Catches; now in Vogue both in City and Countrey.</p>
               <p>Maximes of State with inſtructions to his Son, and the Sons advice to his aged Father, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto are added obſervatious touching Trade and Commerce with the <hi>Hollander</hi> and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, proving that our Sea and Land Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities inrich and ſtrengthen other Countreys againſt our own. By Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> Knight Twelves.</p>
               <p>A Dictionary Engliſh-Latin and Latin-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh fitted for the uſe of young Scholars, by <hi>Eliſha Coles</hi> Schoolmaſter, in quarto. A Book much commended by moſt Schoolmaſters in this Nation, price 7 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Hiſtory Books, Romances, Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe Hiſtory of the Iſland of Barbadoes,</hi> illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a Map of the Iſland, as alſo the principal Trees and Plants there ſet forth in
<pb facs="tcp:97616:100"/>their due proportion and ſhapes, drawn out by their ſeveral and reſpective Scales, together with the Ingenio that makes the Sugar, with the Plots of the ſeveral Houſes, Rooms, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places that are uſed in the whole Proceſs of Sugar-making, <hi>viz.</hi> the Grinding-Room, the Boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Room, the Filling-Room the Curing-Houſe, Still-houſe and Furnaces, all deſcribed in Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-plates, by <hi>Richard Liggon, Gent.</hi> Folio.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The State of Christendom, giving a perfect and Exact account of many Political Intrigues and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret myſteries of State, practiſed in moſt of the Courts of</hi> Europe, <hi>with an account of their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Claims, Intereſts, and Pretenſions.</hi> Written by the Renowned Sir <hi>Henry Wotton</hi> Knight, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time Ambaſſadour in Ordinary to the moſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene <hi>Republick of Venice,</hi> Folio.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> the fam'd Romance, the whole work in five parts, written Originally in <hi>French,</hi> and now Elegantly rendred into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by Sir <hi>Charles Cotterel</hi> maſter of the <hi>Ceremonies</hi> to his late Majeſty, and dedicated to our preſent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, Folio.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hymens Praeludia</hi> or loves Maſter-piece, being that ſo much admired Romance intituled <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra</hi> written in <hi>French,</hi> now rendred into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> by <hi>Robert Loveday,</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irragguagli di Parnaſſo,</hi> or <hi>advertiſements from Parnaſſus,</hi> in two Centuries, with the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical touchſtone, written in Italian by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Roman <hi>Trajano Bocalini,</hi> and Engliſhed by the Honourable Earl of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> the Third Edition, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucans Pharſalia,</hi> or the Civil Warrs of <hi>Rome,</hi> between <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, and <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> by <hi>Thomas May,</hi> Eſq; in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:100"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juvenals</hi> ſixteen Satyrs, or a Survey of the manners and Actions of Mankind, with Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Notes, and Annotations, clearing the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure places out of the Hiſtory, Laws and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the <hi>Romans,</hi> by Sir <hi>Robert Stapleton</hi> Knight, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Paſſion of <hi>Dido</hi> for <hi>Eneas,</hi> as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably expreſt in the fourth Book of <hi>Virgil,</hi> Tranſlated by <hi>Edward Waller,</hi> Eſq; in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Rape of <hi>Lucreece,</hi> committed by <hi>Tarquin</hi> the ſixth, and the remarkable judgments that befel him for it, by that incomparable Maſter of our <hi>Engliſh Poetry Will. Shakeſpear,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Europae Modernae ſpeculum,</hi> or a view of the Empires, Kingdoms, Principalities, Seignieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Common wealths of <hi>Europe,</hi> in their Government, Policy, different Intereſt and mutual aſpect one towards another, from the Treaty at <hi>Munster,</hi> 1648, to this preſent year, by <hi>J. H.</hi> Gent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Olor Iſcanus,</hi> or a Collection of ſome ſelect Poems and Tranſlations, written by <hi>Henry Vaughan</hi> Siluriſt, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The life of <hi>Adam,</hi> written in <hi>Italian</hi> by <hi>Gio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanno Franciſco Loredano</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> Noble man, and rendred into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>J. S.</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Men-miracles</hi> with other Poems, by Mr. <hi>Lluellin</hi> Student of Chriſts Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>State worthies, or the States-men and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites of <hi>England,</hi> ſince the Reformation, their Prudence and Policies, Succeſſes and Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, Advancements and Falls, during the Reigns of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th. Edward</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97616:101"/>and King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, by <hi>D. L.</hi> Mr. of Arts, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Poems by <hi>Thomas Stanley</hi> Eſq; Author of the Hiſtory of Philoſophy, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Tryal of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, with a Catalogue of the names of ſuch as ſate as Judges. with His Majeſties Reaſons againſt their uſurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power, and his laſt Speech at his Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Regale Lectum Miſeriae,</hi> or a Kingly bed of Miſery, in which is contained a dream, with an Elegy upon the Martyrdom of <hi>Charles</hi> late King of <hi>England</hi> of bleſſed Memory, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> with a curſe againſt the enemies of Peace, and the Authors farewel to <hi>England,</hi> by <hi>John Quarles,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The new help to diſcourſe, or Wit, Mirth and Jollity intermixt with more ſerious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, conſiſting of pleaſant Aſtrological Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomical, Philoſophical, Grammatical, Phyſical, Chirurgical, Hiſtorical, Moral and Poetical Queſtions and Anſwers, with ſeveral other va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties intermixt, together with the Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Guide, by <hi>W. W.</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Academy of Complements with new Additions of Songs and Catches, <hi>a la mode,</hi> ſtored with variety of Complemental and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Expreſſions; alſo witty and ingenious Dialogues and Diſcourſes, with ſignificant Letters upon ſeveral Occaſions.</p>
               <p>A new ſet of Cuts for the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in 4to. price 10 <hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With ſeveral other School-books Printed at the <hi>Theater,</hi> and beyond the Seas. Sold by <hi>Peter Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> at the <hi>Leg</hi> and <hi>Star</hi> over againſt the Royal Exchange in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97616:101"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
